<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Annotated Masterlist</title>
            <author>Victoria Myers</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>2010-07-01</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt/>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Converted from a Word document </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <appInfo>
            <application ident="TEI_fromDOCX" version="2.15.0">
               <label>DOCX to TEI</label>
            </application>
         </appInfo>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>$LastChangedDate: 2010-07-01T16:07:51Z$</date>
            <name>Victoria Myers</name>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">Annotated Titles Masterlist  <date when="1803">1803-1808</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated Titles  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1376">
                  <seg type="reference">Speght (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-03.html">1803-01-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Speght, Thomas (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <author>Lydgate, John (Siege of Thebes)</author>  
                  <title>The workes of our ancient and learned English poet, Geffrey Chaucer, newly printed. In this impression you shall find these additions: 1. His portraiture and progenie shewed. 2. His life collected. 3. Arguments to euery booke gathered. 4. Old and obscure words explaned. 5. Authors by him cited, declared. 6. Difficulties opened. 7. Two bookes of his, neuer before printed.</title>  
                  <date when="1598">1598</date>
                  <lb/>AND/OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Speght, Thomas (editor, author of the Life of Chaucer)</author>  
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <author>Lydgate, John (Siege of Thebes)</author>  
                  <title>The works of our ancient, learned, [and] excellent English poet, Jeffrey Chaucer: as they have lately been compar’d with the best manuscripts; and several things added, never before in print. To which is adjoyn’d, the story of the siege of Thebes, by John Lidgate, monk of Bury, together with the life of Chaucer, shewing his countrey, parentage, education, marriage, children, revenues, society, reward, friends, books, death. Also a table, wherein the old and obscure words in Chaucer are explained, and such words (which are many) that either are, by nature or derivation, Arabick, Greek, Latine, Italian, French, Dutch or Saxon, mark’d with particular notes for the better understanding their original.</title>  
                  <date when="1687">1687</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Speght, Edition of Chaucer,  <date when="1597">1597</date> (1:3).<lb/>Speght, Life of Chaucer; his friends (2:339).<lb/>Speght: Additions to the Life of Chaucer: his books (2:402).<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Chaucer’s Works, with Life by Speght, portrait  <date when="1687">1687</date> (item 430).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1377">
                  <seg type="reference">St Francis (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-11.html">1803-01-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Bonaventure, Saint</author>  
                  <title>La vita del glorioso seraphico pa[t]re messer San Francesco.</title>  
                  <date when="1477">1477</date>
                  <lb/>In English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Bonaventure, Saint</author>  
                  <author>Browne, Anthony Maria, viscount Montagu (translator)</author>  
                  <title>The life of the holie father S. Francis, Writen by Saint Bonauenture, and as it is related by the Reuerend Father Aloysius Lipomanus Bishop of Vern. In his fourth tome of the life of Saintes.</title>  
                  <date when="1610">1610</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>S. Bonaventure’s Life and Litanies of St. Francis, transl. at Cowdray, by Anthony Brown, Second Viscount Montague, and dedicated to Lady Winefred Englefield, Doway,  <date when="1635">1635</date> (item 68).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1378">
                  <seg type="reference">Tower, Patent Rolls (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-16.html">1803-01-16</ref>)
                    </seg>WC records receiving a letter from Samuel Ayscough ( <date when="1745">1745-1804</date>) to Sir Henry Ellis ( <date when="1777">1777-1869</date>) on  <date when="1800">1800-08</date>-18, re: ‘preparation for the press of the Account of Patent Rolls in the Tower.’<lb/>See WG’s biography of Chaucer  <date when="1804">1804</date> edition, 2 vols. (1:387).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1379">
                  <seg type="reference">Cotton (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-17.html">1803-01-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cotton, sir Robert (compiler; attributed to)</author>  
                  <author>Bowyer, William (compiler; more likely)</author>  
                  <author>Bowyer, Robert (comp; more likely)</author>  
                  <author>Prynne, William (comp.)</author>  
                  <title>An exact abridgement of the records in the Tower of London, from the reign of King Edward the Second, unto King Richard the Third, of all the Parliaments holden in each kings reign, and the several accounts in every Parliament: together with the names and titles of all the dukes, marquesses, earls, viscounts, and barons, summoned to every of the said Parliaments.  Collected by Sir Robert Cotton Knight and baronet. Revised, rectified in sundry mistakes, and supplied with a preface, marginal notes, several omissions, and exact tables, both of the special matters, great officers speakers, nobles, and other persons therein conteined. By William Prynne Esquire, a bencher of Lincolns Inne.</title>  
                  <date when="1657">1657</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/>WG may have consulted the manuscript book:<lb/> 
                  <author>Cotton, sir Robert (compiler; attributed to)</author>  
                  <author>Bowyer, William (compiler; more likely)</author>  
                  <author>Bowyer, Robert (comp; more likely)</author>  
                  <author>Prynne, William (comp.)</author>  
                  <title>The Cottonian manuscripts</title>  
                  <title>‘An Exact abridgement of the records in the Tower of London from the raigne of King Edward the Second unto King Richard the Third, of all the Parliam-ts holden in each kings raigne and the seueral acts in euery Parliament togeather with the names &amp; titles of all the dukes, marquesses, earles, viscounts, and barrons sommoned to euery of the sayd Parliam-ts.’</title> between  <date when="1618">1618</date> and  <date when="1630">1630</date> written in England in secretary hand, with engraved portraits.<lb/>OR<lb/>The Cottonian manuscripts from Robert Cotton’s Library, transferred to the British Museum in  <date when="1757">1757</date>.  Now held as the Medieval literary and historical manuscripts in the Cotton collection, British Library, London [ca.  <date when="1150">1150</date>-ca.  <date when="1450">1450</date>]<lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Cotton, Abridgement of Records, apud Hume, chap. 16 (1:18).<lb/>‘a collection of Mysteries performed at Coventry … Among the Cottonian manuscripts in <lb/>the British Museum’ (1:85).<lb/>Cottonian MSS, apud Strutt (1:98).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1380">
                  <seg type="reference">Gower, çala (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-20.html">1803-01-20</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Gower, John</author>  
                  <title>De confessione amantis.</title>  
                  <date when="1532">1532</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/>‘Gower’<lb/> in <title>Biographia Britannica: or, The lives of the most eminent persons who have flourished in Great Britain and Ireland, from the earliest ages, down to the present times: collected from the best authorites, both printed and manuscript, and digested in the manner of Mr Bayle’s historical and critical dictionary. …</title> (7 volumes)  <date when="1747">1747-1766</date>
                  <lb/>(According to the second edition, the compilers were Henry Brougham, Dr. John Campbell, William Harris, Philip Morant, William Oldys, and Mr. Hinton.)<lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>‘manuscript dedication of an improved copy of the Vox Clamantis, to Arundel archbishop of Canterbury … MSS. Oxon. in coll. Omn. Animarum, No. 26, apud Bio. Britan. art. Gower (1:336).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1381">
                  <seg type="reference">Mss (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-21.html">1803-01-21</ref>)
                    </seg> WG visits the British Museum on  <date when="1803">1803-01</date>-21.  According to other diary entries, the manuscripts he consults during his work on the <title>Life of Chaucer</title> include: Cottonian manuscripts, see <date when="1803">1803-01</date>-17.<lb/>Rymer manuscripts, see  <date when="1803">1803-01</date>-31.<lb/>Harleian manuscripts as follows:<lb/>Possibly (among others):<lb/> 
                  <author>Harley, Edward, earl of Oxford</author>  
                  <author>Oldys, William (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The Harleian miscellany or, a collection of scarce, curious, and entertaining pamphlets and tracts, as well in manuscripts as in print, found in the late Earl of Oxford’s library; interspersed with historical, political, and critical notes.</title>  (8 volumes)  <date when="1774">1774</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1382">
                  <seg type="reference">Caxton, &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-26.html">1803-01-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <title>Canterbury tales.</title> first printed by Caxton  <date when="1477">1477-8</date>
                  <lb/>and in an improved second edition by Caxton in  <date when="1483">1483</date>
                  <lb/>OR <lb/> 
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <title>Troilus and Criseyde.</title> composed c.  <date when="1380">1380-2</date>, first printed by Caxton  <date when="1484">1484</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Ames, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Typographical antiquities, being an historical account of printing in England: with some memoirs of our ancient printers, and a register of the books printed by them, from the year  <date when="1471">1471</date> to the year  <date when="1600">1600</date>. With an appendix concerning printing in Scotland and Ireland to the same time.</title>  
                  <date when="1749">1749</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Caxton, Edition of Chaucer, apud Ames’s Typographical Antiquities (1:1).<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Ames’s Typographical Antiquities, augmented by Herbert, plates, 3 vol.  <date when="1785">1785-90</date> (item 325).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1383">
                  <seg type="reference">Anstis, &amp;c. (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-28.html">1803-01-28</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Anstis, John (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Aldrich, Robert (compiler)</author>  
                  <title>The Register of the most noble Order of the Garter, from its cover in black velvet, usually called the black book, with notes placed at the bottom of the pages, and an introduction prefixed by the editor. In two volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1724">1724</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Anstis, Register of the Garter, vol. I (1:343).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1384">
                  <seg type="reference">Rymer’s MSS (<ref target="/diary/1803-01-31.html">1803-01-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/>Papers of Thomas Rymer in a collection relating to the history and government of England, made for his ‘Foedera,’ published as follows:<lb/> 
                  <author>Rymer, Thomas</author>  
                  <author>Sanderson, Robert (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Foedera, conventiones, literae, et cujuscunque, generis acta publica, inter reges Angliae, et alios quosvis imperatores, reges, pontifices, principes, vel communitates, ab ineunte saecula duodecimo, viz: ab anno  <date when="1101">1101</date>, ad nostra usque tempora, habita aut tractata, ex autographis infra secretiores archivorum regiorum thesaurarias et per multa saecula reconditis, fidelitor excripta. Ex schedis Thoma Rymer postissium edidit Robertus Sanderson, Tomus 16.</title>  
                  <date when="1615">1615</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Rymer, Foedera, Tom. XI, 9 Edv. 4, Apr. 24 (1:60).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1385">
                  <seg type="reference">Mongitore (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-08.html">1803-02-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Mongitore, Antonio</author>  
                  <title>Bibliotheca sicula sive de scriptoribus siculis qui tum vetera, tun recentiora saecula illustrant, notitiae locvpletissimae … Accessit apparatus praeliminaris operi praevius, complectens sicanae, siculorum ingenio, et literis, et de computo Olympiadum.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1707">1707-1714</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Mongitore, Bibliotheca Sicula (1:382).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1386">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Vossius (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-08.html">1803-02-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Vossius, Gerardus Joannes</author>  
                  <title>Gerardi Joannis Vossii De historicis latinis libri tres.</title>  
                  <date when="1627">1627</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>G.J. Vossius De Historicis Latinis, Lib. II, Cap. lx (1:382).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1387">
                  <seg type="reference">Avesbury (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-10.html">1803-02-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Robert, of Avesbury</author>  
                  <title>Roberti de Avesbury Historia de mirabilibus gestis Eduardi III. Accedunt, (1.) Libri Saxonici, qui ad manus Joannis Joscelini venerunt. (2.) Nomina eorum, qui scripserunt historiam gentis Anglorum, et ubi exstant; per Joannem Joscelinum. E codicibus MSS. descripsit ediditque Tho. Hearnius; qui &amp; appendicem subnexuit. </title>  
                  <date when="1720">1720</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Avesbury, De Mirabilibus Gestis Edv. III ad ann. Hollinshed, &amp;c<lb/>(1:420)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1388">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Hector Boethius (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-10.html">1803-02-10</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Boethius, Hector</author>  
                  <title>Scotorum historiae: a prima gentis origine, cum aliarum &amp; rerum &amp; gentium illustratione non vulgari: prae missa epistola nucupatoria [sic] tabellisque amplissimus, &amp; non poenitenda Isagoge quae ab buus tergo explicabuntur diffusus.</title>  
                  <date when="1526">1526</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Hector Boethius, Lib. XV, ad ann. Barnes (1:421).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1389">
                  <seg type="reference">Villani (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-11.html">1803-02-11</ref>)
                    </seg>WG could be reading the same item that he reads on  <date when="1802">1802-11</date>-26:<lb/> 
                  <author>Villani, Giovanni</author>  
                  <author>Fasolo, Giacomo (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Croniche di Messer Giovanni Villani: nelle quali si tratta dell’origine di Firenze, &amp; di tutti e fatti &amp; guerre state fatte da Fiorentini nella Italia, &amp; nelle quali anchora fa mentione dal principio del mondo infino al tempo dell’ autore di tutte le guerre state per il modo, cosi de principi christiani fraloro, come de gli infedeli, &amp; de christiani congli infedeli. Historia nuoua &amp; utile a sapere le cose passate fatte per futto l’universo.</title>  
                  <date when="1537">1537</date>
                  <lb/>Republished with the second part continued by Villani’s brother Matteo:<lb/> 
                  <title>Cronica universale de suoi tempi … Nuovamente uscita in luce.</title>  
                  <date when="1554">1554</date>
                  <lb/>The first ten books by Giovanni constitute part 1; books 11-13 constitute part 2.<lb/>OR<lb/>WG may be reading the further continuation:<lb/> 
                  <author>Villani, Filippo</author>  
                  <title>Della historia di Matteo Villani cittadino Fiorentino. Li tre vltimi libri: che son’ il resto dell’ istoria scritta da lui, che nelli stampati sino ad’hora mancano; con vn’ aggiunto di Filippo Villani suo figliuolo, ch’arriua sino all’anno  <date when="1364">1364</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1577">1577</date>
                  <lb/>WG cites the following in his biography of Chaucer:<lb/>Gio. Villani, Cronica, Lib XII (1:256). <lb/>Matteo Villani, Lib. I ‘supplement to [his brother’s work] (1:256).<lb/>Filippo Villani, Lib. XI (1:474).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1390">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Duchesne (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-11.html">1803-02-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>du Chesne, André</author>  
                  <title>Histoire generale, d’Angleterre, d’Escosse, et d’Irlande, contenant les choses memorables &amp; remarquables auenuës aux isles &amp; royaumes de la Grande Bretagne, d’Irlande, de Man &amp; autres adjacentes: durant seize cents années, &amp; plus, tant de la domination des anciens Bretons &amp; Romains, que souz les regnes des Saxons, Anglois, Pictes, Escossois, Irlandois, Danois, et Normans. Iusques a Iacques I. roy d’Angleterre, d’Escosse, &amp; d’Irlande, aujourd’huy regnant. Ensemble l’estat et succes des affaires des Anglois en France, Syrie, Castille, Portugal, Gallice, et autres provinces etrangeres. Le tout fedellement recueilly par Andre du Chesne, Tourangeau.</title>  
                  <date when="1614">1614</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Duchesne, Histoire d’Angleterre, Liv. XV (1:460).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1391">
                  <seg type="reference">Regnier (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-12.html">1803-02-12</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work by Regnier.  WG may have read an item in a collection of his works.  The collection cited in WG’s biography of Chaucer is the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Régnier, Mathurin</author>  
                  <title>Oeuvres de Régnier, … Nouvelle édition, considérablement augmentée.</title>  
                  <date when="1780">1780</date>
                  <lb/> The earliest edition of the <title>Oeuvres</title> was published in  <date when="1730">1730</date>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1392">
                  <seg type="reference">Fabian (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-14.html">1803-02-14</ref>)
                    </seg>Most likely:<lb/> 
                  <author>Fabyan, Robert</author>  
                  <title>Fabyan’s cronycle newly prynted, wyth the cronycle, actes, and dedes done in the tyme of the reygne of the most excellent prynce kynge Henry the vii. father vnto our most drad souerayne lord Kynge Henry the viii. To whom be all honour, reue[n]ce, and ioyfull contynaunce of his prosperous reygne, to the pleasure of god and weale of this his realme amen.</title>  
                  <date when="1533">1533</date>
                  <lb/> In his biography of Chaucer, WG refers to Fabian in a note concerning the death of Richard II: ‘The first author, who mentions the tale of his [Richard’s] being murdered by eight assassins, is Fabian.  He however coolly affirms of this story, that it is what “of moste wryters is testyfied and alleged”’ (Godwin’s <title>Life of Chaucer</title> 2:552). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1393">
                  <seg type="reference">duchess Blanche (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-15.html">1803-02-15</ref>)
                    </seg>It is likely that WG is consulting certain documents mentioned in his biography of Chaucer, where he has a note concerning the age of Blanche at the time of her marriage:<lb/> ‘In the <title>Inquisitio post Mortem</title> taken at the decease of duke Henry, her father (Esc. 35 E. 3, p. 1, n. 122,) the lady Blanche, married to John earl of Richmond, is stated to be xviij years old and upward … and the lady Matilda, the other sister and coheiress, who is named after Blanche, married to William earl of Holland, is said to be xx years old and upward.  In the Fine Rolls of the same year, 35 E. 3, m. 23, there is a writ in behalf of the earl and countess of Richmond, dated at Henley, 16 July, in which she is stated to be of full age and to have issue, and in consequence of this she and her husband receive, with the consent of her sister, a certain portion of duke Henry’s inheritance, which before had been reserved.  … In these records therefore we see the lady Blanche stated, in the same year, and with the interval of a very few months, as eighteen, and as twenty-one, years of age.  The last statement however is confirmed by the <title>Inquisitio post Mortem</title>, Esc. 36 E. 3, p. 1, n. 37, taken at the decease of Matilda, her sister, there styled the wife of William duke of Bavaria, in the following year’ (<title>Life of Chaucer</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date> edition, volume 1, note a, pp. 412-413). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1394">
                  <seg type="reference">Herald’s College, Townsend (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-15.html">1803-02-15</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly WG refers to:<lb/> 
                  <author>College of Arms (of Great Britain)</author>  
                  <title>A general registry of births, kept at the Heralds Office on St. Bennet’s Hill near St. Paul’s, London.</title>  
                  <date when="1747">1747</date>
                  <lb/>OR personally consults:<lb/> 
                  <author>Townsend, Francis, esq.</author>, Windsor Herald in his Majesty’s College of Arms,   who aided WG in obtaining a copy of a document referred to in ‘the Life of Chaucer prefixed to Urry’s edition of his works,’ a document which according to WG would question the received date for Chaucer’s birth:  ‘a roll in a cause of chivalry between [sir Richard le] Scrope and [sir Richard] Grosvenour, 10 R. 2. communicated to Mr. Urry by John Anstis Esq; Garter Principal King at Arms’ (Urry, qtd. in WG’s <title>Life of Chaucer </title> 
                  <date when="1804">1804</date> edition, colume 1, xix-xx). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1395">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Dallaway (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-15.html">1803-02-15</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>James Dallaway (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Montague, Mary Wortley, Lady</author>  
                  <title>The works of the Right Honourable Lady Mary Wortley Montague: includes her correspondence, poems, and essays, published by permission, from her genuine papers.</title> (5 volumes)  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1396">
                  <seg type="reference">Bavaria (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-17.html">1803-02-17</ref>)
                    </seg>WG may be referring to the discrepancy he discovered in reports of the marriage of Matilda, eldest daughter of Henry duke of Lancaster. In his biography of Chaucer, he includes the following note:<lb/> ‘In the <title>Inquisitio post Mortem</title> taken at the decease of duke Henry, her father, (Esc. 35 E. 3, p. 1, n. 122),’ she is reported married to William earl of Holland,’ but in the <title>Inquisitio post Mortem</title>, Esc. 36 E. 3, p. 1, n. 37, taken at the decease of Matilda,’ she is called ‘the wife of William duke of Bavaria.’ (<title>Life of Chaucer</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date> edition, volume 1, note a, pp. 412-413). </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1397">
                  <seg type="reference">Aventinus (<ref target="/diary/1803-02-22.html">1803-02-22</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Aventinus, Johannes</author>  Unable to identify specific work; Aventinus was author of many chronicles and annals, as well as a <title>Rudimenta grammaticae</title>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1398">
                  <seg type="reference">Statutes, &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1803-03-16.html">1803-03-16</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Ashmole, Elias</author>  
                  <author>Hollar, Wenceslaus</author>  
                  <author>Sherwin, William</author>  
                  <title>The institution, laws &amp; ceremonies of the most noble Order of the Garter. Collected and digested into one body by Elias Ashmole of the Middle Temple Esq: Windesor Herald at Arms. A work furnished with variety of matter, relating to honor and nobleese [sic]. </title>  
                  <date when="1672">1672</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Statutes of Institution, apud Ashmole, Institution of the Garter, Appendix (1:258).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1399">
                  <seg type="reference">Petrarca (<ref target="/diary/1803-03-17.html">1803-03-17</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Petrarca, Francesco</author>  
                  <author>Manilius, Sebastianus (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Epistolae familiares</title>.  <date when="1492">1492</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Petrarca’s Epistolae, apud Vie de Petrarque, tome I (1:5).<lb/>De Sade, Vie de Petrarque, Tom II (1:218).<lb/>De Sade, Memoires pour la Vie de Petrarque, T. III (1:268).<lb/>Petrarca letter to Boccaccio 8 June  <date when="1373">1373</date> – in De Obedientia et Fide Uxoria: Opera, Ed. <lb/>Bas.  <date when="1581">1581</date>, Tom. I, sub finem (2:148).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1400">
                  <seg type="reference">House of Fame (<ref target="/diary/1803-03-24.html">1803-03-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <title>The house of fame.</title>  
                  <date when="1483">1483</date> printed by William Caxton<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1401">
                  <seg type="reference">Pope, do. (<ref target="/diary/1803-03-24.html">1803-03-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Pope, Alexander</author>  
                  <title>The temple of fame: a vision.</title>  
                  <date when="1715">1715</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1402">
                  <seg type="reference">Rymer, çala (<ref target="/diary/1803-04-20.html">1803-04-20</ref>)
                    </seg>Could be item #933 or # <date when="1384">1384</date>:<lb/> 
                  <author>Rymer, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The tragedies of the last age, consider’d and examin’d by the practice of the ancients, and by the common sense of all ages, in a letter to Fleetwood Shepheard, Esq.</title>  
                  <date when="1678">1678</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Rymer’s (T.) Tragedies of the last Age Examined, and Short View of Tragedy, with Reflections on Shakespeare  <date when="1692">1692-93</date> (item 636).<lb/>OR<lb/>Papers of Thomas Rymer in a collection relating to the history and government of England, made for his ‘Foedera,’ published as follows:<lb/> 
                  <author>Rymer, Thomas</author>  
                  <author>Sanderson, Robert (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Foedera, conventiones, literae, et cujuscunque, generis acta publica, inter reges Angliae, et alios quosvis imperatores, reges, pontifices, principes, vel communitates, ab ineunte saecula duodecimo, viz: ab anno  <date when="1101">1101</date>, ad nostra usque tempora, habita aut tractata, ex autographis infra secretiores archivorum regiorum thesaurarias et per multa saecula reconditis, fidelitor excripta. Ex schedis Thoma Rymer postissium edidit Robertus Sanderson, Tomus 16.</title>  
                  <date when="1615">1615</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Rymer, Foedera, Tom. XI, 9 Edv. 4, Apr. 24 (1:60).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1403">
                  <seg type="reference">Burke (<ref target="/diary/1803-04-29.html">1803-04-29</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Burke, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>Reflections on the revolution in France, and on the proceedings in certain societies in London relative to that event.</title>  
                  <date when="1790">1790</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Edmund Burke’s Reflections on the Revolution in France (2: 286n).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1404">
                  <seg type="reference">Walsingham (<ref target="/diary/1803-05-04.html">1803-05-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walsingham, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Historia brevis Thomae Walsingham, ab Edwardo primo, ad Henricum quintum.</title>  
                  <date when="1574">1574</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Walsingham, Historia Brevis, ad ann. (1:123).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1405">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; M U History (<ref target="/diary/1803-05-05.html">1803-05-05</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1406">
                  <seg type="reference">Acad. des Inscriptions (<ref target="/diary/1803-05-18.html">1803-05-18</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Grosley, Pierre Jean</author>  
                  <author>Lefèvre, André</author>  
                  <title>Memoires de l’Academie des sciences, inscriptions, belles lettres, [b]eaux arts, &amp;c., nouvellement établie à Troyes en Champagne.</title>  
                  <date when="1744">1744</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Memoires de l’Académie des Inscriptions (2: 354)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1407">
                  <seg type="reference">Good Women (<ref target="/diary/1803-05-19.html">1803-05-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <author>Thynne, William (editor)</author> ‘The legende of good women’<lb/> in <title>The workes of Geoffray Chaucer newly printed, with dyuers workes whiche were neuer in print before: as in the table more playnly dothe appere.</title>  
                  <date when="1532">1532</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1408">
                  <seg type="reference">Alexander the Great (<ref target="/diary/1803-05-20.html">1803-05-20</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1409">
                  <seg type="reference">Pasquier (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-06.html">1803-06-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Pasquier, Étienne</author>  
                  <title>Des recherches de la France, livre premier. Plus, un pourparler du prince. Le tout par Etienne Pasquier…</title>.  <date when="1560">1560</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Pasquier, Recherches de la France (2: 303).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1410">
                  <seg type="reference">Caylus (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-10.html">1803-06-10</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Caylus, Anne Claude Philippe, comte de</author> Unable to identify specific work by this writer.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1411">
                  <seg type="reference">Mariana (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-17.html">1803-06-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Mariana, Ioannes</author>  
                  <title>Historia de rebus Hispaniae libri XX.</title>  
                  <date when="1592">1592</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Mariana, De Rebus Hispaniae, Lib. XVIII. cap. v. (2: 327).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1413">
                  <seg type="reference">Moreri (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-24.html">1803-06-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Moreri, Louis</author>  
                  <title>Le grand dictionnaire historique, ou Le mélange curieux de l’histoire sainte et profane … par le Dr. L. Moreri …</title>  
                  <date when="1674">1674</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites: <lb/>Moreri, Dictionnaire, art. Du Bartas (2: 38).<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Moreri (Louis) Grand Dictionnaire Historique, avec Supplement, 6 vol. in 3 Amst.  <date when="1717">1717</date> (item 868).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1414">
                  <seg type="reference">Gough (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-27.html">1803-06-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Gough, Richard</author>  
                  <title>Sepulchral monuments in Great Britain: applied to illustrate the history of families, manners, habits and arts, at the different periods from the Norman conquest to the seventeenth century. With introductory observations…</title>(2 volumes in 3)  <date when="1786">1786-1796</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Gough’s Sepulchral Monuments (1:487).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1415">
                  <seg type="reference">Ellis (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-28.html">1803-06-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Ellis, George (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Specimens of the early English poets.</title>  
                  <date when="1790">1790</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/>Godwin may be meeting Ellis at the British Museum.  For example, see  <date when="1803">1803-07</date>-16 <lb/>and  <date when="1803">1803-09</date>-16.<lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/> Ellis’s Specimens of the Early English poets (1: xii).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1416">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Ritson (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-28.html">1803-06-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Ritson, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Cursory criticisms on the edition of Shakespeare published by Edward Malone.</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Ritson, Joseph (published anonymously)</author>  
                  <title>Bibliographia poetica: a catalogue of Engleish [sic] poets, of the twelfth, thirteenth, fourteenth, fifteenth and sixteenth centurys with a short account of their works.</title>  
                  <date when="1802">1802</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/>Godwin may be meeting Ritson at the British Museum, as with Ellis on the same date ( <date when="1803">1803-06</date>-28).<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Ritson’s Cursory Criticisms on Malone’s Edition of Shakespeare,  <date when="1792">1792</date> (item 201).<lb/>Ritson’s (J.) Bibliographia Poetica, a Catalogue of English Poets  <date when="1802">1802</date> (item 628).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1418">
                  <seg type="reference">Spelman (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-29.html">1803-06-29</ref>)
                    </seg>Godwin may be consulting Spelman on Tenures, read on  <date when="1801">1801-04</date>-29.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Spelman, Henry, Sir</author>  
                  <author>Stephens, Jeremiah (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Concilia, decreta, leges, constitutiones, in re ecclesiarum orbis Britannici. Viz. Pambritannica, Pananglia, Scotica, Hibernica, Cambrica, Mannica, provincialia, diocesana. Ab initio Christianae ibidem religionis, ad nostram usque aetatem. Uti reperiuntur in eorundem actis, canonibus, ecclesiasticis, regnorum constitutionibus, senatus consultis, principum rescriptis, libris impressis, &amp; antique Mss. in regum etiam priscorum diplomatibus, chartis schedis, &amp; monumentis veteribus, studios congesta. Oper &amp; scrutinis Henrici Spelman, Eq. Aur. Tribus distincta tomis: quorum, primus hic tomus ea continet, quae primis Christi seculis, usque ad introitum Normannorum (id est, an. Dom.  <date when="1066">1066</date>.) habita sunt &amp; celebrata</title>.  <date when="1639">1639</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Spelman, Henry, Sir</author>  
                  <title>Henrici Spelmanni Equit. Anglo-Brit. Archaeologus: In modum glossarii ad rem antiquam posteriorem contentis. Latino-barbara, peregrina, obsoleta, et nouatae significationis vocabula, quae post labefactatas à Gothis Vandalisq[ue] res Europaeas, in ecclesiasticis profanisq[ue] scriptoribus; variarum item gentium legibus antiquis, chartis et formulis occurrunt. Scholiis et commentariis illvstrata, in quibus prisci ritus quám plurimi, magistratus dignitates, monera, officia, mores, leges, et consuetudines enerrantur.</title>  
                  <date when="1626">1626</date>
                  <lb/>(first part A-L only; 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> part appeared in  <date when="1664">1664</date>)<lb/>WG cites the following works in his biography of Chaucer:<lb/>Spelman, Gloss. sub voc. Foresta (1:113).<lb/>Spelman, Concilia, ad. ann. (2:388)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1419">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Wake (<ref target="/diary/1803-06-29.html">1803-06-29</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1420">
                  <seg type="reference">Pierce Plowman (<ref target="/diary/1803-07-06.html">1803-07-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Langland, William</author>  
                  <title>The vision of Pierce Plowman, now fyrste imprynted by Roberte Crowley, dwellyng in Ely rentes in Holburne. Anno Domine  <date when="1505">1505</date>.  <date when="1550">1550</date>. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</title>  
                  <date when="1550">1550</date> 1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> ed. London: Roberte Crowley<lb/>‘The date  <date when="1505">1505</date>, evidently a misprint for  <date when="1550">1550</date>, is partly blotted out on the t.p., and  <date when="1550">1550</date> printed below.’ ‘Authorship much disputed.’ (WC)<lb/>WG may be reading the edition below (See  <date when="1803">1803-07</date>-18 where WG is reading Proofs of Plowman.):<lb/> 
                  <author>Langland, William</author>  
                  <author>Tyrwhit, Thomas (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The Vision of Pierce Plowman, now fyrste imprynted by R. Crowley, etc. [Attributed to William Langland.] B.L. MS. notes [by T. Tyrwhit].</title>  
                  <date when="1550">1550</date>
                  <lb/>‘The date has been corrected in MS. to  <date when="1505">1505</date>.’<lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Tyrwhit vs Spenser on Pierce Plowman (2:402-3)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1421">
                  <seg type="reference">Throsby (<ref target="/diary/1803-07-08.html">1803-07-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Throsby, John</author>  
                  <title>Select views in Leicestershire, from original drawings: containing seats of the nobility and gentry, town views and ruins, accompanied with description and historical relations. By J. Throsby.</title>  
                  <date when="1789">1789</date>
                  <lb/>AND/OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Throsby, John</author>  
                  <title>The supplementary volume to the Leicestershire views: containing a series of excursions in the year  <date when="1790">1790</date>, to the villages and places of note in the county. By John Throsby. To which are added, in notes, the most valuable parts of Burton, Nichols, and other antecedent writers on Leicesteshire.</title>  
                  <date when="1790">1790</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Throsby, Supplementary Volume to Views in Leicestershire: art. Ratby (2: 399).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1422">
                  <seg type="reference">Gregory Blunt, çala (<ref target="/diary/1803-08-22.html">1803-08-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Blunt, Gregory</author>  
                  <title>Six more letters to Granville Sharp, Esq. on his remarks upon the use of the article in the Greek Testament. By Gregory Blunt.</title>  
                  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1423">
                  <seg type="reference">Parl. History (<ref target="/diary/1803-08-24.html">1803-08-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <title>Parliamentary or constitutional history of England; being a faithful account of all the most remarkable transactions in Parliament from the earliest times. Collected from the journals of both houses, the records, original manuscripts, scarce speeches and tracts; all compared with the several cotemporary writers, and connected throughout, with the history of the times. By several hands.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751-61</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1424">
                  <seg type="reference">Hall (<ref target="/diary/1803-09-01.html">1803-09-01</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Hall’s (Jos.) Virgidemiarum; Satires, in six books  <date when="1597">1597</date>, rep. Oxford,  <date when="1753">1753</date> (item 260).<lb/>Hall’s Characters of Vertues and Vices, in two bookes,  <date when="1608">1608</date>—Epistles, 3 vol.  <date when="1608">1608-11</date>, with duplicates of the first 2 vol. (item 261).<lb/>Hall’s Epistles, vol. 1  <date when="1608">1608</date> (item 262).<lb/>Hall’s Old Religion, or True State of the Difference between the Reformed and Roman Church  <date when="1628">1628</date> (item 263).<lb/>Hall’s Occasional Meditations, set forth by R. Hall, second edition  <date when="1631">1631</date> (item 264).<lb/>Hall’s Occational Meditations, with additions, third edit.  <date when="1633">1633</date> (item 265).<lb/>Hall’s Christian Moderation, in two bookes  <date when="1640">1640</date> (item 266).<lb/>Hall’s Great Mystery of Godliness  <date when="1652">1652</date> (item 267).<lb/>Hall’s (J. of Durham) Horae Vacivae, or Essays  <date when="1646">1646</date> (item 268).<lb/>Hall’s Chronicle, black letter, imperfect, no date (item 835).<lb/>The above are identified more fully as follows:<lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Virgidemiarum: sixe bookes: First three bookes, of toothlesse satyrs; the three last bookes, of byting satyres.</title>  
                  <date when="1597">1597</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Characters of vertves and vices. In two bookes.</title>  
                  <date when="1608">1608</date> 
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Epistles.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1608">1608-1611</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>The olde religion: a treatise, wherin is laid downe the true state of the difference betwixt the reformed, and Romane Church; and the blame of this schisme is cast vpon the true authors. Seruing for the vindication of our innocence, for the setling of wauering minds for a preseruatiue against Popish insinuations.</title>  
                  <date when="1628">1628</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Occasional meditations.</title>  
                  <date when="1630">1630</date>  
                  <lb/> 
                  <date when="1631">1631</date> 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition<lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <author>Hall, Robert (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Occasional meditations by Jos. Exon. Set forth by Richard Hawkings. The third edition: with the addition of 49. meditations not heretofore published. </title>  
                  <date when="1633">1633</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>Christian moderation. In two books. By Jos: Exon.</title>  
                  <date when="1640">1640</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>The great mystery of godliness, laid forth by way of affectuous and feeling meditation: also the invisible world, discovered to spirituell eyes, and reduced to usefull meditation. In three books. By Jos. Hall, D. D. B. Norwich</title>  
                  <date when="1659">1659</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, John</author>  
                  <title>Horae vacivae, or, Essays: Some occasionall considerations by John Hall.</title>  
                  <date when="1646">1646</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Hall, Edward</author>  
                  <author>Grafton, Richard</author>  
                  <title>The union of the two noble and illustre families of Lancastre and Yorke, beyng long in continuall discension for the croune of this noble realme, with al the actes done in both the tymes of the princes, both of the one linage and of the other, beginnyng at the tyme of king Henry the fowerth, the first aucthor of this deuision, and so succssiuely proceading to the reigne of the high and prudent prince king Henry the eyght, the indubitate flower and very heire of both the saied linages. Whereunto is added to euery kyng a seuerall table.</title>  
                  <date when="1548">1548</date> 
                  <lb/>Uniform title: Hall’s chronicle.<lb/>‘Hall’s work ended with  <date when="1532">1532</date> . . . continued to the death of Henry VIII from Hall’s notes by Richard Grafton.’<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1425">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Speed (<ref target="/diary/1803-09-01.html">1803-09-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Speed, John</author>  
                  <title>The history of Great Britaine under the conquests of ye Romans, Saxons, Danes and Normans. Their originals, manners, warres, coines &amp; seales: with ye successions, lives, acts &amp; issues of the English monarchs from Iulius Caesar, to our most gracious soueraigne King Iames. by Iohn Speed.</title>  
                  <date when="1611">1611</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Speed’s Historie of Great Britaine (no date) (item 893)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1426">
                  <seg type="reference">Scroop (<ref target="/diary/1803-09-06.html">1803-09-06</ref>)
                    </seg> In his biography of Chaucer, WG refers to Scrope in a note concerning the death of Richard II: ‘Scrope, archbishop of York, who was beheaded for high treason in  <date when="1405">1405</date>, asserts, in the manifesto in which he announced his rebellion, that Richard perished in consequence of being denied all sustenance, having first endured the miseries of hunger and thirst for fifteen days and nights. (Anglia Sacra, para II, art. 18).  (Godwin’s <title>Life of Chaucer</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date> edition, 2:552). Unable to locate Scrope’s manifesto, but see:<lb/> 
                  <author>Wharton, Henry</author>  
                  <title>Anglia sacra, sive collectio historiarum, partem antiquitus, partem recenter scriptorum, de archiepiscopis et episcopis Angliae, a prima fidei christianae suceptione ad annum MDXL.</title>  
                  <date when="1691">1691</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1427">
                  <seg type="reference">Read Chaucer, p. 98 (<ref target="/diary/1803-09-12.html">1803-09-12</ref>)
                    </seg>WG is reading his manuscript biography of Chaucer, published as:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Life of Geoffrey Chaucer, the early English poet, including memoirs of his near friend and kinsman John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster, with Sketches of the manners, opinions, acts and literature of England in the 14</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title>
                     <seg> </seg>century.</title>  (2 volumes)  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1428">
                  <seg type="reference">Granger (<ref target="/diary/1803-09-15.html">1803-09-15</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Granger, James</author>  
                  <title>A biographical history of England, from Egbert the Great to the Revolution: consisting of characters disposed in different classes, and adapted to a methodical catalogue of engraved British heads. Intended as an essay towards reducing our biography to system, and a help to the knowledge of portraits. Interspersed with variety of anecdotes, and memoirs of a great number of persons. With a preface, shewing the utility of a collection of engraved portraits … By the Rev. J. Granger.</title>  
                  <date when="1769">1769</date>
                  <lb/>A supplement was published in  <date when="1774">1774</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1431">
                  <seg type="reference">Journal &amp; Newspapers – JOURNAL IS A DWROTE; NEWSPAPERS A DTEXT (<ref target="/diary/1803-10-13.html">1803-10-13</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific works.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1432">
                  <seg type="reference">Lofft’s Tragedy (<ref target="/diary/1803-10-21.html">1803-10-21</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1434">
                  <seg type="reference">Belinda, p. 82 (<ref target="/diary/1803-10-29.html">1803-10-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Maria</author>  
                  <title>Belinda. By Maria Edgeworth. In three volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1435">
                  <seg type="reference">Belmour, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-05.html">1803-11-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Damer, Anne Seymour</author>  
                  <title>Belmour: a novel in three volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1436">
                  <seg type="reference">Catullus, Ep. 1, 2, 3, 4 (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-09.html">1803-11-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Catullus, Gaius Valerius (b. 84 B.C.)</author>  
                  <title>Gai Valeri Catulli Veronensis Liber (The Poems of Gaius Valerius Catullus)</title> Date unknown<lb/>WG probably read one of the following editions:<lb/> 
                  <title>Catullus, Tibullus et Propertius, pristino nitori restituti, &amp; ad optima exemplaria emendati: Cum fragmentis C. Gallo inscriptis. A reprint of the Leiden edition of  <date when="1743">1743</date>, edited by Lenglet Dufresnoy.</title>  
                  <date when="1754">1754</date> [1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> edition]<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <title>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius, ex recensione Jo. Antonii Vulpii, cum notis.</title>  
                  <date when="1786">1786</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius Paris, Barbou,  <date when="1754">1754</date> (item 112).<lb/>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius, ex recens. Jo. Ant. Vulpii, 2 tom. in 1 Venet.  <date when="1786">1786</date> (item 113).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1437">
                  <seg type="reference">Charles II, çala (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-13.html">1803-11-13</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te0955">
                  <seg type="reference">Notes for C Burnet, çala. – IGNORE – LEAVE AS DWROTE (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-14.html">1803-11-14</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/> ^ 975. Burnet, çala<lb/> 
                  <date when="1803">1803-11</date>-15<lb/>Possibly C. Burnet, the same as  <date when="1800">1800-11</date>-14.<lb/>Unable to identify.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Burnet, Gilbert</author>  
                  <author>Burnet, Sir Thomas (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Bishop Burnet’s history of his own time.  v. 1 From the restoration of King Charles II, to the settlement of King William and Mary at the revolution.  To which is prefix’d A summary recapitulation of affairs in church and state from King James I to the restoration in the year  <date when="1660">1660</date>.—v. 2 From the revolution to the conclusion of the treaty of peace at Utrecht, in the reign of Queen Anne. To which is added, the author’s life by the editor.  </title>(2 volumes)  <date when="1724">1724-1734</date>
                  <lb/>Read on  <date when="1792">1792-04</date>-30<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1438">
                  <seg type="reference">Beggar Girl, p.60 (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-25.html">1803-11-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Bennett, Mrs.</author>  
                  <title>The beggar girl and her benefactors. In seven volumes. By Mrs. Bennett, …</title>  
                  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1439">
                  <seg type="reference">Lobenstein, p. 33 (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-27.html">1803-11-27</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1440">
                  <seg type="reference">Walpoliana, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1803-11-27.html">1803-11-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walpole, Horace</author>  
                  <author>Pinkerton, John (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Walpoliana.</title>  
                  <date when="1799">1799</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Walpoliana, compiled by Jo. Pinkerton, 2 vol., no date (item 738).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1441">
                  <seg type="reference">Vavasor Griffiths, çala (<ref target="/diary/1803-12-01.html">1803-12-01</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
                  <pb/>Annotated Titles  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1442">
                  <seg type="reference">Misson, 60 pp. (<ref target="/diary/1804-01-07.html">1804-01-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Misson, François Maximilien</author>  
                  <title>Meslange de litérature historique &amp; critique, sur tout ce qui regarde l’état extraordinaire des Cévennois, appellez Camisards.</title>  
                  <date when="1707">1707</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1443">
                  <seg type="reference">Florence, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-01-08.html">1804-01-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following, first recorded on  <date when="1801">1801-01</date>-07:<lb/> 
                  <author>Sale, George (compiler)</author>  
                  <title>The modern part of an universal history, from the earliest account of time. Compiled from original writers, by the authors of the ancient part.</title>  
                  <date when="1759">1759</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1444">
                  <seg type="reference">Adams on Republics, Vol. II, p. 64 (<ref target="/diary/1804-01-14.html">1804-01-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Adams, John</author>  
                  <title>A defence of the constitutions of government of the United States of America.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1787">1787-1788</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <title>The political history of the Italian republics</title> makes up the second and third volumes.   <date when="1787">1787</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1445">
                  <seg type="reference">Read to M J – IGNORE – LEAVE AS DWROTE (<ref target="/diary/1804-01-22.html">1804-01-22</ref>)
                    </seg>WG is probably reading his mss ‘Camilla,’ which he is writing at this time. ‘Camilla’ is the working title for:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Faulkener, A Tragedy</title>.  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1446">
                  <seg type="reference">read to Coleridge – IGNORE – LEAVE AS DWROTE (<ref target="/diary/1804-02-01.html">1804-02-01</ref>)
                    </seg>WG is probably reading his mss ‘Camilla,’ which he is writing at this time. ‘Camilla’ is the working title for:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Faulkener, A Tragedy</title>.  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1447">
                  <seg type="reference">Rousseau, Tom. II, p. 180-262 (<ref target="/diary/1804-02-04.html">1804-02-04</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably Rousseau’s Confessions, read on  <date when="1801">1801-07</date>-20:<lb/>There are several multivolume editions. The earliest is the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Rousseau, Jean Jacques</author>  
                  <author>Mercier, L. S. (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Brizzard, G. (editor)</author>  
                  <author>de l’Aulnaye, F. H. S. (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Les confessions de J.-J. Rousseau</title>  in <title>Oeuvres completes de J. J. Rousseau. Nouv. ed. clasée per ordre de matieres, et ornée de quatre-vingt-dix gravures. t. 23-26.</title>   
                  <date when="1788">1788-93</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Rousseau (J. J.) ses Oeuvres, 17 vol. Londres,  <date when="1782">1782-86</date> (item 633).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1448">
                  <seg type="reference">Petite Ville (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-05.html">1804-03-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Rousseau, Jean-Jacques</author>  
                  <title>Lettres de deux amans, habitans d’une petite ville au pied des Alpes, recuillies et publiées par J.-J. Rousseau.</title>  
                  <date when="1761">1761</date>
                  <lb/>Le faux titre porte: ‘Julie, ou la Nouvelle Héloise.’<lb/>2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> printing<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Picard, Louis-Benoit</author>  
                  <title>La petite ville, comédie en 4 actes.</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1449">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Udolphe (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-05.html">1804-03-05</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Radcliffe, Ann</author>  
                  <author>Desprès, Jean-Baptiste-Denis (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Les mystères d’Udolphe, par Anne Radcliffe. Traduit d’anglais sur la 3e édition.</title> (4 volumes)  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>OR one of several dramas based on the novel:<lb/> 
                  <author>Duval, Alexandre</author>  
                  <title>Montoni, ou Le château d’Udolphe, drame en cinq actes en prose, imite du roman ‘Les mystères d’Udolphe,’ par C. Alexandre Duval.</title>  
                  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Pixérécourt, René Charles Guilbert de</author>  
                  <title>Le Château des Apennines, ou Le fantôme vivant, drame en 5 actes, en prose et à grand spectacle, imité du roman anglais ‘Les mystères d’Udolphe,’ par R.-C. Guilbert-Pixérécourt.</title>  
                  <date when="1798">1798</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Lamartelière, Jean-Henri-Ferdinand</author>  
                  <title>Le testament, ou Les mystères d’Udolphe, drame en 5 actes, en prose, representée pour la première fois à Paris, au théâtre Louvois, le 22 messidor an VI, par le citoyen Jean-Henri-Ferdinand Lamartelière.</title>  
                  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1450">
                  <seg type="reference">Duhautcours, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-06.html">1804-03-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Picard, Louis Benoît</author>  
                  <author>Chéron, François</author>  
                  <title>Duhautcours, ou Le contrat d’union. Comedie en prose et en cinq actes, represéntée pour la premiere fois au théâtre de Louvois, par les comédiens de l’Odéon, le 18 thermidor an 9 (6 août  <date when="1801">1801</date>).</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1451">
                  <seg type="reference">Paine’s Letters (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-12.html">1804-03-12</ref>)
                    </seg>There are several publications grouping a number of Paine’s letters.  Unable to determine which publication WG reads on this date ( <date when="1804">1804-03</date>-12).  <lb/> 
                  <author>Paine, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Letters, by the author of Common sense. First, to the Earl of Shelburne, now Marquis of Lansdowne, on the subject of American independence. Second, to Sir Guy Carlton, now Lord Dorchester, on the murder of Captain Huddy. Third, to the authors of ‘The Republican,’ a French paper; tendering his services in support of the Republican system. Fourth, to the Abbe Syeyes, a member of the French National Assembly; accepting the abbe’s challenge on the subject of government, by offering to defend the republican against the monarchical system.</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date>
                  <lb/>‘Issued as part of several Albany issues of “The writings of Thomas Paine.”’<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Paine, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Letters on government: including both his letters to Mr. Dundas; with two letters to Lord Onslow, and two from Paris. By Thomas Paine. To which are prefixed anecdotes of his life.</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Paine, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Letters from Thomas Paine to the citizens of the United States on his arrival from France</title>.  <date when="1802">1802</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Paine, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Letter from Thomas Paine to the citizens of America, after an absence of fifteen years in Europe. To which are subjoined some letters, between him and the late General Washington, Mr. Samuel Adams, and the present President of the United States, Mr. Jefferson: Also, some original poetry of Mr. Paine’s and a facsimile of his hand-writing, in  <date when="1803">1803</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1452">
                  <seg type="reference">Catullus, Peleus, vs100 (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-22.html">1804-03-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Catullus, Gaius Valerius (b. 84 B.C.)</author> ‘poem LXIV’<lb/> in <title>Gai Valeri Catulli Veronensis Liber (The Poems of Gaius Valerius Catullus)</title> Date unknown<lb/>WG probably read one of the following editions:<lb/> 
                  <title>Catullus, Tibullus et Propertius, pristino nitori restituti, &amp; ad optima exemplaria emendati: Cum fragmentis C. Gallo inscriptis. A reprint of the Leiden edition of  <date when="1743">1743</date>, edited by Lenglet Dufresnoy.</title>  
                  <date when="1754">1754</date> [1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> edition]<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <title>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius, ex recensione Jo. Antonii Vulpii, cum notis.</title>  
                  <date when="1786">1786</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius Paris, Barbou,  <date when="1754">1754</date> (item 112).<lb/>Catullus, Tibullus, et Propertius, ex recens. Jo. Ant. Vulpii, 2 tom. in 1 Venet.  <date when="1786">1786</date> (item 113).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1453">
                  <seg type="reference">Burning Pestle (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-26.html">1804-03-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Beaumont, Francis</author>  
                  <author>Fletcher, John</author>  
                  <title>The knight of the burning pestle. A comedy in five acts, in prose and verse, by F. Beaumont and J. Fletcher.</title>  
                  <date when="1613">1613</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1454">
                  <seg type="reference">Martial, Ep. 1-13 (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-31.html">1804-03-31</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Martialis, Marcus Valerius (b. circa 40 A.D.)</author>  
                  <title>Epigrammata (Epigrams)</title> 80-96 A.D.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Martialis Epigrammata, Notis var. accur. Corn. Schrevelio Lugd. Bat.  <date when="1661">1661</date> (item 522).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1455">
                  <seg type="reference">Cowley, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-31.html">1804-03-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify the specific work WG is reading. Possibly one of the following listed in his sale catalog.<lb/> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>The Mistress, or Seuerall copies of love-verses. Written by Mr. A. Cowley.</title>  
                  <date when="1647">1647</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>Poems, viz. 1. Miscellanies. II. The mistress, or Love verses. III. Pindaresque odes, and IV. Davideis, or, a sacred poem of the troubles of David.</title>  
                  <date when="1656">1656</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>The works of Mr. Abraham Cowley. Consisting of those which were formerly printed and those which he designed for the press, now publish’d out of the author’s original copies.</title> (6 volumes)  <date when="1668">1668</date>
                  <lb/>Includes life by Sprat, Miscellanies, Mistress, Pindaris odes, Davideis, occasional verses, discourse on Cromwel’s government, essays.<lb/>The  <date when="1707">1707</date> edition includes Cutter of Coleman Street.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Cowley’s (Abr.) Mistress, or seuerall Copies of Love-verses,  <date when="1647">1647</date>.<lb/>Cowley’s (A.) Poems and Plays, 3 vol.  <date when="1707">1707-8</date>.<lb/>Cowley’s (Abr.) Poems  <date when="1656">1656</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1456">
                  <seg type="reference">recollections of Bacon, Jonson &amp; Montaigne (<ref target="/diary/1804-03-31.html">1804-03-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1457">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Marvel, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-04-03.html">1804-04-03</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify the specific work WG is reading. Possibly one of the following listed in his sale catalog:<lb/> 
                  <author>Marvell, Andrew</author>  
                  <title>The rehearsal transpos’d: or, Animadversions upon a late book, intituled, A preface shewing what grounds there are of fears and jealousies of popery.</title>  
                  <date when="1672">1672</date>
                  <lb/>AND<lb/> 
                  <title>The rehearsal transpos’d: the second part: Occasioned by two letters: The first printed, by a nameless author [S. Parker], intituled, A reproof, &amp;c. The second letter left for me at a friends house, dated Nov. 3.  <date when="1673">1673</date>. subscribed J. G. and concluding with these words, If thou darest to print or publish any lie or libel against Doctor Parker, by the eternal God I will cut thy throat. Answered by Andrew Marvell.</title>  
                  <date when="1673">1673</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Marvell’s (A.) Rehearsal Transposed, with the Reproof to the Rehearsal Transposed, by the author of Ecclesiastical Politie, 3 vol.  <date when="1672">1672-3</date> (item 523).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1458">
                  <seg type="reference">Montaigne, Ess. 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-04-04.html">1804-04-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Michel de Montaigne</author>  
                  <title>Essais de Messire Michel Seigneur de Montaigne, chevalier de l’Ordre du Roy, &amp; Gentil homme Ordinaire de sa chambre. Livre premier &amp; second.</title>  
                  <date when="1580">1580</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Montaigne, ses Essais, enrichie d’Annotations, 3 vol. Rouen,  <date when="1627">1627</date> (item 563).<lb/>Montaigne, ses Essais, 5 vol. Haye,  <date when="1727">1727</date>—Esprit des Loix, 4 vol.  <date when="1757">1757</date>; in all 9 vol. (item 565).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1459">
                  <seg type="reference">Clarendon, p. 89 (<ref target="/diary/1804-04-06.html">1804-04-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>The history of the rebellion and civil wars in England, begun in the year  <date when="1641">1641</date>. With the precedent passages, and actions, that contributed thereunto, and the happy end, and conclusion thereof by the King’s blessed restoration, and return upon the 29</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title> of May, in the year  <date when="1660">1660</date>. Written by the Right Honourable Edward Earl of Clarendon, late Lord High Chancellour of England, Privy Counsellour in the reigne of King Charles the First and the Second. </title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1702">1702-4</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>State papers collected by Edward, Earl of Clarendon: commencing from the year  <date when="1621">1621</date>: containing the materials from which his History of the great rebellion was composed.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1767">1767-1786</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Clarendon’s History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England and Ireland, 8 vol.  <date when="1721">1721</date> (item 138).<lb/>Clarendon and Whitlock compared, by Oldmixon  <date when="1727">1727</date> (item 139).<lb/>Clarendon’s (Edw. Earl of) State Papers, 3 vol. Oxford,  <date when="1767">1767-86</date>) (item 435).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1460">
                  <seg type="reference">Hydriotaphia, Chap. 1 &amp; 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-04-17.html">1804-04-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Browne, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Hydriotaphia, wine-buriall, or a Discourse of the sepulchrall urnes lately found in Norfolk, together with the garden of Cyrus, or the quincunciall, lozenge, or net-work plantations of the ancients … By Thomas Browne, …</title>  
                  <date when="1658">1658</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Browne’s (Sir Tho.) Hydriotaphia, or discourse of Urne Buriall, plates,  <date when="1658">1658</date>—Christian Morals, Camb.  <date when="1716">1716</date>; 2 vol. (item 81).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1461">
                  <seg type="reference">Vulgar Errors, Chap. 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-04-27.html">1804-04-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Battell, Ralph</author>  
                  <title>Vulgar errors in divinity removed</title>.  <date when="1683">1683</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>Vulgar errors.</title>  
                  <date when="1784">1784</date>
                  <lb/> (A defence of the parliamentary opposition before the general election of  <date when="1784">1784</date>.)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1462">
                  <seg type="reference">D’Aunois, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-04.html">1804-05-04</ref>)
                    </seg>Godwin may have read any of a long list of publications by the Countess d’Aulnoy. The following are a sample:<lb/> 
                  <author>Aulnoy, Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, comtesse d’</author>  
                  <title>Relation d’un voyage d’Espagne: ouest exactement decrit l’estat de la cour de ce royaume, &amp; de son gouvernement.</title>  
                  <date when="1664">1664</date>
                  <lb/>in English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Aulnoy, Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, comtesse d’</author>
                  <seg> </seg> The ingenious and diverting letters of the Lady ---- Travels into Spain. Describing the devotions, nunneries, humours, customs, laws, militia, trade, diet, and recreations of that people: Intermixt with great variety of modern adventures, and surprising accidents: being the truest and best remarks extant on that court and country.<lb/> 
                  <date when="1691">1691</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Aulnoy, Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, comtesse d’</author>
                  <seg> </seg>  
                  <title>Mémoires des avantures singulières de la cour de France</title>.  <date when="1677">1677</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Aulnoy, Marie-Catherine Le Jumel de Barneville, comtesse d’</author>  
                  <title>Les contes des fées, par Madame D***, auteur des Memoires &amp; voyage d’Espagne. </title> earliest publication has no date<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1463">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-07.html">1804-05-07</ref>)
                    </seg>WG may have been reading from one of the following editions of Milton’s poems:<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Poems of Mr. John Milton, both English and Latin, compos’d at several times: printed by his true copies.</title>  
                  <date when="1645">1645</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Poems, &amp;c. upon several occasions, both English and latin, &amp;c. Composed at several times by Mr. John Milton; with a small tractate of education to Mr. Hartlib.; Joannis Miltoni Londinensis poemata.; Of education.</title>  
                  <date when="1673">1673</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Poems upon several occasions, English, Italian, and Latin, with translations, by John Milton. Viz. Lycidas, l’allegro, il penseroso, arcades, comus, odes, sonnets, miscellanies, english psalms, elegiarum liber, epigrammatum liber, sylvanum liber. With notes critical and explanatory, and other illustrations, by Thomas Warton, Fellow of Trinity College and Late Professor of Poetry at Oxford.</title>  
                  <date when="1785">1785</date>
                  <lb/>The same title was published in  <date when="1791">1791</date>.<lb/>Given the list of contents and the fact that WG is reading elegies and sylvae around this time, this is likely the text he is reading, though perhaps in the  <date when="1673">1673</date> edition.<lb/>OR if he is reading Milton’s prose at this time:<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>The works of John Milton. </title>(only the prose)  <date when="1697">1697</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists several collections of Milton’s works, including:<lb/>Milton’s Poems, English and Latin, first edition, by Marshall  <date when="1645">1645</date> (item 537).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, &amp;c. upon several occasions, port.  <date when="1673">1673</date> (item 545).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, upon several occasions, with notes by T. Warton  <date when="1791">1791</date> (item 547).<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1464">
                  <seg type="reference">Hall’s Remonstrance (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-11.html">1804-05-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Hall, Joseph</author>  
                  <title>An humble remonstrance to the High Covrt of Parliament, written by Joseph Hall. </title>  
                  <date when="1640">1640</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1465">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, El. 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-12.html">1804-05-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author> ‘Elegia prima ad Carolum Diodatum’ (To Charles Diodati)<lb/>‘Elegia secunda, Anno aetatis 17: In obitum Praeconis Academici Cantabrigiensis’ (On the Death of the Beadle of Cambridge University)<lb/>‘Elegia tertia Anno aetatis 17. In obitum Praesulis Eliensis’ (On the Death of the Bishop of Ely)<lb/>all composed  <date when="1626">1626</date>
                  <lb/>WG may have read these in one of the editions annotated at  <date when="1804">1804-05</date>-07.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s Poems, English and Latin, first edition, by Marshall  <date when="1645">1645</date> (item 537).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, &amp;c. upon several occasions, port.  <date when="1673">1673</date> (item 545).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, upon several occasions, with notes by T. Warton  <date when="1791">1791</date> (item 547).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1466">
                  <seg type="reference">Of Reformation (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-12.html">1804-05-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Of reformation touching church-discipline in England: and the causes that hitherto have hindered it. Two bookes, written to a friend.</title>  
                  <date when="1641">1641</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton on Reformation, touching Church Discipline in England,  <date when="1641">1641</date>, and four other Tracts by him; in 1 vol. (item 792).<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^1467. Milton, Reason of Church Govt, chap. 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-15.html">1804-05-15</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>The reason of church-governement urg’d against prelaty. By Mr. John Milton. In two books.</title>  
                  <date when="1641">1641</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton Reason of Church Government urged against Prelacy,  <date when="1641">1641</date>—Areopagitica, a Speech for the liberty of unlicensed Printing,  <date when="1644">1644</date>, and six other Tracts, by Milton; in 1 vol. (item 793).<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1468">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, Sylvæ, 6 (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-20.html">1804-05-20</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author> ‘Sylvanum liber.’<lb/>WG may have read this in one of the editions annotated at  <date when="1804">1804-05</date>-07.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s Poems, English and Latin, first edition, by Marshall  <date when="1645">1645</date> (item 537).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, &amp;c. upon several occasions, port.  <date when="1673">1673</date> (item 545).<lb/>Milton’s Poems, upon several occasions, with notes by T. Warton  <date when="1791">1791</date> (item 547).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1469">
                  <seg type="reference">Mansus (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-20.html">1804-05-20</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author> ‘Mansus’<lb/> in <title>Joannis Miltoni Londinensis poemata. Quorum pleraque intra annum aestatis vigesimum conscripsit. Nunc primum edita.</title>  
                  <date when="1645">1645</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1470">
                  <seg type="reference">Epitaphium Damonis, &amp;c. (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-22.html">1804-05-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Epitaphium Damonis.</title> (commemorates Charles Diodati, d.  <date when="1638">1638</date>)  <date when="1639">1639</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^1471. Milton, Remonstrant, §. 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-26.html">1804-05-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Animadversions upon the Remonstrants defence against Smectymnuus.</title>  
                  <date when="1641">1641</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton on Prelatical Episcopacy, and Animadversions upon the Remonstrants’ Defence, two Tracts  <date when="1641">1641</date> (item 791).<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1472">
                  <seg type="reference">Excursion, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-27.html">1804-05-27</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work. WG may have read similarly titled works by David Mallet ( <date when="1728">1728</date>), William Hutchinson ( <date when="1774">1774</date>), Frances Brooke ( <date when="1777">1777</date>), Charles Heath ( <date when="1796">1796</date>), Henry Wansey ( <date when="1798">1798</date>), or Charles Maclean ( <date when="1804">1804</date>).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1473">
                  <seg type="reference">Sopha, p. 102 (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-28.html">1804-05-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Crébillon, Claude-Prosper Jolyot de</author>  
                  <title>Le sopha, conte moral.</title>  
                  <date when="1742">1742</date>
                  <lb/>In English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Crébillon, Claude-Prosper Jolyot de</author>  
                  <title>The sopha, a moral tale.</title>  (2 volumes)  <date when="1742">1742</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1474">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, Def. Secunda, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-05-28.html">1804-05-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Joannis Miltoni Angli Pro populo Anglicano defensio secunda. Contra infamem libellum anonymum cui titules, Regii sanguines clamor ad coelum adversus parricidos Anglicanos.</title>  
                  <date when="1654">1654</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1475">
                  <seg type="reference">Number-Nip, p. 142 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-08.html">1804-06-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Bedford, William (translator)</author> ‘Elfin freaks; or, The seven legends of Number-Nip’<lb/> in <title>Popular tales of the Germans.</title> (volume 2)  <date when="1791">1791</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1476">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, Apology, p. 11 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-10.html">1804-06-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>An apology against a pamphlet call’d A modest confutation of the Animadversions upon the Remonstrants defence against Smectymnuus.</title>  
                  <date when="1742">1742</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1477">
                  <seg type="reference">Robin Hood, p. 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-11.html">1804-06-11</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, Mary Jane (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Tabart’s improved edition of Robin Hood: with coloured plates.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1478">
                  <seg type="reference">Aristonous (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-19.html">1804-06-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Fénelon, François de Salignac de La Mothe</author>  
                  <title>Les avantures de Télémaque, fils d’Ulysse.</title>  
                  <date when="1699">1699-1700</date> Nouv. ed. divisée en dix livres. S. l. s.n., 2 vols.<lb/>(includes in volume 2: Sophronimeou les aventures d’Aristonous (24 p.)<lb/>OR separate publication in  <date when="1700">1700</date> s.l.; republished in  <date when="1804">1804</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1479">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, Def. pro Se, p. 6 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-19.html">1804-06-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Joannis Miltoni Angli Pro se defensio contra Alexandrum Morum Ecclesiasten, libelli famosi, cui titulus, Regii sanguinis clamor ad coelum adversus parricidos Anglicanos.</title>  
                  <date when="1655">1655</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1480">
                  <seg type="reference">Coxe’s Switzerland, p. 70 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-25.html">1804-06-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Coxe, William</author>  
                  <title>Sketches of the natural, civil, and political state of Swisserland: in a series of letters to William Melmoth, Esq.</title>  
                  <date when="1779">1779</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Coxe, William</author>  
                  <title>Travels in Switzerland. In a series of letters to William Melmoth, Esq. from William Coxe, … in three volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1789">1789</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1481">
                  <seg type="reference">Popular Tales, p. 40 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-26.html">1804-06-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Bedford, William (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Popular tales of the Germans.</title>  (2 volumes)  <date when="1791">1791</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1482">
                  <seg type="reference">Royal Indisposition, pp. 112 (<ref target="/diary/1804-06-28.html">1804-06-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>Some particulars of the royal indisposition of  <date when="1788">1788-1789</date>, and of its effects upon illustrious personages and opposite parties interested by it.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1483">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton, Way to Commonwealth, pp. 10 (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-03.html">1804-07-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>The readie &amp; easie way to establish a free commonwealth, and the excellence therof compar’d with the inconveniencies and danger of readmitting kingship in this nation. The second edition revis’d and augmented.</title>  
                  <date when="1660">1660</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton’s (J.) Works, 2 vol. <date when="1697">1697-98</date> (item 864)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1484">
                  <seg type="reference">History of Independency, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-04.html">1804-07-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walker, Clement</author>  
                  <title>Anarchia anglicana, or, The history of independency, by Theodorux Verax.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1648">1648</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1485">
                  <seg type="reference">Ludlow, p. 350 (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-06.html">1804-07-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Ludlow, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of Edmund Ludlow, Esq: Lieutenant General of the Horse … and a Member of the Parliament which began on November 3,  <date when="1640">1640</date>. In two volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1698">1698-9</date>
                  <lb/>Third volume issued in  <date when="1699">1699</date>.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Ludlow’s (E.) Memoirs, 3 vol. Vivay in Switzerland,  <date when="1698">1698</date> 9 (item 503).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1486">
                  <seg type="reference">Love Stratagems, act 1 &amp; 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-12.html">1804-07-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>The stratagems of love. A comic opera. As it is performed on the Theatre in Smock-Alley.</title>  
                  <date when="1762">1762</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1487">
                  <seg type="reference">Whitlocke, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-12.html">1804-07-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Whitelocke, Bulstrode</author>  
                  <author>Morton, Charles (editor)</author>  
                  <title>A journal of the Swedish ambassy, in the years M.DC.LIII and M.DC.LIV from the commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. Written by the ambassador the Lord Commissioner Whitelocke. With an appendix of original papers. In two volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1772">1772</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Whitelocke, Bulstrode</author>  
                  <title>Memorials of the English affairs: or, an historical account of what passed from the beginning of the reign of Charles the First, to Charles the Second his happy restauration. Containing the publick transactons, civil and military; together with the private consultations and secrets of the cabinet.</title>  
                  <date when="1682">1682</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <author>Oldmixon, John</author>  
                  <title>Clarendon and Whitlock compared. To which is occasionally added, a comparison between the history of the rebellion and other histories of the civil war. By John Oldmixon.</title>  
                  <date when="1727">1727</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Whitelocke’s (Lord Commissioner) Journal of the Swedish Embassy,  <date when="1653">1653-4</date>, with <lb/>appendix, edited by Dr. Morton, 2 vol.  <date when="1772">1772</date> (item 831).<lb/>Whitelocke’s Memorials of English Affairs  <date when="1682">1682</date> (item 906).<lb/>Whitelocke’s Memorials of English Affairs, with many Additions  <date when="1732">1732</date> (item 907).<lb/>Clarendon and Whitlock compared, by Oldmixon  <date when="1727">1727</date> (item 139).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1488">
                  <seg type="reference">Fairfax, B. I (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-15.html">1804-07-15</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas, Baron Fairfax</author>  
                  <title>Short Memorials of Thomas Lord Fairfax. Written by himself.</title>  
                  <date when="1699">1699</date>
                  <lb/> WG cites Fairfax’s <title>Memorials</title> in his <title>History of the Commonwealth of England</title> 1: 107. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1489">
                  <seg type="reference">Clarendon, Life, p. 62 (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-15.html">1804-07-15</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>The history of the rebellion and civil wars in England: Begun in the year  <date when="1641">1641</date>. With the precedent passages, and actions, that contributed thereunto, and the happy end, and conclusion thereof by the King’s blessed restoration, and return upon the 29</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title> of May, in the year  <date when="1660">1660</date>
                  </title>. (4 volumes)  <date when="1702">1702-1759</date>
                  <lb/>The fourth volume, dated  <date when="1759">1759</date>, is titled:<lb/> 
                  <title>The life of Edward Earl of Clarendon, Lord High Chancellor of England, and Chancellor of the University of Oxford. Containing 1. An account of the Chancellor’s life from his birth to the restoration in  <date when="1660">1660</date>. II. A continuation of the same, and of his History of the grand rebellion, from the restoration to his banishment in  <date when="1667">1667</date>. Written by himself. Printed from his original manuscripts, given to the University of Oxford, by the heirs of the late Earl of Clarendon</title>.  <date when="1759">1759</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1490">
                  <seg type="reference">Thiebault, Vol. I, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-19.html">1804-07-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work read by WG.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1491">
                  <seg type="reference">Arabian Nights, p. 46. (<ref target="/diary/1804-07-23.html">1804-07-23</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Galland, Antoine</author>  
                  <title>Arabian nights entertainments consisting of one thousand stories, told by the sultaness of the Indies, to divert the sultan from the execution of a bloody vow he had made to marry a lady every day and have her cut off every morning, to avenge himself for the disloyalty of his first sultaness, &amp;c. Translated into French from the Arabian MSS by M. Galland, of the Royal Academy, and now done into English</title>.  <date when="1706">1706</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1492">
                  <seg type="reference">Cutter of C S, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-08-20.html">1804-08-20</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>Cutter of Coleman-street: a comedy: the scene London, in the year  <date when="1568">1568</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1663">1663</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1493">
                  <seg type="reference">Pichegru (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-03.html">1804-09-03</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably the following author:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jean Baptiste Joseph Breton de La Martinière</author> Unable to identify specific work by (or about) this person. WG may have read one or all of the following and some that are not listed:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jean Baptiste Joseph Breton de La Martinière</author>  
                  <title>Moreau et Pichegru au 18 fructidor an V; suivi de la conjuration de ce dernier, pendant les années III, IV, et V; et de la correspondance des nommes Drake et Spencer-Smith, Ambassadeurs anglais, pendant le mois de mars dernier, tendante à renouer les trames contre la France et la personne du premier consul.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Jean Baptiste Joseph Breton de La Martinière (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Procès instruit par la cour de justice criminelle et spéciale du département de la Seine, séante à Paris, contre Georges, Pichegru et autres, prevenus de conspiration contre la personne du premier consul.</title> (8 volumes.)  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>France. Consulat</author>  
                  <title>Acte d’accusation de Georges, Pichegru, Moreau, et autres prévenus du conspiration contre la personne du premier consul et contre la sûreté intérieur et extérieur de la république. (15 floréal)</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1494">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; La Rive, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-03.html">1804-09-03</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1495">
                  <seg type="reference">Essay on Criticism (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-08.html">1804-09-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Pope, Alexander</author>  
                  <title>An essay on criticism</title>.  <date when="1711">1711</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1496">
                  <seg type="reference">Love’s Riddle, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-12.html">1804-09-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>Loves riddle. A pastorall comaedie; written, at the time of his being King’s scholler in Westminster Schoole, by A. Cowley.</title>  
                  <date when="1638">1638</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1497">
                  <seg type="reference">Barth. Fair, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-14.html">1804-09-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Bartholomew Fair</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson: the second volume: containing these plays, viz. 1 Bartholomew Fayre. 2 The staple of newes. 3 The Divell is an asse.</title>  
                  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1498">
                  <seg type="reference">New Inn, acts 1 &amp; 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-16.html">1804-09-16</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The neuu inne, or, The light heart: a comoedy, as it was neuer acted, but most negligently play’d, by some, the Kings seruants: and more squeamishly beheld and censured by others, the Kings subiects  <date when="1629">1629</date>: now, at last, set at liberty to the readers, His Ma[ies]ties seruants and subiects, to be iudg’d  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  </title>.  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1499">
                  <seg type="reference">Read Beaumont, accurante Ht. (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-20.html">1804-09-20</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1500">
                  <seg type="reference">Bobadil, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-21.html">1804-09-21</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Every man in his humor. As it hath beene sundry times publickly acted by the right Honourable the Lord Chamberlaine his servants.</title>  
                  <date when="1601">1601</date>
                  <lb/> Bobadil is a character in Ben Jonson’s <title>Every man in his humour</title>; played by John Bannister ( <date when="1803">1803</date>?) and by David Garrick in the 18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century.  Garrick altered the play  <date when="1769">1769</date>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1501">
                  <seg type="reference">Read to Curran – IGNORE, lEAVE AS DWROTE (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-24.html">1804-09-24</ref>)
                    </seg>WG is probably reading his manuscript ‘Camilla,’ which he is revising on this date ( <date when="1804">1804-09</date>-24). ‘Camilla’ is the working title for:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Faulkener, A Tragedy</title>.  <date when="1807">1807</date> 
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1502">
                  <seg type="reference">Sejanus, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-29.html">1804-09-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Seianus his fall. Written by Ben: Jonson.</title>  
                  <date when="1605">1605</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1503">
                  <seg type="reference">Devil is an Ass, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-09-30.html">1804-09-30</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The devil is an ass</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson: the second volume: containing these plays, viz. 1 Bartholomew Fayre. 2 The staple of newes. 3 The Divell is an asse.</title>  
                  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1504">
                  <seg type="reference">Cynthia’s Revels, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-07.html">1804-10-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The fountaine of selfe-loue. Or Tynthias reuels. As it hath been sundry times priuately acted in the Black-Friers by the Children of her Maiesties Chappell. Written by Ben: Jonson.</title>  
                  <date when="1601">1601</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1505">
                  <seg type="reference">Masques, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-07.html">1804-10-07</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific masques read by WG. ‘Masques at covrt’ were published in a collection of Jonson’s works:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson</title> (1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume)  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1506">
                  <seg type="reference">Tale of a Tub (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-08.html">1804-10-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson</title> (3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> volume)  <date when="1640">1640-1641</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1508">
                  <seg type="reference">Every Man out of his Humour, acts 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-10.html">1804-10-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Every man out of his humour. A comicall satyre acted in the yeere  <date when="1599">1599</date>, by the then Lord Chamberlaine his seruants</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson </title>(1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume)  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1509">
                  <seg type="reference">Macilente, acts 3, 4 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-11.html">1804-10-11</ref>)
                    </seg>Macilente is a character in:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Every man out of his humour. A comicall satyre acted in the yeere  <date when="1599">1599</date>, by the then Lord Chamberlaine his seruants</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson </title>(1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume)  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1510">
                  <seg type="reference">Poetaster, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-14.html">1804-10-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Poetaster; or, The arraignment: as it hath been sundry times priuately acted in the Blacke Friers, by the children of her maiesties chappell.</title>  
                  <date when="1602">1602</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1511">
                  <seg type="reference">Catiline, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-17.html">1804-10-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Catiline his conspiracy. Written by Ben: Iohnson.</title>  
                  <date when="1611">1611</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1512">
                  <seg type="reference">Magnetic Lady, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-19.html">1804-10-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The magnetick lady</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson</title> (3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> volume)  <date when="1640">1640-1641</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1513">
                  <seg type="reference">Rivals, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-19.html">1804-10-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Sheridan, Richard Brinsley</author>  
                  <title>The rivals, a comedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Covent-Garden.</title>  
                  <date when="1775">1775</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1514">
                  <seg type="reference">Jealous Wife, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-24.html">1804-10-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Colman, George, elder</author>  
                  <title>The jealous wife, a comedy in five acts.</title>  
                  <date when="1761">1761</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1515">
                  <seg type="reference">Louis XIV, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-27.html">1804-10-27</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Voltaire, François-Marie Arouet</author>  
                  <title>Le siècle de Louis XIV, publié par M. de Francheville, etc</title>. (2 volumes)  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1516">
                  <seg type="reference">Staple of News, acts 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1804-10-29.html">1804-10-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The staple of newes. A comedie acted in the yeare  <date when="1625">1625</date>. By his maiesties servants</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson, the second volume: containing these plays, viz. 1 Bartholomew Fayre. 2 The staple of newes. 3 The Divell is an asse.</title>  
                  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1517">
                  <seg type="reference">Case is Altered, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-01.html">1804-11-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Ben Ionson, his Case is altered. As it hath beene sundry times acted by the children of the Blacke-Friers.</title>  
                  <date when="1609">1609</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1518">
                  <seg type="reference">Encyclopédie (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-02.html">1804-11-02</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Diderot, Denis</author>  
                  <author>Alembert, Jean Le Rond d’</author>  
                  <title>Encyclopédie; ou Dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des arts et des métiers.</title> 
                  <title>Par une societé de gens de lettres; mis en ordre et publié par M. Diderot; &amp; quant à la partie mathematique par M. d’Alembert .</title>(28 volumes)  <date when="1750">1750</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1519">
                  <seg type="reference">Anderson (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-08.html">1804-11-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Anderson, Robert (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The works of the British poets. With prefaces, biographical and critical.</title> (13 volumes)  <date when="1795">1795</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s current interest in British 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century poets.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1520">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Brown, pp. 120 (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-17.html">1804-11-17</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1521">
                  <seg type="reference">Volpone, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-19.html">1804-11-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Volpone; or, The foxe</title>.  <date when="1607">1607</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1522">
                  <seg type="reference">Jonson (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-19.html">1804-11-19</ref>)
                    </seg> Unable to identify specific work read by WG.  Since he already records reading Ben Jonson’s <title>Volpone</title> on this date, he may be surveying Jonson’s works in a collection. The earliest collection of Jonson’s works is:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson.</title>  
                  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/> This collection contains: <title>Every man in his hvmovr; Cynthias revels; Poetaster; Seianvs his fall; Volpone; Epicoene, or The silent woman; The alchemist, Catiline his conspiracy; Epigrammes 1. booke; The forest; Part of the kings entertainment in passing to his coronation; A panegyric on the happie entrance of Iames, our soveraigne, to his first high session of Parliament; A particular entertainment of qveenes and prince … at Althrope; Masques at covrt.</title> The following is known as the second volume of Jonson’s works:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson: the second volume: containing these plays, viz. 1 Bartholomew Fayre. 2 The staple of newes. 3 The Divell is an asse.</title>  
                  <date when="1631">1631</date>
                  <lb/>And the following collection of his plays is known as the third volume:<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson.</title>  
                  <date when="1640">1640-41</date>
                  <lb/>contains the following:<lb/> 
                  <title>Christmas, his masque</title> ( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>Underwoods </title>( <date when="1640">1640</date>); and <title>Mortimer his fal</title>l ( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>The magnetick lady</title> ( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>A tale of a tub</title> ( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>The sad shepherd</title> ( <date when="1641">1641</date>); <title>Horace, his art of poetrie</title> ( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>The English grammar </title>( <date when="1640">1640</date>); <title>Timber</title> ( <date when="1641">1641</date>). WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1523">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Donne, çala (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-19.html">1804-11-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Donne, John</author>  
                  <title>Poems by J.D. With elegies on the authors death.</title>  
                  <date when="1633">1633</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Donne’s (J.) Poems, with elegies on the Author’s Death  <date when="1635">1635</date> (item 194)<lb/>Ditto.  <date when="1660">1660</date> (item 195)<lb/>Ditto  <date when="1669">1669</date> (item 196)<lb/>Ditto, edited by Isaac Walton …  <date when="1633">1633</date> (item 379)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1524">
                  <seg type="reference">Donne, Anniversaries (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-20.html">1804-11-20</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Donne, John</author>  
                  <title>The first anniversarie:An anatomy of the world.</title>  
                  <date when="1611">1611</date>
                  <lb/>and<lb/> 
                  <title>The second anniversarie: Of the progess of the soule.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1525">
                  <seg type="reference">Donne, Eleg. 1-6 (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-21.html">1804-11-21</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Donne, John</author>  
                  <title>Elegies</title>  in <title>Poems by J.D. With elegies on the authors death.</title>  
                  <date when="1633">1633</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1526">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Donne (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-24.html">1804-11-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walton, Isaac</author>  
                  <title>The life of John Donne, Dr. in divinity, and late dean of Saint Pauls Church, London.</title>  
                  <date when="1658">1658</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Walton, Isaac</author>  
                  <title>The lives of Dr. John Donne, Sir Henry Wotton, Mr. Richard Hooker, Mr. George Herbert. Written by Izaak Walton. To which are added some letters written by Mr. George Herbert, at his being in Cambridge, with others to his mother, the Lady Magdalen Herbert, written by John Donne, afterwards Dean of St. Paul.</title>  
                  <date when="1670">1670</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Donne, Wotton, Hooker, Herbert Lives by I. Walton.  <date when="1675">1675</date> (item #199)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1527">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Wotton (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-25.html">1804-11-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walton, Isaac</author>  
                  <title>The lives of Dr. John Donne, Sir Henry Wotton, Mr. Richard Hooker, Mr. George Herbert. Written by Izaak Walton. To which are added some letters written by Mr. George Herbert, at his being in Cambridge, with others to his mother, the Lady Magdalen Herbert, written by John Donne, afterwards Dean of St. Paul.</title>  
                  <date when="1670">1670</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1528">
                  <seg type="reference">All in the Wrong (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-27.html">1804-11-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Murphy, Arthur</author>  
                  <title>All in the wrong: a comedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Drury Lane.</title>  
                  <date when="1761">1761</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1529">
                  <seg type="reference">Headfort’s Trial, pp. 95 (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-29.html">1804-11-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>No author</author>  
                  <title>A report of the trial on an action for damages, brought by the Reverend Charles Massy against the most noble, the Marquis of Headfort, for criminal conversation with plaintiff’s wife: damages laid at L40,000.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>‘At the head of the title: By authority. Ten thousand pounds damages. Summer assizes. Trial at Ennis, County of Clare, on 17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> July,  <date when="1804">1804</date>. Before the Ho. Baron Smith, and a special jury.’  (‘taken in short-hand by an eminent Barrister.’)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1530">
                  <seg type="reference">January &amp; May, &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1804-11-30.html">1804-11-30</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1531">
                  <seg type="reference">[Perkin Warbeck.] (<ref target="/diary/1804-12-07.html">1804-12-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Gainsford, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The true and wonderfull history of Perkin Warbeck, proclaiming himself Richard the fourth</title>.  <date when="1618">1618</date>
                  <lb/> also known as <title>History of Perkin Warbeck</title> OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Ford, John</author>  
                  <title>The chronicle historie of Perkin Warbeck. a strange truth. Acted (some-times) by the Queenes Maiesties Servants at the Phaenix in Drurie Lane.</title>  
                  <date when="1634">1634</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1532">
                  <seg type="reference">Cleone (<ref target="/diary/1804-12-28.html">1804-12-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Dodsley, Robert</author>  
                  <title>Cleone, a tragedy, as it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Covent Garden.</title>  
                  <date when="1754">1754</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1533">
                  <seg type="reference">Revenge, acts 3, 4, 5 (<ref target="/diary/1804-12-30.html">1804-12-30</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Young, Edward</author>  
                  <title>The Revenge, a tragedy. Adapted for theatrical representation, as performed at the Theatres Royal, Drury Lane and Covent Garden. Regulated from the prompt books, by permission of the managers.</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Chatterton, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The Revenge, a burletta. Acted at Marybone Gardens, MDCCLXX. with additional songs.</title>  
                  <date when="1795">1795</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <pb/>Annotated Titles  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1534">
                  <seg type="reference">Twin Rivals, act 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-01.html">1805-01-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Farquhar, George</author>  
                  <title>The twin-rivals. A comedy. Acted at the Theatre Royal by Her Majesty’s servants</title>. Written by Mr. Farquhar.  <date when="1703">1703</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1535">
                  <seg type="reference">Impertinent Curiosity (D 2), pp. 53 (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-03.html">1805-01-03</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1536">
                  <seg type="reference">Wonder, act 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-05.html">1805-01-05</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Susanna Centlivre</author>  
                  <title>The wonder: A woman keeps a secret.</title>  
                  <date when="1714">1714</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1537">
                  <seg type="reference">Don Carlos (Sch.) p. 210 (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-07.html">1805-01-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Schiller, Johann Christoph Friedrich von</author>  
                  <title>Dom Karlos, infant von Spanien.</title>  
                  <date when="1787">1787</date>
                  <lb/>Translated as:<lb/> 
                  <author>Schiller, Johann Christoph Friedrich von</author>  
                  <author>Noehden, Georg Heinrich (translator)</author>  
                  <author>Stoddart, John (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Don Carlos, prince royal of Spain: an historical drama, from the German of Frederick Schiller …By the translators of Fiesco [Georg Heinrich Noehden and John Stoddart].</title>  
                  <date when="1798">1798</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1538">
                  <seg type="reference">St Phale, p. 64 (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-17.html">1805-01-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Saint-Phale, Mademoiselle de</author>  
                  <author>Star, B.</author>  
                  <title>The history of Madamoiselle de St. Phale, giving a full account of the miraculous conversion of a noble French lady and her daughter to the reformed religion. With the defeat of the intriegues of a Jesuite their confessor. Translated out of the French.</title>  
                  <date when="1690">1690</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1539">
                  <seg type="reference">St Forlaix, Vol. I, II (<ref target="/diary/1805-01-29.html">1805-01-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Framéry, Nicolas Étienne</author>  
                  <author>Mrs. Brooke (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of the Marquis de St. Forlaix. Translated from the French of Mons. Framery. By Mrs. Brooke …</title>  
                  <date when="1770">1770</date>
                  <lb/>In French:<lb/> 
                  <author>Framéry, Nicolas Étienne</author>  
                  <author>Brooke, Frances Moore (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Mémoires de M. le marquis de S. Forlaix, recueillis dans les lettres de sa famille (par F. Brooke, traduits) par M. Framery.</title>  
                  <date when="1770">1770</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1540">
                  <seg type="reference">Loix Criminelles (<ref target="/diary/1805-02-06.html">1805-02-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Muyart de Vouglans</author>  
                  <title>Les loix criminelles de France dans leur ordre naturel, dédiées au Roi.</title>  
                  <date when="1780">1780</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Boucher d’Argis, André Jean</author>  
                  <title>Observations sur les lois criminelles de France.</title>  
                  <date when="1781">1781</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1541">
                  <seg type="reference">Ad. Mowbray, p. 106 (<ref target="/diary/1805-02-09.html">1805-02-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Opie, Amelia Alderson</author>  
                  <title>Adeline Mowbray, or The mother and daughter: a tale. By Mrs. Opie.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1542">
                  <seg type="reference">Modern Griselda, p. 66 (<ref target="/diary/1805-02-18.html">1805-02-18</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Maria</author>  
                  <title>The modern Griselda. A tale.</title>  
                  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1543">
                  <seg type="reference">Alfarache, p. 24 (<ref target="/diary/1805-02-19.html">1805-02-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Alemán, Mateo</author>  
                  <title>Primera parte de la vida del picaro Gvzman de Alfarache.</title>  
                  <date when="1599">1599</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <date when="1604">1604</date> 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> part?<lb/>In English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Alemán, Mateo</author>  
                  <author>Mabbe, James (translator)</author>  
                  <title>The rogue: or, The first [and second] part of the life of Guzman de Alfarache.</title>  
                  <date when="1622">1622</date>
                  <lb/>Translated by Don Diego Puede-Ser, i.e. James Mabbe.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Aleman’s (Matheo) Rogue, or Life of Guzman d’Alfarache, no date<lb/>(item 396).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1544">
                  <seg type="reference">(read act 5) (<ref target="/diary/1805-02-24.html">1805-02-24</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly WG reads act 5 of his manuscript play ‘Camilla,’ which he revises in September of  <date when="1805">1805</date>. ‘Camilla’ is the working title for:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Faulkener, A Tragedy</title>.  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1545">
                  <seg type="reference">Jealous Lovers, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1805-03-11.html">1805-03-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The jealous lovers. A comedie presented to their gracious Majesties at Cambridge, by the students of Trinity-Colledge. Written by Thomas Randolph, Master of Arts, and fellow of the house.</title>  
                  <date when="1632">1632</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1546">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Inchbald, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1805-03-27.html">1805-03-27</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1547">
                  <seg type="reference">Southey, Madoc (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-04.html">1805-04-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Southey, Robert</author>  
                  <title>Madoc.</title>  
                  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1548">
                  <seg type="reference">Hayley (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-04.html">1805-04-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <author>Hayley, John</author>  
                  <title>The poetical works of John Milton. With a life of the author, by William Hayley. Vol. 1.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1794">1794-7</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Hayley’s Life of Milton, Dubl.  <date when="1797">1797</date> (item 548).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1549">
                  <seg type="reference">Muses’ Looking Glass, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-06.html">1805-04-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Randolph, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Poems, with the Muses looking-glass: and Amyntas</title>.  <date when="1638">1638</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1550">
                  <seg type="reference">Cæsar, Druides (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-09.html">1805-04-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Caesar, C. Julius</author>  
                  <title>de Bello Gallico (The Gallic War)</title> 51 B.C.<lb/>Book VI, chapters 13, 14, 16 discuss the Druids.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1551">
                  <seg type="reference">Davies (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-14.html">1805-04-14</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work read by WG. Possibly one of the following listed in his sale catalog:<lb/> 
                  <author>Davies, Sir John</author>  
                  <title>A discoverie of the true causes why Ireland was neuer entirely subdued nor brought vnder obedience of the crowne of England, vntill the beginning of His Maiesties happie raigne.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/> 
                  <date when="1747">1747</date> reprinted exactly from the edition of  <date when="1612">1612</date>.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Davies, Sir John</author>  
                  <title>The original, nature and immortality of the soul. A poem. With an introduction concerning humane knowledge.</title>  
                  <date when="1697">1697</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Davies, Sir John</author>  
                  <title>Historical Tracts: by Sir John Davies…: consisting of 1. A discovery of the true cause why Ireland was never brought under obedience of the crown of England. 2. A letter to the Earl of Salisbury on the state of Ireland, in  <date when="1607">1607</date> [or rather,  <date when="1606">1606</date>]. 3. A letter to the Earl of Salisbury, in  <date when="1610">1610</date>; giving an account of the plantation in Ulster. 4. A speech to the Lord-Deputy in  <date when="1613">1613</date>, tracing the ancient constitution of Ireland. To which is prefixed a new life of the author [by the editor, George Chalmers], etc.</title>  
                  <date when="1786">1786</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Massinger, Philip</author>  
                  <author>Davies, Thomas (author of the life of Massinger)</author>  
                  <title>The dramatick works of Philip Massinger complete, in four volumes. Revised and corrected, with notes critical and explanatory, by John Monck Mason, Esqu. To which are added, … Critical reflections on the old English dramatick writers; and a short essay on the life and writings of Massinger, …</title>  
                  <date when="1779">1779</date>
                  <lb/>OR separately published:<lb/> 
                  <author>Davies, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Some account of the life of Philip Massinger.</title>  
                  <date when="1779">1779</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Davies’s (Sir John) Discoverie of the True Causes why Ireland was never entirely <lb/>	subdued  <date when="1612">1612</date>, reprint,  <date when="1747">1747</date> (item 179).<lb/>Davies’s (Sir John) Original and Immortality of the Soul, Glasgow, Foulis,  <date when="1749">1749</date> (item <lb/>	180).<lb/>Davies’s (Sir John) Historical Tracts, with Life by George Chalmers  <date when="1786">1786</date> (item 181).<lb/>T. Davies’ Life of P. Massinger,  <date when="1789">1789</date>, privately printed (item 201).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1552">
                  <seg type="reference">Owen, &amp;c; çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-14.html">1805-04-14</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1553">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Maurice, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-16.html">1805-04-16</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work read by WG. Possibly the following work first recorded on  <date when="1794">1794-12</date>-18:<lb/> 
                  <author>Maurice, comte de Saxe</author>  
                  <title>Reveries, or, Memoirs upon the art of war. Trans. by Sir William Fawcett.</title>  
                  <date when="1757">1757</date> 
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1554">
                  <seg type="reference">Turner, Vindication, p. 150 (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-17.html">1805-04-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Turner, John</author>  
                  <title>A vindication of the rights and privileges of the Christian church. … In answer to a late book intituled The rights of the Christian Church asserted, &amp;c. By John Turner…</title>  
                  <date when="1707">1707</date>
                  <lb/>Of John Turner’s many ‘vindications,’ this title matches WG’s reading most closely in number of pages.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1555">
                  <seg type="reference">Robertson, India, pp. 140 (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-18.html">1805-04-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Robertson, William</author>  
                  <title>An historical disquisition concerning the knowledge which the ancients had of India: and the progress of trade with that country prior to the discovery of the passage to it by the Cape of Good Hope, with an appendix, containing observations on the civil policy, the laws … and religious institutions of the Indians. By William Robertson.</title>  
                  <date when="1741">1741</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1556">
                  <seg type="reference">Bailly, p. 90 (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-18.html">1805-04-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following work first recorded on  <date when="1797">1797-06</date>-11:<lb/> 
                  <author>Bailly, Jean Sylvain Bailly</author>  
                  <author>Voltaire, François-Marie Arouet</author>  
                  <title>Lettres sur l’origine des sciences, et sur celle des peuples de l’Asie: Adressées à m. de Voltaire par m. Bailly, &amp; précédées de quelques lettres de m. de Voltaire à l’auteur.</title>  
                  <date when="1777">1777</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1557">
                  <seg type="reference">Strabo Diodorus (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-22.html">1805-04-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Strabo (b. 64 or 63 B.C.)</author>  
                  <title>The Geography of Strabo.</title> probably 7 B.C.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1558">
                  <seg type="reference">Mela (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-22.html">1805-04-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Mela, Pomponius</author>  
                  <title>Pomponii Melae Cosmographia.</title>  
                  <date when="1471">1471</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1559">
                  <seg type="reference">Pliny, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-22.html">1805-04-22</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Gaius Plinius Secundus (Pliny the Elder, 23-79 A.B.)</author>  
                  <title>Plinii Naturalis Historia (Pliny’s Natural History)</title> completed 77 A.D.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Gaius Plinius Caecilius Secundus (Pliny the Younger, 61 or 62 – 115 A.D.)</author>  
                  <title>C. Plinii Saecilii Secundi Epistularum (Letters)</title> 97-109 A.D.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1560">
                  <seg type="reference">Agricola, §.1-10 (<ref target="/diary/1805-04-26.html">1805-04-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Tacitus, Cornelius</author>  
                  <title>De Vita Iulii Agricolae (The Life of Julius Agricola)</title> comp. 97-98 A.D.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Taciti Opera, ad fidem Optimarum editionum expressa, 2 vol. Edinb.  <date when="1805">1805</date> (item 706).<lb/>Tacite Opera, Notis var. cura Gronovii, 2 vol. Traj. Bat.  <date when="1721">1721</date> (item 821).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1562">
                  <seg type="reference">Mably (<ref target="/diary/1805-05-05.html">1805-05-05</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably the following work by Mably first recorded on  <date when="1796">1796-02</date>-05:<lb/> 
                  <author>Mably, Gabriel Bonnot, abbé de</author>  
                  <title>Observations sur les Romains.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751</date> 
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s other reading of Roman history at this time.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1563">
                  <seg type="reference">Whitaker, p. 212 (<ref target="/diary/1805-05-06.html">1805-05-06</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Whitaker, John</author>  
                  <title>The genuine history of the Britons asserted. In a full and candid refutation of Mr. Macpherson’s Introduction to the history of Great Britain and Ireland. By the Rev. Mr. Whitaker.</title>  
                  <date when="1772">1772</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <seg> </seg>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s writing a history of England at this time.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Whitaker’s History of Manchester, 2 vol.  <date when="1773">1773</date> (item 745).<lb/>Whitaker’s Genuine History of the Britons asserted  <date when="1773">1773</date> (item 746).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1564">
                  <seg type="reference">Annual Review, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-05-13.html">1805-05-13</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Aikin, Arthur (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The annual review and history of literature.</title>  
                  <date when="1802">1802-1808</date>
                  <lb/> Also known as <title>The annual review, or, Register of literature</title> until changed to the above title. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1565">
                  <seg type="reference">History of the Plague (<ref target="/diary/1805-06-11.html">1805-06-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Defoe, Daniel</author>  
                  <title>The history of the great plague in London, in the year  <date when="1665">1665</date>. … By a citizen, who lived the whole time in London. To which is added, a journal of the plague at Marseilles, in the year  <date when="1720">1720</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1754">1754</date>
                  <lb/> First published in  <date when="1722">1722</date> as <title>The journal of the plague year</title>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1566">
                  <seg type="reference">Chapman (<ref target="/diary/1805-06-23.html">1805-06-23</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Homer</author>  
                  <author>Chapman, George (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Homer’s Odysses, translated according to ye Greeke by Geo. Chapman.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/>Chapman’s Odyssey, rather than Iliad, given the diary context.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1567">
                  <seg type="reference">Warton, &amp;c, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-06-23.html">1805-06-23</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably one of the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Warton, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The history of English poetry from the close of the eleventh to the commencement of the eighteenth century. To which are prefixed, two dissertations: 1, On the origin of romantic fiction in Europe; 2, On the introduction of learning into England. By Thomas Warton.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1774">1774-1781</date>
                  <lb/> The third volume is prefixed with <title>Gesta Romanorum</title>; a fourth volume published in  <date when="1806">1806</date> contains an index by Thos. Fillingham. OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Warton, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Essays on gothic architecture: twelve plates of ornaments, &amp;c. selected from ancient buildings; calculated to exhibit the various styles of different periods.</title>  
                  <date when="1686">1686</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s writing a history of England at this time.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Warton, Bentham, Grose and Milner’s Essays on Gothic Architecture, plates  <date when="1802">1802</date> (item 740).<lb/>Warton (T.) History of English Poetry, with the fragment of the fourth vol. and Fillingham’s Index, 5 vol.  <date when="1775">1775-1806</date> (item 830).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^1568. Barclay, &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1805-07-04.html">1805-07-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Barclay, John</author>  
                  <title>Ioannis Barclaii Argenis</title>.  <date when="1621">1621</date>
                  <lb/>In English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Barclay, John</author>  
                  <author>LeGrys, Sir Robert (translator)</author>  
                  <author>May, Thomas (verses)</author>  
                  <title>Iohn Barclay. His Argenis.</title>  
                  <date when="1629">1629</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Barclay’s (J.) Argenis, transl. by sir Rob. Le Grys, the Verses by Thomas May  <date when="1629">1629</date> (item 337).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1569">
                  <seg type="reference">Cowley, Plantarum, vs. 200 (<ref target="/diary/1805-07-07.html">1805-07-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cowley, Abraham</author>  
                  <title>Plantarum libri duo …</title>  
                  <date when="1662">1662</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Cowley’s (Abr.) Mistress, or Seuerall Copies of Love-verses,  <date when="1647">1647</date> (item 158).<lb/>Cowley’s (A. Poems and Plays, plates, 3 vol.  <date when="1707">1707-8</date> (item 159).<lb/>Cowley’s (Abr.) Poems  <date when="1656">1656</date> (item 426).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1570">
                  <seg type="reference">Youthful Worthies (<ref target="/diary/1805-07-08.html">1805-07-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1571">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Jane Grey, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-07-08.html">1805-07-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Life of Lady Jane Grey, and of Lord Guildford Dudley, her hasband: this young lady at twelve years of age understood eight languages: was for nine days Queen of England: and was beheaded in the Tower in the seventeenth year of her age, being at that time the most amiable and accomplished woman in Europe.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1573">
                  <seg type="reference">Pope, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-07-18.html">1805-07-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly WG is reading here and there in a collection:<lb/> 
                  <author>Pope, Alexander</author>  
                  <author>Warburton, William (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The works of Alexander Pope Esq.: in nine volumes complete.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s sale catalog.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Pope’s (Alex.) Works, with notes by Bp. Warburton, plates, 6 vol.  <date when="1764">1764</date> (item 607).<lb/>Pope’s Works, with notes and illustrations by W. Roscoe 10 vol.  <date when="1824">1824</date> (item 608).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1575">
                  <seg type="reference">Epicene, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-05.html">1805-08-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>Epicoene, or The silent woman</title>  in <title>The workes of Beniamin Jonson. </title>(1<hi rend="superscript">st</hi> volume)  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Jonson’s (Ben) Plays, imp.  <date when="1616">1616</date>—Plays, &amp;c  <date when="1640">1640</date>, imp.; 2 vol. (item 851).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1576">
                  <seg type="reference">Alchemist, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-09.html">1805-08-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The Alchemist. Written by Ben. Ionson.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1577">
                  <seg type="reference">Waller, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-10.html">1805-08-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Waller, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>Poems, &amp;c. written by Ed. Waller of Beckonsfield Esquire: lately a member of the Honourable House of Commons; and printed by copy of his own handwriting; all lyrick poems in this booke were set by Mr. Henry Lavves, Gent. of Kings Chappell, and one of his majesties Private Musick; printed and published according to order.</title>  
                  <date when="1645">1645</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Waller, William</author>  
                  <title>Vindication of the character and conduct of Sir William Waller, … commander in chief of the Parliament forces in the West, explanatory of his conduct in taking up arms against Charles the First. (Written by himself.) and now first published from the original manuscript, with an introduction by the editor.</title>  
                  <date when="1793">1793</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Waller’s (Edm.) Poems, from his own hand-writing  <date when="1645">1645</date> (item 733).<lb/>Waller’s (Sir Will.) vindication of his Character and Conduct, manuscript notes  <date when="1793">1793</date> (item 734).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1578">
                  <seg type="reference">Dryden, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-18.html">1805-08-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following work read by WG on  <date when="1800">1800-06</date>-23:<lb/>See item # <date when="1088">1088</date> Prose Works/Malone for one possible.<lb/> 
                  <author>Dryden, John</author>  
                  <author>Malone, Edmond</author>  
                  <title>The critical and miscellaneous prose works of John Dryden: now first collected: with notes and illustrations; an account of the life and writing of the author, grounded on original and authentick documents; and a collection of his letters, the greater part of which has never before been published.</title>  
                  <date when="1800">1800</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Dryden’s Prose Works, by Malone, portraits, first two volumes  <date when="1800">1800</date> (item 207).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1579">
                  <seg type="reference">Chapman, Iliad, B I/2 (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-21.html">1805-08-21</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Homer</author>  
                  <author>Chapman, George (translator)</author>  
                  <title>The Iliads of Homer, prince of poets. Neuer before in any languag truly translated. With a comment on some of his chiefe places; donne according to the Greeke by Geo. Chapman.</title>  
                  <date when="1611">1611</date>
                  <lb/>(Seven books were published in  <date when="1598">1598</date>, twelve in  <date when="1609">1609</date>.)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1580">
                  <seg type="reference">Killed with Kindness (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-23.html">1805-08-23</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Heywood, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>A woman killed with kindness.</title>  
                  <date when="1607">1607</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1581">
                  <seg type="reference">Bld. – IGNORE, NO ACTION REQUIRED (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-29.html">1805-08-29</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1582">
                  <seg type="reference">Harry, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-08-29.html">1805-08-29</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Richard Lovell</author>  
                  <title>Harry and Lucy. A tale for instruction and amusement of youth.</title>  
                  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Maria (attributed to)</author>  
                  <title>Harry and Lucy, being the first part of Early lessons by the author of the Parent’s assistant. </title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>‘The series “Harry and Lucy” was begun by [Richard Lovell] Edgeworth and his wife Honora; later he was assisted by his daughter Maria who further continued the series as part of her “Early lessons.”’ (Online Dictionary of National Biography)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1583">
                  <seg type="reference">Drayton, Numphidia (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-02.html">1805-09-02</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Drayton, Michael</author>  
                  <title>The works of Michael Drayton: … containing 1. The battle of Agincourt. II. The barons wars. III. England’s heroical epistles. IV. The miseries of Queen Margaret. … V. Nymphidia … VI. The moon-calf. VII. The legends of Robert Duke of Normandy, Matilda the Fair; Pierce Gaveston, and Tho. Cromwell Earl of Essex. VIII. The quest of Cynthia. IX. The shepherd’s Sirena. X. Poly-Olbion, with the annotations of the learned Selden. XI. Elegies on several occasions. XII. Ideas. Being all the writings of that celebrated author, now first collected into one volume.</title>  
                  <date when="1748">1748</date>
                  <lb/>The earliest collection of Drayton’s works is:<lb/> 
                  <title>Poems: By Michaell Draiton Esquire</title>  
                  <date when="1605">1605</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Drayton’s (M.) Poems, new corrected  <date when="1613">1613</date> (item 202).<lb/>Drayton’s Works, Poly-Olbion, &amp;c. 4 vol.  <date when="1753">1753</date> (item  <date when="1753">1753</date>).<lb/>Drayton’s (Mich.) Poly-Olbion, with the maps, and port. of Prince Henry, by Hole (wanting title), no date (item 442).<lb/>Drayton’s (M.) Battle of Agincourt, and other Poems,  <date when="1627">1627</date>—Barons’ Wars, the Owle, Pastorals, &amp;c.  <date when="1619">1619</date>; 2 vol. (item 443).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1584">
                  <seg type="reference">Boileau, Reflexions (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-02.html">1805-09-02</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Boileau Despréaux, Nicolas</author>  
                  <author>Longinus</author>  
                  <author>André Dacier</author>  
                  <author>Charles Rollin</author>  
                  <title>Oeuvres diverse du sieur D***. Avec le Traité du sublime ou du merveilleux dans le discours, traduit du grec de Longin. Et les Reflexions critique sur ce rheteur, ou l’on répond aux objections faites contre quelques anciens.</title>  
                  <date when="1694">1694-1698</date> Nouv. ed. rev. &amp; augm.<lb/>Boileau’s Oeuvres of  <date when="1757">1757</date>, listed in WG’s sale catalog, also include Réflexions critiques sur quelques passages de Longin.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Boileau, ses Oeuvres, 3 vol. Paris,  <date when="1757">1757</date> (item 67).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1585">
                  <seg type="reference">Quarles, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-05.html">1805-09-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Quarles, Francis</author>  
                  <title>Divine poems: The history of Jonah, Ester, Job, Sions sonnets, elegies …</title>  
                  <date when="1630">1630</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Quarles’ (F.) Divine Poems, with Sion’s Sonnets, Elegies, &amp;c.  <date when="1717">1717</date> (item 617).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1586">
                  <seg type="reference">J C Scaligeri Vita (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-14.html">1805-09-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Scaliger, Joseph-Juste</author>  
                  <author>Scaliger, Julius Caesar</author>  
                  <author>Van der Does, Jan (le fils)</author>  
                  <title>Josephi Scaligari Iul. Caes. F. Epistola De vetustate et splendore gentis scaligerae, et Iul. Caes. Scaligeri vita. Iul Caes. Scaligeri Oratio in luctu filioli Audecti: Item testimonia de Gente scaligeri et Iul. Caes. Scaligero. </title>  
                  <date when="1594">1594</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1587">
                  <seg type="reference">Widow’s Tears, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-16.html">1805-09-16</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Chapman, George</author>  
                  <title>The widowwes teares: a comedie. As it was often presented in the blacke and white Friers.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s reading of other works by Chapman at this time.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1588">
                  <seg type="reference">Eastward Hoe, act 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-18.html">1805-09-18</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chapman, George</author>  
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <author>Marston, John</author>  
                  <title>Eastward Hoe. As it was played in the Black-friers. By the Children of her Maiesties Revels.</title>  
                  <date when="1605">1605</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1589">
                  <seg type="reference">Malcontent, act. 1 (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-23.html">1805-09-23</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Marston, John</author>  
                  <title>The malcontent. By Iohn Marston.</title>  
                  <date when="1604">1604</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1590">
                  <seg type="reference">Perdue, p. 147 (<ref target="/diary/1805-09-29.html">1805-09-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Holcroft, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of Bryan Perdue, a novel.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1592">
                  <seg type="reference">Read to M J (<ref target="/diary/1805-11-01.html">1805-11-01</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably WG reading his revision of ‘Camilla.’ ‘Camilla’ is the working title for:<lb/> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Faulkener, A Tragedy</title>.  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1593">
                  <seg type="reference">Newspapers (<ref target="/diary/1805-11-04.html">1805-11-04</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1594">
                  <seg type="reference">Ballard, çala (<ref target="/diary/1805-11-12.html">1805-11-12</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>Possibly Thomas Ballard (fl.  <date when="1698">1698-1754</date>), author of many book and library catalogs.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1595">
                  <seg type="reference">Arcadia, p. 11 (<ref target="/diary/1805-11-27.html">1805-11-27</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Sidney, Sir Philip</author>  
                  <title>The countesse of Pembrokes Arcadia, written by Sir Philippe Sidnei.</title>  
                  <date when="1590">1590</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1596">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Burns, p. 96 (<ref target="/diary/1805-12-04.html">1805-12-04</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify the specific biography of Burns. The following are texts possibly read by WG:<lb/> 
                  <author>Burns, Robert</author>  
                  <author>Cunningham, Allan</author>  
                  <title>The complete works of Robert Burns, containing his poems, songs, and correspondence. Illustrated by W. H. Barltett et al; with a new life of the poet, and notices, critical and biographical by Allan Cunningham.</title>  
                  <date when="1786">1786</date>; a 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edition was published in  <date when="1801">1801</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Heron, Robert</author>  
                  <title>A memoir of the life of the late Robert Burns; written by Robert Heron.</title>  
                  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>The works of Robert Burns: with an account of his life, and a criticism of his writings. To which are prefixed some observations on the character and condition of the Scottish.</title>  (4 volumes)  <date when="1800">1800</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1597">
                  <seg type="reference">Sad Shepherd (<ref target="/diary/1805-12-26.html">1805-12-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  
                  <title>The sad shepherd</title>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson, 3</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">rd</hi>
                  <title> volume</title>  
                  <date when="1641">1641</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te0980">
                  <seg type="reference">Eutropius, w. C C, 25 days (<ref target="/diary/1805-12-27.html">1805-12-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Eutropius (4</author>
                  <hi rend="bold superscript">th</hi>
                  <author> century)</author>  
                  <title>Eutropii Historia Romanae breviarum ab urbe condita usq </title>  
                  <title>(A breviary of Roman history from the building of Rome …)</title> c. 369 A.D.<lb/>
                  <pb/> Annotated Titles  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1598">
                  <seg type="reference">Cumberland, p. 115 (<ref target="/diary/1806-01-10.html">1806-01-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cumberland, Richard</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of Richard Cumberland</title>.  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on match between number of pages in text and number of pages WG reads to finish.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1599">
                  <seg type="reference">Morland, p. 72 (<ref target="/diary/1806-01-23.html">1806-01-23</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Morland, Sir Samuel</author>  
                  <title>The history of the evangelical churches of the valleys of Piemont: Containing a most exact geographical description of the place, and a faithfull account of the doctrine, life, and persecutions of the ancient inhabitants. Together with a most naked and punctual relation of the late bloudy massacres,  <date when="1655">1655</date>. And a narrative of all the following transactions, to the year of our Lord,  <date when="1658">1658</date>. All which are justified, partly by divers ancient manuscripts written many hundred years before Calvin or Luther, and partly by other most authentick attestations: the true original of the greatest part whereof, are to be seen in their proper languages by all the curious in the publick library of the famous University of Cambridge.</title>  
                  <date when="1658">1658</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s History of the Commonwealth cites:<lb/>Morland, History of Evangelical Churches in Piedmont (7:205).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1600">
                  <seg type="reference">Sleeper Awake, pp. 65 (<ref target="/diary/1806-01-31.html">1806-01-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1601">
                  <seg type="reference">Leonora, p. 93 (<ref target="/diary/1806-02-04.html">1806-02-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Maria</author>  
                  <title>Leonora</title>.  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1602">
                  <seg type="reference">Cromwel, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-02-08.html">1806-02-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Although earlier biographies of Cromwell were published, WG possibly read one of the following (see his sale catalog):<lb/> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>The life of Oliver Cromwel, L. Protector of the Common-Wealth of England, Scotland and Ireland. Being an account of all the battles[,] sieges, and other military atchievements wherein he was engaged in these three nations. And likewise, of his civil administration, while he had the supream government, till his death. Relating matters of fact, without partiality.</title>  
                  <date when="1724">1724</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Kimber, Isaac</author>  
                  <title>The life of Oliver Cromwell Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. Impartially collected from the best historians, and several original manuscripts.</title>  
                  <date when="1724">1724</date>
                  <lb/> The  <date when="1742">1742</date> 
                  <title>The life of Oliver Cromwell Lord-Protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland. The fifth edition. By M. Morgan Gent.</title> is ‘substantially the same as’ the text attributed to Isaac Kimber. (WC) OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Nickolls, John (editor)</author>  
                  <title>Original letters and papers of state, attributed to Oliver Cromwell; concerning the affairs of Great Britain. From the year MDCXLIX to MDCLVIII. Found among the political collections of Mr. John Milton. Now first published from the originals</title>.  <date when="1743">1743</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Cromwell:--Life of Oliver Cromwell, Lord Protector, port. by Vertue  <date when="1724">1724</date> (item 167).<lb/>Cromwell:--Life of Oliver Cromwell, Law Protector, by M. Morgan, Gent. made perfect by manuscript  <date when="1742">1742</date> (item 169).<lb/>Cromwell:--Letters and Papers of State addressed to Cromwell, found among the Political Collections of John Milton, published by Jo. Nickolls  <date when="1743">1743</date> (item 437)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1603">
                  <seg type="reference">Hesiod, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-02-25.html">1806-02-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Hesiod</author> (8<hi rend="superscript">th</hi>-7<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century B.C.)  <title>Theogony.</title> or<lb/> 
                  <title>Works and days.</title> date unknown<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1604">
                  <seg type="reference">Cochrane Johnson, p. 50 (<ref target="/diary/1806-02-26.html">1806-02-26</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/> 
                  <date when="1605">1605</date>. Anacharasis, 35 pp.<lb/> 
                  <date when="1806">1806-03</date>-05<lb/> 
                  <author>Barthélémi, Jean Jaques</author>
                  <seg> </seg> Voyage du jeune Anacharsis en Grecs.<lb/>DATE?<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1606">
                  <seg type="reference">Cicero de Natura Deorum, c. 8 (<ref target="/diary/1806-03-10.html">1806-03-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cicero, Marcus Tullius</author>  
                  <title>De Natura Deorum (On the nature of the gods)</title> written c. 45 B.C.<lb/> 
                  <date when="1607">1607</date>. Barthelemi, çala<lb/> 
                  <date when="1806">1806-03</date>-11<lb/> 
                  <author>Barthélémi, Jean Jaques </author>  
                  <title>D’Anacharsis ou lettres d’un troubadour sur cet ouvrage: Suivies de 2 notices analytiques, et de l’epitre de M. de Fontanesa</title>.  <date when="1789">1789</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Barthélémi, Jean Jaques</author>  
                  <author>Beaumont, William (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Travels of Anacharsis the younger in Greece: during the middle of the fourth century before the Christian aera</title>.  <date when="1790">1790-1791</date>
                  <lb/>In French:<lb/> 
                  <author>Barthélémi, Jean Jaques</author>
                  <seg> </seg> Voyage du jeune Anacharsis en Grecs.<lb/>DATE?<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1608">
                  <seg type="reference">Manor House, p. 120 (<ref target="/diary/1806-03-19.html">1806-03-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Smith, Charlotte Turner</author>  
                  <title>The old manor house. A novel, in four volumes. By Charlotte Smith.</title>  
                  <date when="1793">1793</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te0049">
                  <seg type="reference">Marmontel, p. 86 (<ref target="/diary/1806-03-20.html">1806-03-20</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Marmontel, Jean François</author>  
                  <title>Nouveaux contes moraux.</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date>
                  <lb/> The first edition of <title>Contes Moraux</title> ( <date when="1761">1761</date>) was published in two volumes only.  In the  <date when="1792">1792</date> (printed for J. Bew) English translation there were 4 volumes.   OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Marmontel, Jean François</author>  
                  <title>Mémoires</title>,  volumes 1-4 of <title>Oeuvres posthumes de Marmontel, … imprimees sur la manuscrit autographe de l’auteur.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>Eleven volumes were published between  <date when="1804">1804-1806</date> (volumes 1-4 published in  <date when="1804">1804</date>) and notes the following: ‘I-IV. Mémoires; V-VI. Régence du duc d’Orléans; VII. Logique; VIII. Métaphysique; IX. Morale; X. Grammaire; XI. Mélanges.’<lb/>WG reads a 4-volume work by or about Marmontel between  <date when="1806">1806-03</date>-20 and  <date when="1806">1806-04</date>-03.  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1609">
                  <seg type="reference">Catalogue, H S (<ref target="/diary/1806-03-30.html">1806-03-30</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1610">
                  <seg type="reference">Patch’s Trial, pp. 76 (<ref target="/diary/1806-04-12.html">1806-04-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Great Britain. Court of Exchequer</author>  
                  <title>The trial of Richard Patch for the wilful murder of Mr. Isaac Blight, on the 23d of Sept.  <date when="1805">1805</date>, at Rotherhithe, in the county of Surrey, before the Right Hon. sir A. Macdonald, knt., Lord Chief Baron of His Majesty’s Court of Exchequer, at the Session House, Newington, Surrey, on Saturday, April 5,  <date when="1805">1805</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>Taken in short hand by Blanchard and Ramsey.<lb/>Also see WG’s entry ‘Cha. Price, pp. 56’ on  <date when="1793">1793-10</date>-25.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1611">
                  <seg type="reference">Warwick, p. 134 (<ref target="/diary/1806-04-13.html">1806-04-13</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Warwick, Sir Philip</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of the reign of King Charles I. … Together with a continuation to the happy restauration of King Charles II. By Sir Philip Warwick, … Published from the original manuscript with an alphabetical table.</title>  
                  <date when="1701">1701</date>?<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Warwick’s (Sir P.) Memoirs of the Reign of Charles I  <date when="1701">1701</date> (item 741)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1612">
                  <seg type="reference">P Knight, p. 34 (<ref target="/diary/1806-04-26.html">1806-04-26</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Knight, Richard Payne</author>  
                  <title>A monody, occasioned by the death of the Right Hon. Charles James Fox …: dedicated to the Right Hon. Edward, Earl of Oxford; with notes, political and biographical.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>Since this is WG’s only entry in this year for Richard Payne Knight, it is likely he is reading a brief item by this author.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1613">
                  <seg type="reference">Raleigh, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-04-28.html">1806-04-28</ref>)
                    </seg>Cayley, junior, Arthur<lb/> 
                  <title>The life of Sir Walter Ralegh, knt.</title>  
                  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Raleigh, Sir Walter</author>  
                  <title>The works of Sir Walter Raleigh kt. political, commercial, and philosophical; together with his letters and poems. … To which is prefix’d, a new account of his life by Tho. Birch, M.A. F.R.S. …</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Raleigh, Sir Walter</author>  
                  <title>The historie of the world in five bookes … by Sir Walter Ralegh.</title>  
                  <date when="1614">1614</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Raleigh Life of, by Arthur Cayley, jun., 2 vol.  <date when="1806">1806</date> (item 621).<lb/>Raleigh’s (Sir W.) Works, Letters, and Poems, with Life by T. Birch, port. 2 vol.  <date when="1751">1751</date> (item 619)<lb/>Ralegh’s (Sir W.) History of the World, port.  <date when="1652">1652</date> (item 879)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1614">
                  <seg type="reference">Mutabilitie, C. I (<ref target="/diary/1806-05-12.html">1806-05-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>The faerie queene: disposed into XII books, fashioning twelue morall vertues.</title>  
                  <date when="1609">1609</date>
                  <lb/>The Mutability Cantos of Book VII were first published in the first folio ( <date when="1609">1609</date>).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1615">
                  <seg type="reference">Spartan Dame, acts 1 &amp; 2 (<ref target="/diary/1806-05-29.html">1806-05-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Southerne, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The Spartan dame. A tragedy. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal in Drury Lane, by His Majesty’s servants. By Mr. Southerne.</title>  
                  <date when="1719">1719</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1616">
                  <seg type="reference">Edgworth, Moral Tales, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-05-30.html">1806-05-30</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Edgeworth, Maria</author>  
                  <title>Moral tales for young people. By Maria Edgeworth. </title>(3 volumes)  <date when="1802">1802</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1617">
                  <seg type="reference">Shelton’s D Quixote, p. 46 (<ref target="/diary/1806-06-05.html">1806-06-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de</author>  
                  <author>Shelton, Thomas (translator)</author>  
                  <title>The history of the valorovs and wittie-knight-errant, Don-Qvixote, of the Mancha.</title>  
                  <date when="1612">1612</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1618">
                  <seg type="reference">Newspapers. (<ref target="/diary/1806-06-17.html">1806-06-17</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1619">
                  <seg type="reference">Dermody, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1806-08-03.html">1806-08-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Raymond, James Grant</author>  
                  <title>The life of Thomas Dermody: interspersed with pieces of original poetry, many exhibiting unexampled prematurity of genuine poetical talent; and containing a series of correspondence with several eminent characters. By James Grant Raymond. In two volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>This appears to be the only two-volume work by or on Dermody.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1620">
                  <seg type="reference">Buncle, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1806-08-07.html">1806-08-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Amory, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The life of John Buncle, Esq: containing various observations and reflections, made in several parts of the world; and many extraordinary relations</title>. (2 volumes)  <date when="1756">1756</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1621">
                  <seg type="reference">Psyche (<ref target="/diary/1806-08-18.html">1806-08-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following work, first recorded on  <date when="1793">1793-09</date>-19:<lb/> 
                  <author>Moliére, Jean-Baptiste Poquelin</author>  
                  <title>Psiche, tragedie-ballet.</title>  
                  <date when="1671">1671</date>; first performed  <date when="1671">1671</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1622">
                  <seg type="reference">Paradise Lost, B. I (<ref target="/diary/1806-08-29.html">1806-08-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Paradise lost. A poem written in ten books by John Milton.</title>  
                  <date when="1667">1667</date> quarto<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Paradise lost: A poem in twelve books. The author John Milton … revised and augmented by the same author</title>.  <date when="1674">1674</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1623">
                  <seg type="reference">Wortley M, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1806-08-29.html">1806-08-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Montagu, Mary Wortley, Lady</author>  
                  <title>The works of the Right Honourable Lady Mary Wortley Montagu, including her correspondence, poems and essays, published by permission from her genuine papers. In five volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>WG reads vols. I, III, IV, V<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1624">
                  <seg type="reference">Browne’s Pastorals, p. 22 (<ref target="/diary/1806-10-03.html">1806-10-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Browne, William</author>  
                  <title>Britannia’s pastorals.</title>  
                  <date when="1613">1613</date> (Book I);  <date when="1616">1616</date> (Book II);  <date when="1625">1625</date> (both books)<lb/>WG probably read this work in the following edition:<lb/> 
                  <author>Browne, William</author>  
                  <title>The works of William Browne. Containing Britannia’s pastorals: with notes … by the Rev. W. Thompson … The shepherd’s pipe: … The Inner-Temple masque, never published before; and other poems. With the life of the author.  In three volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1772">1772</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Browne’s (Will.) Britannia’s Pastorals, Shepherd’s Pipe, and other Works, 3 vol.  <date when="1772">1772</date> (item 84)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1625">
                  <seg type="reference">Dutens, Vol. I (<ref>1806-10-2</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <date when="1806">1806-10</date>-2<lb/>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Dutens, L.</author>  
                  <title>Memoires d’un voyer qui se repose.  </title>(3 volumes)  <date when="1807">1807</date>: 3<hi rend="superscript">rd</hi> edition<lb/>In English:<lb/> 
                  <author>Dutens, L.</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of a traveller, now in retirement: interspersed with historical, literary, and political anecdotes, relative to many of the principal personalges of the present age.</title> (5 volumes)  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>Volume 5 has the title Dutensiana; intended as a sequel to the Memoirs of a traveller.)<lb/>WG reads a 4-volume work by Dutens.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1626">
                  <seg type="reference">Last Minstrel, C. I, II, III (<ref target="/diary/1806-11-03.html">1806-11-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Scott, Sir Walter</author>  
                  <title>The lay of the last minstrel.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1628">
                  <seg type="reference">Macklin, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-11-25.html">1806-11-25</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Cooke, William</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of Charles, comedian; with the dramatic characters, manners, anecdotes, &amp;c. of the age in which he lived: forming an history of the stage during almost the whole of the last century. And a chronological list of the parts played by him.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>Another edition was published in  <date when="1806">1806</date>.<lb/>Conjecture based on date of publication. WG reads ‘Macklin’ only on this date ( <date when="1806">1806-11</date>-25) and the following day.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1629">
                  <seg type="reference">Shakespear Tales, fin. (<ref target="/diary/1806-12-01.html">1806-12-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Lamb, Charles</author>  
                  <author>Lamb, Mary</author>  
                  <author>Mulready, William (illustrator)</author>  
                  <title>Tales from Shakespeare: designed for the use of young persons.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>‘The ten plates in each volume were engraved by William Blake from designs by William Mulready.’ (WC)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1630">
                  <seg type="reference">Ath. Ox., &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1806-12-08.html">1806-12-08</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Wood, Anthony à</author>  
                  <title>Athenae Oxonienses.</title>  
                  <date when="1691">1691</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1631">
                  <seg type="reference">Newspapers (<ref target="/diary/1806-12-13.html">1806-12-13</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1632">
                  <seg type="reference">Richardson on Milton, çala (<ref target="/diary/1806-12-16.html">1806-12-16</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Richardson, Jonathan</author>  
                  <title>Explanatory notes and remarks on Milton’s Paradise lost.</title>  
                  <date when="1734">1734</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Milton: Explanatory notes and Remarks on the Paradise Lost, by Richardson  <date when="1734">1734</date> (item 542)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1633">
                  <seg type="reference">Mongomery’s Poems (<ref target="/diary/1806-12-30.html">1806-12-30</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Montgomery, James</author>  
                  <title>The wanderer of Switzerland, and other poems.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>
                  <pb/>Annotated Titles  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1634">
                  <seg type="reference">Wild Irish Girl, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1807-01-05.html">1807-01-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Owenson, Sydney, Lady Morgan</author>  
                  <title>The wild Irish girl, a national tale.</title>  
                  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1635">
                  <seg type="reference">Piccolomini, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1807-01-14.html">1807-01-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Schiller, Friedrich</author>  
                  <author>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Wallenstein: A Drama in Two Parts … The Piccolomini, or the First Part of Wallenstein: A Drama in Five Acts … The Death of Wallenstein: A Tragedy in Five Acts. Translated from the German of Frederick Schiller by S. T. Coleridge.</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1636">
                  <seg type="reference">Wallestein, fin. (<ref target="/diary/1807-01-22.html">1807-01-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Schiller, Friedrich</author>  
                  <author>Coleridge, Samuel Taylor (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Wallenstein: A Drama in Two Parts: The Piccolomini, or the First Part of Wallenstein: A Drama in Five Acts. The Death of Wallenstein: A Tragedy in Five Acts. Translated from the German of Frederick Schiller by S. T. Coleridge.</title>  
                  <date when="1800">1800</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1637">
                  <seg type="reference">Bligh’s Voyage, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-01-28.html">1807-01-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Bligh, William</author>  
                  <title>A narrative of the mutiny on board His Majesty’s ship Bounty; and the subsequent voyage of part of the crew, in the ship’s boat, from Tofoa, one of the Friendly Islands, to Timor, a Dutch settlement in the East-Indies.</title>  
                  <date when="1790">1790</date> (first edition)<lb/>The  <date when="1792">1792</date> edition reads:<lb/> 
                  <title>A voyage to the South Sea, undertaken by command of His Majesty, for the purpose of conveying the bread-fruit tree to the West Indies in His Majesty’s ship the Bounty, commanded by Lieutenant William Bligh; Including an account of the mutiny on board the said ship, and the susequent voyage[etc. as above].</title>  
                  <date when="1792">1792</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1638">
                  <seg type="reference">Hudibras, C. I (<ref target="/diary/1807-02-04.html">1807-02-04</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Butler, Samuel</author>  
                  <title>Hudibras: … Written in the time of the late wars. Corrected and amended with several additions and annotations.</title>  
                  <date when="1684">1684</date>
                  <lb/>This is the first edition of the three books published together in one. Separately, they appeared in  <date when="1663">1663</date>,  <date when="1664">1664</date>,  <date when="1678">1678</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1639">
                  <seg type="reference">Jonson’s Masks, p. 54 (<ref target="/diary/1807-02-11.html">1807-02-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  in <title>The workes of Beniamin Ionson.</title>  
                  <date when="1616">1616</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Jonson, Ben</author>  in <title>The workes of Benjamin Jonson.</title>  
                  <date when="1640">1640</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1640">
                  <seg type="reference">Edward II, acts 1, 2, 3 (<ref target="/diary/1807-02-21.html">1807-02-21</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Marlowe, Christopher</author>  
                  <title>Edward the second. The troublesome raigne and lamentable death of Edward the second, King of England: with the tragicall fall of proud Mortimer: as it was sundrie times publiquely acted in the honourable citie of London, by the most honourable the Earle of Pembroke his seruants. Written by Chri. Marlow Gent.</title>  
                  <date when="1594">1594</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1641">
                  <seg type="reference">Mustapha, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1807-02-23.html">1807-02-23</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Greville, Fulke, Baron Brooke (published anonymously)</author>  
                  <title>The tragedy of Mustapha</title>.  <date when="1609">1609</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1642">
                  <seg type="reference">Gorboduc, act 1 (<ref target="/diary/1807-02-28.html">1807-02-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Norton, Thomas</author>  
                  <author>Sackville, Thomas, Earl of Dorset</author>  
                  <title>The tragedie of Gorboduc, whereof three actes were wrytten by Thomas Nortone, and the two laste by Thomas Sackuyle. Sette for the as the same was shewed before the Quenes most excellent Maiestie, in her highnes court of Whitehall, the .xviij. day of January, anno Domini . <date when="1561">1561</date>. By the Gentlemen of thynner Temple in London.</title>  
                  <date when="1565">1565</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1643">
                  <seg type="reference">Campaspe, acts 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1807-03-12.html">1807-03-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Lyly, John (published anonymously)</author>  
                  <title>A moste excellent comedie of Alexander, Campaspe and Diogenes played beefore the Queene Maiestie on twelfe day at night, by her Maiesties children, and the children of Poules [Paul’s]; Alexander and Campaspe; Campaspe; Tragicall comedie of Alexander and Campaspe.</title>  
                  <date when="1584">1584</date>
                  <lb/>(Later editions titled Campaspe.)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1644">
                  <seg type="reference">Search, pp. 83 (<ref target="/diary/1807-03-16.html">1807-03-16</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify with certainty. WG often used ‘pp.’ to indicate that the total number of pages read was the same as the total number of pages in the item. In the present case no item with the requisite number of pages has been found. Possibly WG reads only 83 pages in one of the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Search, Edward (i.e. Tucker, Abraham)</author>  
                  <author>Hazlitt, William (editor)</author>  
                  <title>An abridgement of The light of nature pursued.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>550+ pages<lb/>The unabridged version, by Abraham Tucker, was originally published, in seven volumes, under the name of Edward Search, esq.’<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Search, Edward (i.e. Tucker, Abraham</author>)  <title>Freewill, foreknowledge, and fate; a fragment, by Edward Search.</title>  
                  <date when="1763">1763</date>
                  <lb/>268 pages<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Search, Simon</author>  
                  <title>The spirit of the times. In a series of observations on the important events of the age. Politics. By Simon Search. Containing an account of the English commemoration of the first anniversary of the French Revolution in a letter to Jos. Priestley.</title>  
                  <date when="1790">1790-1</date>
                  <lb/>252 pages<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1645">
                  <seg type="reference">Milton (Todd), çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-03-27.html">1807-03-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <author>Todd, Henry John</author>  
                  <title>The poetical works of John Milton, … with the principal notes of various commentators, to which are added illustrations, with some account of the life of Milton by … Henry John Todd, …</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date> London: J. Johnson<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1646">
                  <seg type="reference">Paradise Regd B. I (<ref target="/diary/1807-03-30.html">1807-03-30</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably the Todd edition recorded on  <date when="1807">1807-03</date>-27:<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <author>Todd, Henry John</author>  
                  <title>The poetical works of John Milton, … with the principal notes of various commentators, to which are added illustrations, with some account of the life of Milton by … Henry John Todd, …</title>  
                  <date when="1801">1801</date>
                  <lb/>The earliest edition is:<lb/> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>Paradise regain’d, a poem in IV books: to which is added Samson Agonistes.</title>  
                  <date when="1671">1671</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists: <lb/>Paradise Regained, &amp;c. fourth edition, Mason,  <date when="1705">1705</date>.<lb/>Paradise Regained, &amp;c. eighth edition,  <date when="1743">1743</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1647">
                  <seg type="reference">Doctrine of Divorce, p. 11 (<ref target="/diary/1807-04-06.html">1807-04-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Milton, John</author>  
                  <title>The doctrine and discipline of divorce restored to the good of both sexes, from the bondage of canon law, and other mistakes, to Christian freedom, guided by the rule of charity. Wherein also many places of Scripture, have recover’d their long-lost meaning: seasonable to be now thought on in the reformation intended.</title>  
                  <date when="1643">1643</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1648">
                  <seg type="reference">Spenser, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-04-09.html">1807-04-09</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly WG reads one of the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>A view of the state of Ireland, written dialogue-wise betweene Eudoxus and Irenaeus, in the year  <date when="1596">1596</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1633">1633</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>The faerie queene. Disposed into twelue books, fashioning XII. morall vertues.</title>  
                  <date when="1590">1590</date>;  <date when="1609">1609</date> with the Mutability cantos.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <author>Warton, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Observations on the fairy queen of Spenser.</title>  
                  <date when="1762">1762</date>
                  <lb/>WG could be reading the new  <date when="1807">1807</date> edition.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Spenser’s (Edm.) View of the State of Ireland, temp. Elizabeth Dubl.  <date when="1763">1763</date> (item 693).<lb/>Spenser’s Faerie Queene, with notes by Ralph Church, 4 vol.  <date when="1758">1758</date> (item 694).<lb/>Spenser:--Observations on the Faerie Queene, by T. Warton, manuscript notes by W. Huggins, translator of Ariosto  <date when="1754">1754</date> (item 695).<lb/>Spenser: Observations on the Faerie Queene, by T. Warton, 2 vol.  <date when="1807">1807</date> (item 696).<lb/>Spenser’s Faerie Queene, Twelve Bookes, Fashioning twelve Morall Vertues, russia  <date when="1609">1609</date> (item 894).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1649">
                  <seg type="reference">Literary History, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-04-18.html">1807-04-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Sainte-Palaye, M. de La Curne de</author>  
                  <author>Dobson, Susannah (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The literary history of the troubadours. Containing their lives, extracts from their works, and many particulars relative to the customs, morals, and history of the twelfth and thirteenth centuries. Collected and abridged from the French, by the author of the Life of Petrarch [Susannah Dobson].</title>  
                  <date when="1779">1779</date>; republished in  <date when="1807">1807</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1650">
                  <seg type="reference">Caleb Williams, Vol. I (<ref target="/diary/1807-04-27.html">1807-04-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Godwin, William</author>  
                  <title>Things as They Are; or, the adventures of Caleb Williams. In three volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1794">1794</date>;  <date when="1797">1797</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1651">
                  <seg type="reference">Spenser’s Ireland, p. 60 (<ref target="/diary/1807-05-01.html">1807-05-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>A view of the state of Ireland, written dialogue-wise betweene Eudoxus and Irenaeus, in the year  <date when="1596">1596</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1633">1633</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists several items by Spenser, including:<lb/>Spenser’s (Edm.) View of the State of Ireland, temp. Elizabeth Dubl.  <date when="1763">1763</date> (item 693).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1652">
                  <seg type="reference">Winter in London, p. 77 (<ref target="/diary/1807-05-09.html">1807-05-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Surr, T. S. (Skinner, Thomas)</author>  
                  <title>A winter in London, or, sketches of fashion: a novel</title>. (3 volumes)  <date when="1806">1806</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1654">
                  <seg type="reference">Tooke v. Paul, pp. 22 (<ref target="/diary/1807-05-12.html">1807-05-12</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Tooke, John Horne</author>  
                  <title>A letter to the editor of The Times</title>. [‘On the political connexion between J. Paul and Sir F. Burdett.’]  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1656">
                  <seg type="reference">Faux Dauphin, 2 Vs. (<ref target="/diary/1807-05-29.html">1807-05-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Beauchamp, Alphonse de (published anonymously)</author>  
                  <title>Le faux Dauphin actuellement en France, ou Histoire d’un imposteur, se disant le dernier fils de Louis XVI. Rédigée sur des pièces authentiques, et notamment sur le jugement du Tribunal Criminel du Département de la Marne, du 13 germinal dernier; précédée d’une analyse rapide des révolutions occasionnées par les imposteurs les plus célèbres, qui ont usurpé la qualité de prince, de roi ou d’empereur.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1803">1803</date> 
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1658">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; P Pilgrim (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-05.html">1807-06-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Shakespeare, William</author>  
                  <title>The passionate pilgrime. By W. Shakespeare.</title>  
                  <date when="1599">1599</date>
                  <lb/>Some of the poems are not by Shakespeare (Norton).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1659">
                  <seg type="reference">Venus &amp; Adonis (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-06.html">1807-06-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Shakespeare, William</author>  
                  <title>Venus and Adonis.</title>  
                  <date when="1593">1593</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1660">
                  <seg type="reference">Daniel, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-09.html">1807-06-09</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>  
                  <title>Delia. Contayning certaine sonnets: vvith The complaint of Rosamond.</title>  
                  <date when="1592">1592</date>
                  <lb/> This is the earliest printing of <title>Rosamond</title>, which WG is reading on  <date when="1807">1807-06</date>-11. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1661">
                  <seg type="reference">Jonathas (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-09.html">1807-06-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Ceriziers, René de</author>  
                  <title>Jonathas, ou le Vray ami par le Sr de Ceriziers.</title>  
                  <date when="1645">1645</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Duché de Vancy, Joseph-François</author>  
                  <title>Jonathas, tragédie tirée de l’Écriture sainte, dédiée au roy.</title>  
                  <date when="1700">1700</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Bretonneau, François et al. (published anonymously)</author>  
                  <title>David et Jonathas: tragedie en musique, qui sera representée sur le théatre du college de Louis le Grand, le XXVIII. février.</title>  
                  <date when="1688">1688</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author> (later edition? Pierre Brumoy)  <title>Jonathas et David, ou triomphe de l’amité, tragédie, sera representée par les pensionnaires du collège de Louis le Grand, le … 23e de mai  <date when="1735">1735</date>…</title>  
                  <date when="1735">1735</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1662">
                  <seg type="reference">Lover’s Complaint (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-10.html">1807-06-10</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Shakespeare, William</author> ‘A Lover’s Complaint’ <lb/> in <title>Shake-speares Sonnets.</title>  
                  <date when="1609">1609</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1663">
                  <seg type="reference">Daniel, Rosamond (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-11.html">1807-06-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Daniel, Samuel</author>  
                  <title>Delia. Contayning certaine sonnets: vvith The complaint of Rosamond.</title>  
                  <date when="1592">1592</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1664">
                  <seg type="reference">Burdet, pp. 5 (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-19.html">1807-06-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly one of the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Burdet, Thomas (editor and publisher)</author>  
                  <author>Charles I, King of England</author>  
                  <title>His Majesties speech to the peers of Scotland; concerning presbyteriall government. With the answer of the Scottish nobility to his Majesty at Newcastle. Together with a brief relation, of another defeat given to the rebels in the north of Ireland, by the British army, since the breaking off of the treaty at Dublin. Also the Lord Lisles propositions concerning that kingdom. </title>  
                  <date when="1646">1646</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Burdet, John</author>  
                  <title>The resolution of the Prince of Wales, concerning the landing of his army in the Isle of Loving-land, within the county of Suffolk, and his propositions to all Englishmen, concerning his engagement for King, city, &amp; kingdom against the army, &amp; to fight for their liberties, freedom &amp; priviledges. Likevvise, the further proceedings of the Royall Navie, under his Highness the D. of York, and the declaration of the seamen in the Isle of VVight and Portsmouth, concerning the Kings Majesty and the Fleet Royall.</title>  
                  <date when="1648">1648</date>
                  <lb/>Both of these items are 6 pages in length, the closest match with the length of WG’s reading.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1665">
                  <seg type="reference">Malone, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-25.html">1807-06-25</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following, first recorded on  <date when="1792">1792-07</date>-30:<lb/> 
                  <author>Malone, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>An attempt to ascertain the order in which the plays of Shakespeare were written</title>,  in <title>The plays of William Shakespeare, with notes by Samuel Johnson and George Steevens</title>, edited by Isaac Reed, 2<hi rend="superscript">nd</hi> edn. revised and augmented, 10 vols, vol. 1.   <date when="1778">1778</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Shakespeare’s Plays and Poems, with notes by Malone, 16 vo. Dubl,  <date when="1794">1794</date>.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1666">
                  <seg type="reference">Hazlit, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-06-30.html">1807-06-30</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Hazlitt, William</author>  
                  <title>A reply to the essay on population, by the Rev. T. R. Malthus. In a series of letters.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>See  <date when="1807">1807-08</date>-01, where WG possibly continues reading what he is skimming on  <date when="1807">1807-06</date>-30.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1668">
                  <seg type="reference">Hazlit to Malthus, p. 118 (<ref target="/diary/1807-08-01.html">1807-08-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Hazlitt, William</author>  
                  <title>A reply to the essay on population, by the Rev. T. R. Malthus. In a series of letters.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1669">
                  <seg type="reference">Paul, pp. 219 (<ref target="/diary/1807-08-20.html">1807-08-20</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work. Possibly the person Horne Tooke disputes with in the item cited in WG diary  <date when="1807">1807-05</date>-12.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1670">
                  <seg type="reference">Woodland, Vol. 1 &amp; 4 (<ref target="/diary/1807-08-22.html">1807-08-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Woodland, Miss M.</author>  
                  <title>Tales for mothers and daughters.</title> (4 volumes)  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1671">
                  <seg type="reference">Goldsmith, An. Nature, p. 68 (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-01.html">1807-09-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Goldsmith, Oliver</author>  
                  <title>An history of the earth, and animated nature.</title>  
                  <date when="1774">1774</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1672">
                  <seg type="reference">Seneca, cap. 1-10 (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-04.html">1807-09-04</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>  [<title>Moral Essays</title>] c. 41-59 A.D.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1673">
                  <seg type="reference">Seneca, Prov. cap. 1 &amp; 2 (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-07.html">1807-09-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>  
                  <title>L. Annaei Senecae Dialogorum, Liber I: Ad Lucilium, Qvare aliqva incommoda bonis viris accidant, cvm providentia sit (De Providentia) [The Dialogues, Book I: To Lucilius, Why, though there is a Providence, some Misfortunes befall Good Men]</title> c. 41-42 A.D.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1674">
                  <seg type="reference">Colin Clout (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-07.html">1807-09-07</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>Colin Clovts come home againe</title>.  <date when="1595">1595</date> London: VVilliam Ponsonbie<lb/>WC<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1675">
                  <seg type="reference">Spencer, Hymns (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-09.html">1807-09-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund</author>  
                  <title>Fowre hymnes.</title>  
                  <date when="1596">1596</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1676">
                  <seg type="reference">Just Italian (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-16.html">1807-09-16</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>D’Avenant, Sir William</author>  
                  <title>The iust Italian.</title>  
                  <date when="1630">1630</date>
                  <lb/> WG may have read this item in a collection of D’Avenant’s works.  The earliest collection containing <title>The just Italian</title> as well as <title>Gondibert</title> (read  <date when="1807">1807-09</date>-18) is the following:  <author>D’Avenant, Sir William</author>  
                  <title>The works of Sir William D’Avenant: consisting of those which were formerly printed and those which he design’d for the press now published out of the authors originall copies.</title> [ <date when="1672">1672</date>]- <date when="1673">1673</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1677">
                  <seg type="reference">Davenant, çala (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-16.html">1807-09-16</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>D’Avenant, Sir William</author>  
                  <title>The works of Sir William D’Avenant: consisting of those which were formerly printed and those which he design’d for the press now published out of the authors originall copies.</title> [ <date when="1672">1672</date>]- <date when="1673">1673</date>
                  <lb/> The preceding is the first edition of D’Avenant’s works and probably the same source for his reading of <title>The just Italian</title> on  <date when="1807">1807-09</date>-16 and <title>Gondibert</title> on  <date when="1807">1807-09</date>-18. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1678">
                  <seg type="reference">Seneca, De Brevitate, c. 4 (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-18.html">1807-09-18</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Seneca, Lucius Annaeus</author>  
                  <title>Ad Pavlinvm: De brevitate vitae (To Paulinus: On the shortness of life)</title> c. 58-59 A.D.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1679">
                  <seg type="reference">Gondibert, C. I, II (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-18.html">1807-09-18</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>D’Avenant, Sir William</author>  
                  <title>Gondibert: an heroick poem</title>  in <title>The works of Sir William D’Avenant: consisting of those which were formerly printed and those which he design’d for the press now published out of the authors originall copies.</title> [ <date when="1672">1672</date>]- <date when="1673">1673</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1680">
                  <seg type="reference">Crispianus (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-19.html">1807-09-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^1681. Lamb’s Ulysses, p. 124 (<ref target="/diary/1807-09-22.html">1807-09-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Lamb, Charles</author>  
                  <title>The adventures of Ulysses.</title>  
                  <date when="1808">1808</date>
                  <lb/>Printed by T. Davison for the Juvenile Library<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1682">
                  <seg type="reference">Vertot, Portugal, p. 56 (<ref target="/diary/1807-12-29.html">1807-12-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Vertot, Rene Aubert de Vertot, abbe de</author>  
                  <title>The history of the revolution in Portugal, in the year,  <date when="1640">1640</date>. Or, An account of their revolt from Spain, and setting the crown on the head of Don John of Braganza, father to Don Pedro, the present king, and Catharine Queen Dowager of England. Written in French by the excellent pen of the Abbot Vertat [sic], (author of the History of the revolution of Sweden) and done into English.</title>  
                  <date when="1700">1700</date>
                  <lb/>In French:<lb/> 
                  <author>Vertot, Rene Aubert de Vertot, abbe de</author>  
                  <title>Histoire de la conjuration de Portugal en  <date when="1640">1640</date>.</title>  
                  <date when="1689">1689</date>
                  <lb/>Later editions, enlarged, were published under the titles: Histoire des révolutions de Portugal and Révolutions de Portugal.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Vertot, Revolutions de Portugal, Syede, la Republique Romaine, &amp;c. 11 vol. (item 722).<lb/>
                  <pb/>Annotated Titles  <date when="1808">1808</date>
                  <lb/>Annotated as follows:<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="teNaN">
                  <seg type="reference">^ indicates start of item; item has been assigned most probable identity. (<ref>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.</ref>)
                    </seg>Where several identities are equally probable, all are given.<lb/>Where no identity could be assigned, that is indicated.<lb/>Item Number: also appears in the diary transcription <lb/>wherever WG refers to the same title, with the following exceptions:<lb/>when the identification is one of several possibilities, <lb/>or when the identification points to different contents of a volume<lb/>or when the identification is conjectured.<lb/>Element Content<lb/>Date Read<lb/>Author in boldface<lb/>Translator and/or editor, if any, in boldface<lb/>Title, complete so far as possible, in italics<lb/>Date of first publication, so far as that is available or applicable<lb/>Comment, if any<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1683">
                  <seg type="reference">Goldsmith, p. 89-209 (<ref target="/diary/1808-01-24.html">1808-01-24</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify with certainty. Possibly the following, first recorded in WG’s diary on  <date when="1807">1807-09</date>-01:<lb/> 
                  <author>Goldsmith, Oliver</author>  
                  <title>An history of the earth, and animated nature.</title> (8 volumes)  <date when="1774">1774</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1685">
                  <seg type="reference">Lilienwald, pt I (<ref target="/diary/1808-02-19.html">1808-02-19</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1686">
                  <seg type="reference">Gibbon, Ch. II (<ref target="/diary/1808-02-21.html">1808-02-21</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Gibbon, Edward</author>  
                  <title>Critical observations on the sixth book of the Aeneid.</title>  
                  <date when="1770">1770</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Gibbon, Edward</author>  
                  <title>The history of the decline and fall of the Roman empire.</title>  
                  <date when="1776">1776-88</date>
                  <lb/> Both of these were previously recorded in WG’s diary, <title>Critical observations</title> on  <date when="1795">1795-04</date>-23 and <title>Decline and fall</title> on  <date when="1798">1798-10</date>-10. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1687">
                  <seg type="reference">Bevis (<ref target="/diary/1808-02-23.html">1808-02-23</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify with certainty. Possibly the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Author unknown</author>  
                  <title>Bevis of Hampton or Beure de Hanstone</title> (uniform title)   or <title>In all the londes of crystyente</title> (variant title)  <date when="1500">1500</date>
                  <lb/>Based on a 12<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century Anglo-Norman chanson de geste ‘Beure de Hanstone’ (ESTC)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1688">
                  <seg type="reference">Misson, apud Pirates (<ref target="/diary/1808-03-05.html">1808-03-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Johnson, Charles (pseudonym)</author>  
                  <title>General history of the pyrates, from their first rise and settlement in the island of Providence, to the present time. With the remarkable actions and adventures of the two female pyrates Mary Read and Anne Bonny, contain’d in the following chapters … Chap. I. Of Capt. Avery. II. Of Capt. Martel. III. Of Capt. Teach…. The 4</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title> edition…. By Captain Charles Johnson.</title>  
                  <date when="1726">1726</date>[-28]<lb/> 
                  <title>Volume II: The history of the pyrates, containing the lives of Captain Misson, Captain Bowen, Captain Kidd…. By Capt. Charles Johnson.</title> [ <date when="1728">1728</date>]<lb/>Captain Misson appears only in second volume of the fourth edition.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1690">
                  <seg type="reference">Apollonius Rhodius, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-03-27.html">1808-03-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Apollonius Rhodius</author> (b. ca. 280 B.C.)  <title>Argonautica.</title> date unknown<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1691">
                  <seg type="reference">Lutrin, C. I (<ref target="/diary/1808-04-05.html">1808-04-05</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Boileau Despréaux, Nicolas</author> ‘Lutrin, poëme heroique,’<lb/> in <title>Oeuvres diverses du sieur D*** avec le Traité du sublime ou du merveilleux dans le discours, traduit du grec de Longin.</title>  
                  <date when="1674">1674</date>
                  <lb/>Contents: Satires, I-IX – Discours sur la satire – Epistres, I-IV – L’art poëtique, en vers – Lutrin, poëme heroique –Epistre a Monsieur de Guilleragues – Traité du sublime – Remarques<lb/>English first edition:<lb/> 
                  <author>Boileau Despréaux, Nicolas</author>  
                  <author>N. O. (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Le Lutrin, an heroick poem, written originally in French by Monsieur Boileau. Made English by N.O.</title>  
                  <date when="1682">1682</date>
                  <lb/>WG probably read the following edition:<lb/> 
                  <author>Boileau-Despréaux, Nicolas</author>  
                  <title>Oeuvres de M. Boileau Despréaux. </title>(3 volumes)  <date when="1757">1757</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Boileau, ses Oeuvres, 3 vols, Paris,  <date when="1757">1757</date> (item 67).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1692">
                  <seg type="reference">Betham, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-04-17.html">1808-04-17</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1694">
                  <seg type="reference">Lauder (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-08.html">1808-05-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work with certainty. The following coincide with WG’s interests at this time:<lb/> 
                  <author>Laudér, William</author>  
                  <title>An essay on Milton’s use and imitation of the moderns in his Paradise lost. With some observations on the Paradise regain’d.</title>  
                  <date when="1741">1741</date>
                  <lb/>Also published in  <date when="1750">1750</date>.<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Laudér, William</author>  
                  <title>A letter to the Reverend Mr. Douglas: occasioned by his Vindication of Milton; to which are subjoined several curious original letters from the authors of Universal history, Mr. Ainsworth, Mr. Maclaurin, &amp;c. By William lauder, A.M.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Lauder, George</author>  
                  <title>On the most horrid and terrible treason … committed upon the sacred person of … Charles … King of Great Britain, France, and Ireland, &amp;c. by a base crue of cursed conspirators. [In verse. Signed: G. L. i.e. George Lauder.]</title>  
                  <date when="1649">1649</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Lauder, Alexander</author>  
                  <title>The ancient bishops consider’d; both with respect to the extent of their jurisdiction, and nature of their power. In answer to Mr. Chillingworth and others. Wherein the conformity of the government and discipline of the Church of Scotland, with that of the ancient church, is fully manifested: and it is made evident, that the ministers of the gospel … are not presbyters but bishops … By Alexander Lauder.</title>  
                  <date when="1707">1707</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1695">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Wilkes, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-08.html">1808-05-08</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific work with certainty. Possibly one of the following recent publications:<lb/> 
                  <author>Wilkes, John</author>  
                  <author>Almon, John (editor)</author>  
                  <title>The correspondence of the late John Wilkes: with his friends, printed from the original manuscripts, in which are introduced memoirs of his life</title>. (4 volumes)  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Wilkes, John</author>  
                  <title>Letters, from the year  <date when="1774">1774</date> to the year  <date when="1796">1796</date>, addressed to his daughter, the late Miss Wilkes: with a collection of his miscellaneous poems, to which is prefix’d a memoir of the life of Mr. Wilkes.</title>  
                  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1696">
                  <seg type="reference">Yates’s Bury (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-09.html">1808-05-09</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Yates, Richard</author>  
                  <title>An illustration of the monastic history and antiquities of the town and abbey of St. Edmund’s Bury.</title>  
                  <date when="1805">1805</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1697">
                  <seg type="reference">Sydney (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-11.html">1808-05-11</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify with certainty.  Possibly the following work, since WG is reading the Sydney papers on  <date when="1808">1808-06</date>-14.<lb/> 
                  <author>Collins, Arthur (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Henry, Sir</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Philip, Sir</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Robert</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Robert, Earl of Leicester</author>  
                  <title>Letters and memorials of state: in the reigns of Queen Mary, Queen Elizabeth, King James, King Charles the First, part of the reign of King Charles the Second, and Oliver’s usurpation.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1746">1746</date>
                  <lb/>Binder’s title: Sydney’s memoirs<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Sidney’s (Alg.) Discourses concerning Government, 2 vol. Edinb.  <date when="1750">1750</date> (item 679)<lb/>Sidney (Alg.) Discourses concerning Government  <date when="1698">1698</date> (item 890)<lb/>Sidney’s (Alg.) Letters to the Honorable Henry Saville,  <date when="1679">1679-82</date>  
                  <date when="1742">1742</date> (item 680).<lb/>Sidney:--Memoirs of Algernon Sidney, by G. W. Meadley, port.  <date when="1813">1813</date> (item 681).<lb/>**Sidney Papers:--Journal of Robert Sidney Earl of Leicester, and Letters of Algernon Sidney, edited by Blencowe  <date when="1825">1825</date> (item 682).<lb/>as well as the following works by Sir Philip Sidney.<lb/>Sidney’s (Sir Philip) Memoirs, by Dean Zouch, port.  <date when="1808">1808</date> (item 819).<lb/>Sidney’s (Sir P.) Countess of Pembroke’s Arcadia  <date when="1598">1598</date> (item 888)<lb/>Sidney’s (Sir P.) Countess of Pembroke’s Arcadia  <date when="1674">1674</date> (item 889)<lb/>Sidney’s Letters and Memorials of State, edited by Arthur Collins, port. of Sir Philip Sidney, 2 vol.  <date when="1746">1746</date> (item 891).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1698">
                  <seg type="reference">&amp; Howel, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-11.html">1808-05-11</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Howell, James</author>  
                  <title>Epistolae Ho-Elinae: familiar letters, domestic and forren; divided into six sections, partly historicall, politicall, philosophicall, upon emergent occasions.</title>  
                  <date when="1645">1645</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Howell’s (James) Familiar Letters, port.  <date when="1726">1726</date> (item 312).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1699">
                  <seg type="reference">Donne’s Letters, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-19.html">1808-05-19</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Donne, John</author>  
                  <title>Letters to severall persons of honour.</title>  
                  <date when="1651">1651</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Donne (Jo.) Letters to several Persons of Honour  <date when="1651">1651</date> (item 381)<lb/>Another edition, portrait  <date when="1654">1654</date> (item 382)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1700">
                  <seg type="reference">Walton’s Herbert (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-22.html">1808-05-22</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Walton, Izaak</author>  
                  <title>The lives of Dr. John Donne, Sir Henry Wotton, Mr. Richard Hooker, Mr. George Herbert.</title>  
                  <date when="1670">1670</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Herbert, George</author>  
                  <author>Walton, Izaak</author>  
                  <title>The temple. Sacred poems and private ejaculations. By Mr George Herbert, late oratour of the University of Cambridge. Together with his life. With several additions.</title>  
                  <date when="1674">1674</date>
                  <lb/>Tenth edition, the first edition Walton had his hand in.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Donne, Wotton, Hooker, and Herbert, Lives of by I. Walton  <date when="1675">1675</date> (item 199).<lb/>Herbert’s (Geo.) Temple, Sacred Poems, with Life, port.  <date when="1679">1679</date> (item 288).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1701">
                  <seg type="reference">Corinna, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-05-25.html">1808-05-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Rochester, John Wilmot</author>  
                  <title>Corinna, or Humane frailty.</title>  
                  <date when="1699">1699</date> London: J. Nutt<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Staël, Germaine de</author>  
                  <author>Lawler, Dennis (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Corinna; or, Italy … Translated by D. Lawler. </title>(5 volumes)  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>In French:<lb/> 
                  <author>Staël, Germaine de</author>  
                  <title>Corinne ou l’Italie, par Mme de Staël-Holstein.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Rochester:--Poems, by John Wilmot, Earl of Rochester, four editions,  <date when="1699">1699</date>,  <date when="1701">1701-32</date>, and 57<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1702">
                  <seg type="reference">Donne, Meditations, &amp;c (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-01.html">1808-06-01</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Donne, John</author>  
                  <title>Deuotions vpon emergent occasions: and seuerall steps in my sicknes: digested into 1. Meditations vpon our humane conditions. 2. Expostulations, and debatements with God. 3. Prayers, vpon the seuerall occasions, to him.</title>  
                  <date when="1624">1624</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1703">
                  <seg type="reference">Fox, p. 27{,} fin. (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-05.html">1808-06-05</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific title.<lb/>Probably Charles James Fox, who died in  <date when="1806">1806</date>.  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1705">
                  <seg type="reference">Suckling, &amp;c. (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-12.html">1808-06-12</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Suckling, Sir John</author>  
                  <title>The works of Sir John Suckling: containing all his poems, plays, letters &amp;c. Published by his friends (from his own copies) to perpetuate his memory.</title>  
                  <date when="1676">1676</date>
                  <lb/>Each work in the collection has a separate title page, printed for H. Mosely, on various dates.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Suckling’s (Sir J.) Poems, Letters, and Plays, 2 vol.  <date when="1770">1770</date> (item 703).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1706">
                  <seg type="reference">Carew (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-13.html">1808-06-13</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Carew, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Poems, songs, sonnets, together with a masque.</title>  
                  <date when="1670">1670</date>: 4<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> edition revised and enlarged.<lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Carew’s (Tho.) Poems, Songs, and Sonnets, with Masque, Manuscript notes  <date when="1772">1772</date> (item 107)<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1708">
                  <seg type="reference">Sydney papers, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-14.html">1808-06-14</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Collins, Arthur (editor)</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Henry, Sir</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Philip, Sir</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Robert</author>  
                  <author>Sidney, Robert, Earl of Leicester</author>  
                  <title>Letters and memorials of state: in the reigns of Queen Mary, Queen Elizabeth, King James, King Charles the First, part of the reign of King Charles the Second, and Oliver’s usurpation.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1746">1746</date>
                  <lb/>Binder’s title: Sydney’s memoirs<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1709">
                  <seg type="reference">Clarendon, p. 44 (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-25.html">1808-06-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>The history of the rebellion and civil wars in England, begun in the year  <date when="1641">1641</date>. With the precedent passages, and actions, that contributed thereunto, and the happy end, and conclusion thereof by the King’s blessed restoration, and return upon the 29</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title> of May, in the year  <date when="1660">1660</date>. Written by the Right Honourable Edward Earl of Clarendon, late Lord High Chancellour of England, Privy Counsellour in the reigne of King Charles the First and the Second. </title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1702">1702-4</date> 
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>State papers collected by Edward, Earl of Clarendon: commencing from the year  <date when="1621">1621</date>: containing the materials from which his History of the great rebellion was composed.</title> (3 volumes)  <date when="1767">1767-1786</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>The history of the rebellion and civil wars in England: Begun in the year  <date when="1641">1641</date>. With the precedent passages, and actions, that contributed thereunto, and the happy end, and conclusion thereof by the King’s blessed restoration, and return upon the 29</title>
                  <hi rend="italic superscript">th</hi>
                  <title> of May, in the year  <date when="1660">1660</date>
                  </title>. (4 volumes)  <date when="1702">1702-1759</date>
                  <lb/>The fourth volume, dated  <date when="1759">1759</date>, is titled:<lb/> 
                  <title>The life of Edward Earl of Clarendon, Lord High Chancellor of England, and Chancellor of the University of Oxford. Containing 1. An account of the Chancellor’s life from his birth to the restoration in  <date when="1660">1660</date>. II. A continuation of the same, and of his History of the grand rebellion, from the restoration to his banishment in  <date when="1667">1667</date>. Written by himself. Printed from his original manuscripts, given to the University of Oxford, by the heirs of the late Earl of Clarendon</title>.  <date when="1759">1759</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Clarendon’s History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England and Ireland, 8 vol.  <date when="1721">1721</date> (item 138).<lb/>Clarendon’s (Edw. Earl of) State Papers, 3 vol. Oxford,  <date when="1767">1767-86</date>) (item 435).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1710">
                  <seg type="reference">Mark Noble, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-06-30.html">1808-06-30</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Noble, Mark</author>  
                  <title>The lives of the English regicides.</title>  
                  <date when="1798">1798</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Noble, Mark</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of several persons and families, who, by females are allied to, or descended from, the protectorate-house of Cromwell; chiefly collected from original papers and records. To which is added, a catalogue of such Persons who were raised to honors or great employments by the Cromwells; with the lives of many of them.</title>  
                  <date when="1784">1784</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Noble’s (Mark) Memoirs of the Protectorate House of Cromwell, ports. 2 vol. Birm.  <date when="1787">1787</date> (item 573).<lb/>Noble’s (Mark) Lives of the English Regicides, Manuscript notes, 2 vol.  <date when="1798">1798</date> (item 574).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1711">
                  <seg type="reference">Tandy, pp. 138 (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-17.html">1808-07-17</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Tandy, James</author>  
                  <title>An appeal to the public, by James Tandy, Esq.; containing a statement of his unjust and severe imprisonment, the different examinations which took place before the Privy Council, with various memorials, and letters to government, etc. and in which several distinguished characters are deeply involved.</title>  
                  <date when="1807">1807</date> 
                  <lb/>Conjecture based partly on page numbers and partly on topic.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1712">
                  <seg type="reference">Hargrave, p. 182 (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-18.html">1808-07-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify specific title. Possibly WG is consulting the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Hargrave, Francis (editor)</author>  
                  <title>A complete collection of state-trials, and proceedings for high-treason, … the fourth edition; commencing with the eleventh year of the reign of King Richard II. and ending with the sixteenth year of the reign of King George III. … To which is prefixed, a new preface, by Francis Hargrave.</title>  
                  <date when="1776">1776-81</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1714">
                  <seg type="reference">Lamb’s Specimens, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-24.html">1808-07-24</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Lamb, Charles</author>  
                  <title>Specimens of English dramatic poets, who lived about the time of Shakespeare: with notes.</title>  
                  <date when="1808">1808</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Lamb’s (Charles) Specimens of English Dramatic Poets coeval with Shakespeare  <date when="1808">1808</date> (item 475).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1715">
                  <seg type="reference">Revenger, act 1, 2 (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-25.html">1808-07-25</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Tourneur, Cyril</author>  
                  <title>The Revenger’s Tragaedie. In four acts in prose and verse. By Cyril Tourneur.</title>  
                  <date when="1607">1607</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1716">
                  <seg type="reference">Neal, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-27.html">1808-07-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Neal, Daniel</author>  
                  <title>The history of the Puritans or Protestant non-conformists, from the reformation to the death of Queen Elizabeth: with an account of their principles; their attempts for a further reformation in the church; their sufferings; and the lives and characters of their principal divines …</title> (4 volumes)  <date when="1732">1732-38</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Neal (Dan.) History of the Puritans, or the Protestant Nonconformists, 5 vol.  <date when="1822">1822</date> (item 570).<lb/>WG’s History of the Commonwealth lists:<lb/>Daniel Neal. Puritans (1: 55).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1717">
                  <seg type="reference">Baxter, p. 20 (<ref target="/diary/1808-07-27.html">1808-07-27</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Baxter, Richard</author>  
                  <title>Reliquiae Baxterianae: or, Mr. Richard Baxter’s narrative of the most memorable passages of his life and times. Faithfully published from his own original manuscript by Matthew Sylvester.</title>  (1 volume in three parts)  <date when="1696">1696</date>
                  <lb/>Variant title: Life of the reverend Mr. Richard Baxter. The third part.<lb/>WG’s Commonwealth lists:<lb/>Richard Baxter. Life of Baxter by Himself (1: 52).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1718">
                  <seg type="reference">Semiramis (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-06.html">1808-08-06</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Voltaire, François-Marie Arouet</author>  
                  <title>La Tragédie de Sémiramis et quelques autres pièces de littérature</title>.  <date when="1749">1749</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1719">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of Swift, p. 143 (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-09.html">1808-08-09</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following first recorded on  <date when="1801">1801-06</date>-30:<lb/> 
                  <author>Sheridan, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The life of the Rev. Dr. Jonathan Swift, Dean of St. Patrick’s, Dublin. By Thomas Sheridan.</title>  
                  <date when="1784">1784</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Orrery, John Boyle, Earl of</author>  
                  <title>Remarks on the life and writings of Dr. Jonathan Swift, dean of St. Patrick’s, Dublin; in a series of letters from John earl of Orrery to his son, the Honourable Hamilton Boyle.</title>  
                  <date when="1752">1752</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists:<lb/>Sheridan’s (T.) Life of Dean Swift, port.  <date when="1787">1787</date> (item 676).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1721">
                  <seg type="reference">Maugraby, pp. 221 (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-14.html">1808-08-14</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chavis, Denis</author>  
                  <author>Cazotte, Jacques</author>  
                  <title>Arabian tales; being a continuation of the Arabian nights entertainments. Consisting of one thousand one stories, told by the Sultaness of the Indies. Translated from the Arabian manuscript into French, by Dom Chavis and M. Cazotte and now translated into English from the last French edition…</title> (4 volumes)  <date when="1792">1792</date> Edinburgh: Mudie<lb/>OR (possibly a variant title)<lb/> 
                  <author>Chavis, Denis</author>  
                  <author>Cazotte, Jacques</author>  
                  <author>Heron, Robert (translator)</author>  
                  <title>Arabian tales: or a continuation of the Arabian nights entertainments: consisting of stories related by the Sultana of the Indies to divert her husband from the performance of a rash vow. Newly translated from the original Arabic into French, by Dom Chavis, a native Arab, and M. Cazotte. And translated from the French into English, by Robert Heron.</title>  (4 volumes)  <date when="1792">1792</date> Edinburgh: Bell and Bradfute etc.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1722">
                  <seg type="reference">Augustus, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-18.html">1808-08-18</ref>)
                    </seg>Probably:<lb/> 
                  <author>Blackwell, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of the court of Augustus. By Thomas Blackwell…</title>  
                  <date when="1753">1753-55</date>
                  <lb/>This work was continued and finished by John Mills:<lb/> 
                  <author>Blackwell, Thomas</author>  
                  <author>Mills, John</author>  
                  <title>Vol. I-II. Memoirs of the court of Augustus, by Thomas Blackwell, … Vol. III. Memoirs of the court of Augustus, continued and completed from the original papers of the late Thomas Blackwell, … by John Mills, …</title>  
                  <date when="1760">1760-1763</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s sale catalog lists: Blackwell’s (T.) Memoirs of the Court of Augustus, 3 vol.  <date when="1760">1760</date>. <lb/>Note: During the latter part of  <date when="1808">1808</date>, WG records ‘Augustus, çala,’ ‘Blackwell,’ and ‘Augustus,’ the last followed by page numbers in a way that suggests he is writing something on Augustus. We record both ‘Blackwell’ and ‘Augustus, çala’ among the titles WG read, since he customarily used ‘çala’ to record his reading.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1723">
                  <seg type="reference">Tim. Thomas, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-28.html">1808-08-28</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Chaucer, Geoffrey</author>  
                  <author>Thomas, Timothy</author>  
                  <title>The works of Geoffrey Chaucer: compared with the former edit	ions, and many valuable mass. out of which, three tales are added which were never before printed; by John Urry. Together with a glossary by … [Timothy Thomas]. To the whole is prefixed the Author’s life [b the Rev. John Dart, corrected and enlarged by William Thomas] … and a preface … [by Timothy Thomas].</title>  
                  <date when="1721">1721</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Epictetus</author>  
                  <author>Thomas, Timothy</author>  
                  <title>The manual of Epictetus’s Morals attempted in English verse by T. T. …</title>  
                  <date when="1744">1744</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1724">
                  <seg type="reference">W Abbey, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-31.html">1808-08-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Widmore, Richard</author>  
                  <title>An history of the church of St. Peter, Westminster, commonly called Westminster Abbey: chiefly from manuscript authorities.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>WG’s biography of Chaucer cites:<lb/>Widmore, History of Westminster Abbey (2:550).<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1725">
                  <seg type="reference">Four Plays, Pt I, II (<ref target="/diary/1808-08-31.html">1808-08-31</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Boyle, Roger, Earl of Orrery</author>  
                  <title>Four new plays: Viz. The history of Henry the fifth, Mustapha, The black prince, and Tryphon.  As they were acted by His Majesties servants, and His Highness the Duke of York’s. Written by the Right Honourable the Earl of Orrery.</title>  
                  <date when="1670">1670</date>
                  <lb/>This title has two parts, each having two plays.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1726">
                  <seg type="reference">Lysons, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-09-11.html">1808-09-11</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly:<lb/> 
                  <author>Lysons, Daniel</author>  
                  <title>The environs of London: being an historical account of the towns, villages, and hamlets, within twelve miles of that capital; interspersed with biographical anecdotes. By the Rev. Daniel Lysons, A.M. F.R.S. Chaplain to the Right Hon. the Earl of Orford. … . County of Surrey.</title> (4 volumes)  <date when="1792">1792</date>[- <date when="1796">1796</date>]<lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Lysons, Daniel</author>  
                  <title>An historical account of those parishes in the county of Middlesex, which are not described in The envrions of London. By the Rev. Daniel Lysons, M.A. F.R.S &amp; E.S.A.</title>  
                  <date when="1800">1800</date>
                  <lb/>Conjecture based on WG’s recent travel to Reading.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1727">
                  <seg type="reference">Read Lefanu (<ref target="/diary/1808-10-03.html">1808-10-03</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Lefanu, Alicia</author>  
                  <title>Lucy Osmond.</title>  
                  <date when="1803">1803</date>
                  <lb/>OR<lb/> 
                  <author>Lefanu, Elizabeth Sheridan</author>  
                  <title>The India voyage. By Mrs. H. Lefanu, daughter of the late Thomas Sheridan.</title> (2 volumes)  <date when="1804">1804</date>
                  <lb/> NOTE:  The Juvenile Library published Alicia Lefanu’s poem <title>Rosara’s Chain</title> in  <date when="1812">1812</date>, and WG writes to A Lefanu in  <date when="1811">1811</date>.  This may provide some grounds to believe WG read her  <date when="1803">1803</date> novel.  (However, WG also visits a Mrs. Lefanu in  <date when="1800">1800</date>, who may be Mrs. H. Lefanu.)  Since Lefanu’s name is coupled with that of Lamb on  <date when="1808">1808-10</date>-03, and since Lamb is writing for the Juvenile Library at this time, we may wish to conjecture that WG is reading a piece submitted for the JL. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1729">
                  <seg type="reference">Cevallos, pp. (<ref target="/diary/1808-10-12.html">1808-10-12</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify with certainty. The most recent of the possible titles is the following:<lb/> 
                  <author>Cevallos, Pedro</author>  
                  <title>An exposure of the arts and machinations which led to the usurpation of the crown of Spain, and of the means pursued by Bonaparte to carry his views into effect: to which are annexed documents to substantiate every assertion. Translated from the Spanish of Pedro Cavallos; revised and edited by John Joseph Stockdale.</title>  
                  <date when="1808">1808</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1730">
                  <seg type="reference">Class-Book, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-10-23.html">1808-10-23</ref>)
                    </seg>Unable to identify.<lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1731">
                  <seg type="reference">Life of sir Thomas Pope, pp. 258 (<ref target="/diary/1808-10-23.html">1808-10-23</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Wharton, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>The life of sir Thomas Pope, founder of Trinity College Oxford: chiefly compiled from original evidences by Thomas Wharton.</title>  
                  <date when="1772">1772</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1732">
                  <seg type="reference">Woolston, çala (<ref target="/diary/1808-10-30.html">1808-10-30</ref>)
                    </seg>Possibly the following item, annotated as a possible reading on  <date when="1792">1792-08</date>-21.<lb/> 
                  <author>Woolston, Thomas</author>  
                  <title>Discourses on the miracles of our saviour, in view of the present controversy between infidels and apostates.</title>  
                  <date when="1727">1727-29</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1733">
                  <seg type="reference">Nourjahad, pp. 239 (<ref target="/diary/1808-12-13.html">1808-12-13</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Sheridan, Frances</author>  
                  <title>The history of Nourjahad. By the editor of Sidney Bidulph.</title>  
                  <date when="1767">1767</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1734">
                  <seg type="reference">Bidulph; p. 110 (<ref target="/diary/1808-12-15.html">1808-12-15</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Sheridan, Frances</author>  
                  <title>Memoirs of Miss Sidney Bidulph.</title>  
                  <date when="1761">1761</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="te1735">
                  <seg type="reference">B Thoughtless, p. 60 (<ref target="/diary/1808-12-29.html">1808-12-29</ref>)
                    </seg> 
                  <author>Haywood, Eliza</author>  
                  <title>The history of Miss Betsy Thoughtless. In four volumes.</title>  
                  <date when="1751">1751</date>
                  <lb/>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>