<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Conference</title>
                <principal>Mark Philp</principal>
                <funder>Leverhulme Foundation and the John Fell OUP Research Fund</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Published by the Godwin Diary Project, University of Oxford</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born Digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-09-09">
                <persName>Dr James Cummings</persName> created this file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <head>The Godwin Diary: Reconstructing London's Culture 1788-1836</head>

            <p><ref
                    target="http://godwindiary.politics.ox.ac.uk/conference/Con_Inv_Call_for_Paper_website.pdf"
                    >Full conference details</ref>
                <ref target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/web/help/help_pdf.asp"><graphic
                        url="/images/pdficon_small.gif" /></ref>
            </p>
            <p><ref target="http://godwindiary.politics.ox.ac.uk/conference/programme.pdf"
                    >Programme</ref>
                <ref target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/web/help/help_pdf.asp"><graphic
                        url="/images/pdficon_small.gif"/></ref></p>
            <p rend="bold italic"> Registration is now closed </p>
            <p>On 23-24 July 2010 the Leverhulme sponsored research project responsible for editing
                the diary of William Godwin held a two-day conference to introduce scholars to
                the new resource and to explore how that resource provides a distinctive light on
                our understanding of late eighteenth and early nineteenth century social and
                political culture. The conference will take place at the Department of Politics
                &amp; International Relations, Manor Road, Oxford. The Godwin Diary conference will
                mark the culmination of three years' effort to edit the diary and publish a digital
                and fully searchable edition. Accompanying the searchable text will be a complete
                scan of the original diary </p>
            <p>The conference organizers have invited a number of speakers but would also welcome
                proposals for paper from those interested in exploring the light that the resource
                can shed on their own research interests. Those speaking include: John Barrell,
                Luisa Calé, Julie Carlson, Greg Claeys, Pamela Clemit, Beth Lau, Jon Mee, Jane
                Moody, and Philip Schofield. </p>
            <p>We should state at the outset that the conference format, and the nature of the
                papers presented, is a little unusual. The objective of the conference is to launch
                the diary website and to illustrate its potential as a research tool for the study
                of the period 1788- 1836. It is not, therefore, a 'Godwin conference' but is
                concerned with how the diary illuminates various aspects of London's cultural and
                material worlds with particular emphasis on the manifold networks of relationships
                that Godwin mapped in his diary. Accordingly, papers should focus on the
                contribution Godwin's Diary might make to some of their own research interests. To
                enable people to do this the Godwin team will provide speakers with access to the
                Diary in advance of the conference. Moreover, rather than expecting people to write
                extensive papers on their research areas we are asking for short contributions of
                just 10 minutes. Our belief is that this will prove an attractive format that will
                allow a very wide range of issues to be discussed during the two days and will give
                some indication of the immense richness of the resource as a research tool. Our hope
                is that scholars will find attractive the idea of brief papers about particular
                topics that link the Diary to their research interests and indicate its
                contribution. The Bodleian has agreed that a collection of the papers will be
                published in a special issue of the Bodleian Library Record. </p>
            <p>We plan to have sessions on publishing culture, theatre, lives and deaths,
                sociability, visual culture, and radicalism. There will also be a panel on the
                practice of diarykeeping. We will offer a hands-on session navigating the diary and
                exploiting its search mechanisms. The conference will also, in conjunction with the
                Bodleian Library, host an exhibition of the diary and other key manuscripts from the
                Godwin-Shelley archive (Abinger Collection). It is also planned to stage the world
                premiere of Godwin's MS tragedy, St Dunstan (1790)! </p>
            <p>Those attending the conference will get access to the diary before its full launch in
                Autumn 2010 as we hope to improve the resource after feedback from users. An outline
                plan of the conference and its different sessions is appended below, along with
                suggested topics (other topics are welcome). Those interested in contributing are
                asked to indicate the panel which they believe is most appropriate and to provide a
                brief paragraph outlining their research interest and what they would hope to
                discuss in their paper (no more than 300 words). This should be sent to the project
                e-mail address (below) by 1 October 2009. </p>
            <p><ref
                    target="http://godwindiary.politics.ox.ac.uk/conference/Con_Inv_Call_for_Paper_website.pdf"
                    >Full conference details</ref>
                <ref target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/web/help/help_pdf.asp"><graphic
                        url="/images/pdficon_small.gif"/></ref>
            </p>
            <p> Contact: <ref target="mailto:godwin.diary@politics.ox.ac.uk"
                    >godwin.diary@politics.ox.ac.uk</ref>
            </p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
