<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI
   xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>William Godwin's Diary </title>
        <title type="sub">Reconstructing a Social and Political Culture 1788-1836</title>
        </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Published by the William Godwin's Diary project, University of Oxford</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>William Godwin's Diary</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      
      <divGen type="twitterFeed"/>
      <div rend="indented">
        <p>Welcome to the <ref target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/index.php/news/william-godwins-diary-wins-award.html">award-winning</ref> 
	   digital edition of the diary of William Godwin (1756-1836). Godwin’s
          diary consists of 32 octavo notebooks. The first entry is for <ref target="/diary/1788-04-06.html">6 April 1788</ref> and the final
          entry is for <ref target="/diary/1836-03-26.html">26 March 1836</ref>, shortly before he died. The diary is a resource of immense
          importance to researchers of history, politics, literature, and women’s studies.  It
          maps the radical intellectual and political life of the late eighteenth and early
          nineteenth centuries, as well as providing extensive evidence on publishing relations,
          conversational coteries, artistic circles and theatrical production over the same
          period.  One can also trace the developing relationships of one of the most important
          families in British literature, Godwin’s own, which included his wife Mary
          Wollstonecraft (1759-1797), their daughter Mary Shelley (1797-1851) and his son-in-law
          Percy Bysshe Shelley (1792-1822). Many of the most important figures in British cultural
          history feature in its pages, including Anna Barbauld, Samuel Taylor Coleridge, Charles
          James Fox, William Hazlitt, Thomas Holcroft, Elizabeth Inchbald, Charles and Mary Lamb,
          Mary Robinson, Richard Brinsley Sheridan, William Wordsworth, and many others.</p>
        <p>The diary has been transcribed and encoded so that the data it contains is able to be extract. High
          resolution scanned images of the diary are also provided. 
There is also a series of podcasts available on "<ref target="http://podcasts.ox.ac.uk/series/judgement-and-justice-life-and-diary-william-godwin">Judgement and Justice: The Life and Diary of William Godwin</ref>".</p>
        <p>Those new to the resource are encouraged to refer to the  
          <ref target="/introduction.html">Introduction to the Resource</ref> and to the section about <ref target="/introduction.html#Searching">searching</ref> the site. The diary
         is part of the Abinger Collection of manuscripts held in the Bodleian Library. For further details, see <ref target="/abinger.html">Abinger Collection</ref>. Further 
          detailed work on people appearing in the Diary, that draws on diverse genealogical resources, has 
          been undertaken by Edward Pope and is posted on his website: <ref target="http://www.edpopehistory.co.uk/">http://www.edpopehistory.co.uk/</ref>. This is a source of invaluable material, 
          not all of which has been included or cross referenced here, and users of the Diary are strongly advised to consult it.</p>
        
        <p>If you have questions, comments or suggestions on the 
  website feel free to send them to: <ref target="mailto:godwin.diary@politics.ox.ac.uk">godwin.diary@politics.ox.ac.uk</ref>.  You may also follow <ref target="http://www.twitter.com/godwindiary">@godwindiary</ref> on twitter for excerpts from the diary. In early 2012 the website won the <ref target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/index.php/news/william-godwins-diary-wins-award.html">annual award for Digital Resources</ref> from the <ref target="http://www.bsecs.org.uk/">British Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies</ref>.  
</p>
      </div>
      <div rend="logos">
	      <p rend="logos">
		      <ref rend="noStyle" target="http://www.politics.ox.ac.uk/">
			      <graphic url="/images/dpir-small.jpg">
				      <desc>Logo of the Department of Politics and International Relations</desc></graphic>
		      </ref>
		      <ref rend="noStyle" target="http://www.leverhulme.ac.uk/">
		      <graphic url="/images/leverhulme-small.jpg">
				      <desc>Logo of The Leverhulme Trust</desc></graphic>
		      </ref>
		      <ref rend="noStyle" target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/">
		      <graphic url="/images/bodleian.jpg">
				      <desc>Logo of the Bodleian Libraries</desc></graphic>
		      </ref>
		      <ref rend="noStyle" target="http://www.oucs.ox.ac.uk/">
		      <graphic url="/images/oucslogo.jpg">
				      <desc>Logo of the Oxford University Computing Services</desc></graphic>
		      </ref><ref rend="noStyle" target="http://www.bsecs.org.uk/">
		      <graphic url="/images/bsecs_logo.gif">
				      <desc>Logo of the British Society for Eighteenth-Century Studies</desc></graphic>
		      </ref>

</p>

      </div>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
