<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Introduction to the resource</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published by the William Godwin's Diary project, University of Oxford</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>William Godwin's Diary</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div xml:id="Searching" rend="indented">
                <head>Searching the resource</head>
                <p>The project has sought to code the diary so as to retain the richness and
                    diversity of the information. Each element in a day’s entry has been coded so as
                    to distinguish what Godwin read, what he wrote, whom he saw, where he saw them,
                    in what activities or meals they shared, and where he went. It is possible,
                    then, to search for dates, for particular people, for activities, for texts
                    written or read, for events attended, and so on. In the display of the diary
                    transcription many textual elements appear as blue hyperlinks and some (unidentified people) are
                    underlined; the colouring and underlining can be hidden by unchecking the 'Formatting' box. </p>
                <p>Because Godwin’s entries are cryptic, judgments have been made throughout the
                    coding process as to what particular entries mean. Also, Godwin is often
                    inconsistent in the way he spells or abbreviates people’s names, the titles of
                    works he is writing, and those he is reading. Using the <ref target="/search.html">search</ref> facility for
                    ‘Holcroft’ will identify all instances where he enters ‘Holcroft’ in the diary.
                    But it will not reveal the huge number of cases in which he contracts Holcroft
                    to ‘Ht’ or variations thereof. Nor does this facility currently allow ‘fuzzy’
                    searching. However, the underlying coding does allow variants to be recognised
                    as instances of the same name if searched for under PEOPLE. As a result, when
                    searching names, we strongly recommend searching both with the open SEARCH
                    facility, and in the People section under ‘<ref target="/people/">People (identified)</ref>’. The former will search for the name as it appears in the diary and in
                    the editorial matter while the latter will search by the underlying coding,
                    rather than by the exact spelling. Users may also find the CTRL+F search
                    function on a PC or the Command+F search function on a Mac helpful on some pages
                    of the resource.</p>
                <p>The aim of the editorial apparatus has been to clarify Godwin’s entries and to
                    provide additional information that will allow the user to pursue their inquiry
                    further. In the attempt to identify the ~64,000 name entries in the diary we have
                    created files for about 1,110 people and families, which say something about
                    well over three quarters of the total name entries. Where there is a lack of
                    certainty we have indicated what possibilities there are and the reasoning we
                    have used in making an identification, usually based on the particular social
                    contexts for that entry and/or other primary and secondary sources. Biographical
                    information is offered for those identified but where those individuals appear
                    in the <ref target="http://www.oxforddnb.com/"><title>Oxford Dictionary of National
                        Biography</title></ref>, we have kept this to a minimum. We have generally excluded
                    spouses from our identifications unless 1) the spouse is of independent
                    historical interest or 2) Godwin had a significant relationship with them
                    independent of the primary figure (but see also the comments under <ref
                        target="#Abbreviations">Abbreviations and names</ref> for more complex
                    cases). We have prioritized the identification of those who appear frequently in
                    the diary, those we deemed important to Godwin, and those we thought would be of
                    interest to a general audience. These principles have not been followed
                    rigidly as identifications often flowed organically (identifying one person in a
                    group often leads to the identification of others). Users will have further
                    information we lacked and we welcome feedback on our judgments and further
                    information about people and entries in the diary. The editorial matter and
                    coding of the diary will be updated on a regular basis over the first year of
                    public access, and intermittently thereafter.</p>
                <p>Users of the diary are strongly encouraged to consult <ref
                        target="#Abbreviations">Abbreviations and names</ref>
                </p>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="Abbreviations" rend="indented">
                <head>Abbreviations and names</head>
                <p>Godwin uses abbreviations throughout the diary but especially when referring to
                    people, and he has a range of shorthand entries that qualify what he has
                    written. The abbreviations for people are many and various: He almost wholly
                    refuses to add the second consonant of any name ending in a double consonant.
                    For example: Thelwall is always Thelwal; Crosdill is always Crosdil, except when
                    Godwin records his death!</p>
                <p>Just as Holcroft becomes ‘Ht’, many others in the diary are contracted to the
                    first and last letters of their names <emph>but they are not consistently
                        contracted </emph>– Godwin can move back and forward between full spellings
                    and contractions; he can also use initials rather than contractions; and he can
                    use the same initials or contractions for different people – so M stands for
                    Marshall, but also for his daughter Mary at one period of her life. Women are
                    more likely to be contracted than men, but certainly not exclusively so. People
                    can also be referred to by, or, more precisely, their presence may be inferred
                    from, a place name. For instance, when Godwin becomes intimate with Mary
                    Wollstonecraft the entry truncates her to ‘chez elle’ or ‘chez moi’. Another
                    example is John Philpott Curran being referred to for much of Godwin’s visit to
                    Ireland in <ref target="/diary/1800.html">1800</ref> as ‘Rathfarnham’ (where Curran lived in Dublin). In addition, we
                    have recognised a problem with Godwin’s referencing, particularly of meals and
                    the presence of the host and spouse or other family member. For example, Godwin
                    dines frequently at Charles Lamb’s. Except when Mary Lamb was in hospital, she
                    would likely be present and active at the dinner, as is testified by letters and
                    diaries from the period and yet Godwin makes no reference to her presence.  The
                    same is true for many other couples. Accordingly, we have taken the editorial
                    decision to presume the presence of significant others when Godwin calls for
                    meals but only mentions the host and <emph>when that significant other has an
                        individual code</emph>.  In some cases this will overstate their presence –
                    we do not know exactly when Mary Lamb was in hospital.  For other couples there
                    is less risk of over-stating the spouse’s presence.  However, when Godwin records an entry such as 'call
                    on Lamb' (as against 'call on Lambs') we have treated this more narrowly and coded only for the named
                    person.</p>
                <p>A complication of the abbreviations is the fluctuating degree of intimacy that
                    Godwin has with people. This can be particularly difficult to unpick when people
                    share surnames and more so again when it is a common surname. Godwin felt that
                    he had no need to distinguish in his diary between various ‘Smiths’ or ‘Taylors’
                    who appear throughout the diary, but it seems clear from context that different
                    people are being recorded. In other words, ‘Smith’ in <ref target="/diary/1792.html">1792</ref> is someone different
                    to ‘Smith’ in <ref target="/diary/1802.html">1802</ref>. Often context can help make an identification but
                    occasionally there is no context (e.g. ‘Call on Smith’).</p>
                <p>Names are usually given without initials. Women’s names may first appear prefixed
                    with Miss or Mrs, but this is not invariably so; and that prefix may then be
                    replaced by an initial or discarded altogether. Those given initials may lose
                    them; those without may gain them, and may lose them again. Even when people
                    with the same surname are involved in Godwin’s circles in the same period,
                    Godwin does not systematically distinguish different people by using
                    initials.</p>
                <p>For ‘nah’, ‘nit’, ‘adv’ and other abbreviations relating to calls and meetings
                    see <ref target="#Calls">Calls</ref>.</p>
            </div>



            <div xml:id="Calls" rend="indented">
                <head>Calls</head>
                <p>Godwin indicates when he calls on others and when they call on him. Entries may
                    be followed, usually in superscript by nah, na, nit, or n. These mean that
                    Godwin does not in fact see them – because they are ‘not at home’, ‘not
                    available’, ‘not in town’, or simply not there. Similarly, callers on Godwin may
                    be recorded with similar notes when Godwin is out or when he does not see them.
                    When looking at an individual person record under <ref target="/people/"
                        >People</ref> users will find results that indicate how many of the calls
                    the person makes on Godwin or Godwin makes on them and of these calls how many
                    do not result in an actual meeting. This example illustrates an important
                    principle of searching the diary: appearance in the diary does not automatically
                    constitute a physical encounter between Godwin and an individual. An individual
                    can appear in the diary as an unsuccessful call, as a topic of conversation, as
                    a correspondent, in a paratextual list, as a death, in an entry where Godwin
                    notes meetings between two or more others where he was not himself present, and
                    so on. In each case the entry is not a contact. Users are directed to be careful
                    in distinguishing actual physical encounters with Godwin from these types of
                    diary entries. </p>
                <p>Moreover, users should note that there are some ‘meetings’ whose nature cannot be
                    determined and that there is a grey area as to what constitutes a physical
                    encounter in any case. When Godwin attended, for instance, the trial on Thomas
                    Hardy on <ref target="/diary/1794-11-01.html">1 November 1794</ref>, he wrote ‘see <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/wharton.html">Wharton</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/thomson.html">Thomson</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/walker.html">Walker</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/roberts%20m..html">Roberts M.</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/VAU01.html">Vaughan</ref>, <ref target="/people/HAR01.html"
                        >Harwood</ref>, <ref target="/people/FRO01.html">Frost</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/WIL19.html">Williams</ref>, <ref target="/people/BAN03.html"
                        >Banks</ref>, <ref target="/people/SHA01.html">Sharp</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/FER01.html">Ferguson</ref>, <ref target="/people/SYM01.html"
                        >Symonds</ref>, <ref target="/people/TOW01.html">Towers</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/MOO06.html">C. Moore</ref>, <ref target="/people/MOO04.html"
                        >G. Moore</ref>, <ref target="/people/unidentified/hawes.html">Hawes</ref>,
                        <ref target="/people/RIT01.html">Ritson</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/gray.html">Gray</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/WEB01.html">Webb</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/unidentified/belmano.html">Belmano</ref>, <ref
                        target="/people/MAC03.html">Macdonald</ref>’. It seems improbable that he
                    spoke to all of these but likely he did with some. Does a wave across a crowded
                    courtroom, a nod in the queue to gain entry, or the recognition of someone on
                    the other side of the room constitute a meeting? The editors have taken take the
                    view that all encounters treated by Godwin as a meeting should be acknowledged
                    as a meeting. While it may be tempting to assume that meetings recorded by
                    Godwin as ‘see’ are not actual physical encounters, this is not borne out by
                    considering the use of ‘see’ in the diary as a whole, so there is no distinct
                    subcategory of meetings systematically distinguished from other subcategories,
                    where Godwin sees but does not meet people. </p>
                <p>Within each person’s file, there is an option to explore the meals and meetings
                    they had with Godwin in more detail. A chronological list is offered of all
                    meals and meetings in which the person features. The user has the opportunity to
                    narrow the encounters listed by category (meal or meeting), subcategory (type of
                    meeting or meal), venue, or number of participants. The user may also determine
                    which meetings the subject of their search attended with other specified
                    persons. For example, if searching for Coleridge, one can then view just the
                    meetings at which Coleridge and Wordsworth appear together and distinguish
                    within those any n/nah/nit instances Godwin notes. One can search for meetings
                    of up to four people (excluding Godwin): for example, if one wanted to see if
                    Godwin, Coleridge, Wordsworth, Charles Lamb, and Thomas De Quincey ever got
                    together, the diary records one such encounter (tea at Coleridge’s on <ref target="/diary/1808-03-03.html">3 March
                    1808</ref>). Where we have been unable to identify a person who appears in a meeting,
                    the person’s name will be marked by an asterix.</p>
                <p>When Godwin records calling on a number of people in one entry (call on X, Y, and
                    Z), these calls have been treated as a sequence of individual calls. Similarly,
                    when Godwin records a number of people calling on him (X, Y, and Z call), these
                    have been treated as a sequence of individual calls. The project recognizes that
                    in some cases people may be calling ensemble but there is sufficient evidence
                    that the individual approach is most accurate with some exceptions noted
                    below.</p>
                <p>When Godwin records calling with someone on others (call, with X, on Y &amp; Z),
                    his companion is deemed to be present at both meetings. However, when Godwin
                    records an entry such as ‘Call on X &amp; Y with Z’, Z is treated as being at
                    the latter meeting only.</p>
                <p>Most meetings are clear – people call on Godwin, or he calls on them, although
                    the etiquette of calling is complex (see, for example, the discussion in Leonore
                    Davidoff’s <emph>The Best Circles: Society Etiquette and the Season</emph> –
                    although this is based on slightly more formal contexts). </p>
                <p>The most complex meeting in the diary is the frequently used ‘adv.’ which, from
                    two entries in <ref target="/diary/1792.html">1792</ref> where Godwin spells it out in full, we know to be a
                    contraction of ‘advenae’. The word ‘advena’ (plural ‘advenae’) is something of a
                    rarity in Latin, being a first-declension noun with an ‘-a’ ending, which is
                    usually feminine but here of indeterminate gender, i.e. potentially masculine,
                    feminine or neuter. The standard dictionary of classical Latin (Lewis &amp;
                    Short) defines its primary meaning as ‘one who comes to a place’, but then ‘a
                    foreigner, stranger, or alien’. Godwin uses the term to indicate that he
                    unexpectedly encountered the person at a meal or meeting or at an event. Meals
                    may involve a number of people with whom Godwin dines, followed by ‘adv’ and
                    another list. This suggests that the former were part of an arranged dinner, and
                    the latter call on the host either during or after dinner.</p>
                <p>When Godwin records a number of people encountered ‘adv’ the individuals have
                    been grouped collectively. Although this differs from our principle of recording
                    other types of meetings such as calls individually, the adv encounter functions
                    as a subset to a wider meeting/meal/activity and as such we have taken the view
                    that individuals listed as adv encounters are more likely to encounter each
                    other within the physical and social confines of the broader
                    meal/meeting/activity’s parameters. The same assumption has been made about
                    participants of an ‘au soir’ meeting who are also grouped collectively.</p>
                <p>We have also indicated when people function as a venue for a call. This is worth
                    noting not only for the light shed on Godwin’s relationship with the individual
                    (for example, if Godwin calls many times on them but this is not reciprocated,
                    this suggests a particular kind of relationship) but for the light shed on
                    non-Godwin relationships . If, for example, Godwin only meets X when he is
                    visiting Y, then it may suggest that there is a relationship between X and Y
                    that is noteworthy. Users should consider the effect that Godwin’s age, income,
                    marital status would have on the patterns of calling and dining. </p>

            </div>



            <div xml:id="Meals" rend="indented">
                <head>Meals</head>
                <p>Godwin is reasonably consistent in identifying meals at which he meets others. ‘X
                    dines’ means what it says; X dines, means that X is Godwin’s guest. It is likely
                    that meals at which Godwin is the host may include meals in inns or coffee
                    houses that Godwin hosts, as well as those in his own home, but we have no way
                    of knowing this for certain. The range of meals: breakfast, dinner, tea, supper
                    are self-explanatory, although readers may wish to refer to scholarly
                    discussions of dining practices in late eighteenth and early nineteenth-century
                    London (see <ref target="/project-bibl.html">bibliography</ref>) The editors
                    have been careful to record each type of meal separately as distinct types
                    suggest a certain level of intimacy which is very useful in mapping changes over
                    time in Godwin’s relationship with people, or indeed, in the relationships
                    between other people in the diary. </p>

            </div>





            <div xml:id="List1796" rend="indented">
                <head>1796 List</head>
                <p>The diary’s editorial matter refers frequently to the '<ref target="/diary/1796list.html">1796 list</ref>'. The 1796 list
                    is a series of names and dates that Godwin inserted into the last few pages of
                    his diary notebook for February 1795-September 1796. He compiled the list –
                    probably in 1805 – to map the growth and range of his acquaintance over the
                    years 1773-1805. In some cases the names are underlined, probably an indication
                    that the relationship was one Godwin considered particularly important. One of
                    the pages is of particular interest as Godwin selects twenty-five names from his
                    main chronological list and puts them in order of when he made their
                    acquaintance. It seems probable that Godwin here lists those twenty-five people
                    he considered most significant to his life and is interested in thinking about
                    either the longevity of those relationships or how the sequence of meeting
                    matters or both. ‘Significant’ here has a deliberate (and inescapable) ambiguity
                    as the list excludes, for example, Mary Wollstonecraft. Other names have then
                    been added in the margins, which suggests that Godwin revisited this list
                    subsequently to note other important relationships. The <ref target="/diary/1796list.html">list</ref> appears after the
                    entry for <ref target="/diary/1796-09-24.html">24 September 1796</ref>.</p>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="Reading" rend="indented">
                <head>Reading</head>
                <p>Godwin was a voracious reader right up until he died. He noted in his unfinished
                    autobiography that when he was a student at Hoxton Academy he would rise at 5am
                    and read until midnight and the passion for reading never left him. Although the
                    diary commences in <ref target="/diary/1788.html">1788</ref>, he does not record his daily reading until <ref target="/diary/1791.html">1791</ref> when
                    the diary becomes more detailed. </p>
                <p>There are various subcategories of reading. The overwhelming majority of entries
                    may be found under ‘Texts Read’. Other entries can be found under ‘Cala’ which
                    is when Godwin browses through a text ‘ça et la’; ‘Discussed’ where it appears
                    that Godwin discusses a text with someone or reads a work aloud; ‘Texts
                    Mentioned’ where Godwin refers to a text but is not reading it (e.g. borrowing a
                    book); and ‘Letter Received’ where Godwin notes the receipt of correspondence
                    (which he does not do consistently, since many extant letters do not correspond
                    to an entry in the diary, and for many entries in the diary there is no extant
                    letter).</p>
                <p>The aim has been to identify the author (and where applicable translator/editor),
                    full title, and first publication date for each item.  There has been no
                    concerted attempt to identify the specific edition that Godwin read.  However,
                    information from the sale catalogue of his library has been provided, as well as
                    notations on his readings in the British Museum (now the British Library), which
                    may serve scholars in tracing specific editions.  Occasionally, we have noted
                    reprints and later editions available to Godwin, especially where his diary
                    explicitly states that he is using a specific edition.</p>
                <p>The annotations follow a specific sequence.  Each item reproduces the entry from
                    Godwin’s diary, with the date of the entry.  In the annotation, the name of the
                    author (and where applicable translator/editor) is given in boldface, with title
                    in italics below author, and with publication date in roman after.  Comments
                    stand below the bibliographical information.  Because there are many
                    inconsistencies in how titles are recorded in our sources, we have followed the
                    practice of capitalizing only the first word of title, subtitle, proper names,
                    and personal titles such as ‘Earl’.  Spelling has not been modernized unless the
                    source has modernized it.</p>
                <p>Given Godwin’s cryptic entries, absolutely certain identification has not always
                    been possible.  We have therefore in many cases supplied a brief comment to show
                    the basis of confidence.  When we wished to draw attention to the issue of
                    confidence, we have used the following indicator words: <list>
                        <item>a. ‘probably,’ </item>
                        <item>b. ‘possibly’ (often applied where several candidate identifications
                            are equally possible),  </item>
                        <item>c. ‘unable to identify with certainty’ (usually applied to the title
                            by an identified author),</item>
                        <item>d. and ‘unable to identify’ (applied to both author and title).
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </p>
                <p>The basis of confidence in an identification rests on one or more of the
                    following:  Godwin’s own footnotes in published works (though these are
                    sometimes cryptic), listing in his sale catalogue, identification by previous
                    scholars, likelihood from the paucity of alternative candidates, previous
                    mention in the diary, similar topics of works read within the same time period,
                    and already read works by the same author.</p>
                <p>It has not been possible to check the title pages of all the works Godwin read,
                    especially in their first editions.  For some authors, we have consulted
                    available scholarly editions that give publication dates and titles of first
                    editions or single-author bibliographies.  In an initial search of many items,
                    we have consulted the extensive listing in WorldCat, but since the recording of
                    titles in this source is not always accurate or consistent, we have followed up
                    by consulting listings in the English Short Title Catalogue (ESTC), the British
                    Library Integrated Catalogue, the catalogue of the UCLA Libraries, and the
                    catalogue of the Bibliothèque nationale de France.  We have also found valuable
                    aid in identifying authors in the <emph>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</emph>. A
                    full list of the sources consulted may be seen in the bibliography.</p>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="Writing" rend="indented">
		<head>Writing</head>
                <p>Godwin wrote almost every morning. His rate of composition varied but he usually
                    managed 2-5 pages per day. Users can view Godwin’s writing activities by date,
                    by type of activity or with reference to the writing of particular texts. </p>
                <p>The editors have distinguished Godwin’s different writing activities according to
                    his own nomenclature so the user can see writing activity under ‘Transcribe’,
                    Translate’, ‘Correct’ and so on. The editors have further incorporated indirect
                    writing activities such as ‘Meditate on Writing’, ‘Notes Made’ and ‘Invent’ so
                    that users can get a comprehensive view of Godwin’s writing process.</p>
                <p>Searching by text allows the user to see all writing activities, direct and
                    indirect, that have been assigned to a particular text, both published and
                    unpublished, completed and incomplete.</p>
                <p>When Godwin engages in two different activities on one text (for example, ‘Pol.
                    Justice, 3pp; revise), they have been treated as two separate activities. When
                    he records the completion of a text, it has been coded as a standard ‘write’
                    entry. </p>
            </div>


            <div xml:id="Health" rend="indented">
                <head>Health</head>
                <p>Godwin kept fastidious diary records of his personal health problems, concerns,
                    and moments of well-being. He maintained discretion when recording some of the
                    more sensitive aspects of his health, generally referring to these issues in
                    Latin or French. Godwin has been diagnosed, at various times, as suffering from
                    haemorrhoids and constipation, and might have also had a form of rectal cancer
                    (see St Clair). Another frequent issue is his ‘delerium’ or ‘deliquium’, which
                    has been described by William St Clair as fits sometimes accompanied by
                    vomiting. Latin and French words have been translated, and using context or
                    various sources we have attempted to indicate what Godwin might have meant by
                    some of the health phrases he utilised. Self-explanatory health issues such as
                    ‘fever’ or ‘constipation’ have not been annotated, nor have conjectures been
                    made about ambiguous or uncertain symptoms or treatments such as ‘syringe’ –
                    noted on <ref target="/diary/1792-11-09.html">9</ref> and <ref target="1792-11-10">10 November, 1792</ref> – to cite one such example. When
                    searching for health complaints, users should keep in mind that Godwin often used his own <emph>sui
                    generis</emph> methods of spelling – for example, ‘headache’ is sometimes noted as
                    ‘head ach’ or ‘head-ach’ and sometimes ailments have been abbreviated (such as
                    ‘constip’ for constipation’).</p>
            </div>


            <div xml:id="Topics" rend="indented">
                <head>Topics</head>
                <p>Godwin occasionally recorded topics of conversation in his diary. It is unclear
                    why he records some conversations and not others although one may presume that
                    it was because he felt the conversation or the interlocutor was worthy of note.
                    It is also true that he records the topics of conversations more frequently in
                    the mid-1790s than either before or after.</p>
            </div>



            <div xml:id="Events" rend="indented">
                <head>Events</head>
                <p>Godwin goes to the theatre and concerts, attends lectures, notes trials and
                    parliamentary and public events, registers personal events, keeps track of the
                    weather and temperature, and visits libraries and gardens. Editorial notes
                    identify these events in the diary and provide background information about
                    them. In the open ‘Search’ editorial matter is kept distinct from the diary, but
                    each may be searched. Place names are also recorded in the diary, and entries
                    relating to visits and activity outside London are also noted.</p>

            </div>


            <div xml:id="Formatting" rend="indented">
                <head>Formatting and Script</head>
                <p>Most of the diary entries are written in Godwin’s fluent italic script in black
                    pen. However, many public events are entered below the day’s entry and are
                    written in red ink. Moreover, in a relatively small number of entries additions
                    have been made in pencil. Also, there are a number of cases where Godwin seems
                    to be adding names to a meeting after the initial diary entry, resulting in
                    names appearing in the side margins. Finally, Godwin occasionally enters dates
                    wrongly and does not always retroactively correct them; and sometimes it looks
                    as if he is compiling the diary from sets of notes, which leads him to make
                    transcription mistakes, which he then rectifies by crossings out. In each case,
                    we have tried to signal in the transcript that there is something distinctive
                    about the entry, so as to encourage readers to check the transcribed entry
                    against the scan of the manuscript.</p>

            </div>

            <div xml:id="ShortTitles" rend="indented">
                <head>Short Titles</head>
                <p>The editors have had frequent and grateful recourse to the work of Godwin
                    biographers Don Locke, Peter Marshall, and William St Clair. They are referred
                    to in brief by surname in the editorial matter; full information is available in
                    the <ref target="/project-bibl.html">bibliography</ref>.</p>

            </div>



        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
