<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About the Leverhulme Trust</title>
                <principal>Mark Philp</principal>
                <funder>Leverhulme Foundation and the John Fell OUP Research Fund</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Published by the Godwin Diary Project, University of Oxford</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born Digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-09-09">
                <persName>Dr James Cummings</persName> created this file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>History</head>
                <p>The Victorian businessman and entrepreneur, William Hesketh Lever first brought
                    his exceptional creativity and energy to the manufacture and marketing of
                    Sunlight Soap which only a decade after its launch was being sold in 134
                    countries. </p>
                <p>Lever extended his business activities in ways that both served and profited from
                    the rapid rise of a mass market for basic consumer products. From the earliest
                    days, he was also a philanthropist, supporting a variety of educational,
                    religious, civic, community, and medical causes. His achievements were
                    recognized in 1922 when the title of Lord Leverhulme of the Western Isles was
                    conferred upon him. </p>
                <p>On his death in 1925, Lord Leverhulme left a proportion of his interest in the
                    company he had founded, Lever Brothers, in trust for specific beneficiaries: to
                    include first certain trade charities and secondly the provision of
                    "scholarships for the purposes of research and education". The Leverhulme Trust
                    was established. In the succeeding years, Lever Brothers became a cornerstone of
                    Unilever, one of the major multinational companies, created in 1930 by the
                    merger of Lever Brothers with the Van den Berghs margarine company of the
                    Netherlands. The Leverhulme Trust's shareholding thus became part of Unilever
                    plc. November 1983 saw an evolution in the arrangements for the two charitable
                    objectives. Subsequently, the Leverhulme Trust has been able to give
                    concentrated attention to research and education. </p>
                <p>One special element in Viscount Leverhulme's legacy is the request that the
                    Trustees all be drawn from the highest levels within Lever Brothers Ltd or now
                    from its descendant Unilever plc. The Trust is therefore led by a group of
                    colleagues with wide but self-consistent experience, with a high level of mutual
                    understanding and respect built up over many years, and with a full recognition
                    of the special qualities and achievement of the founder. The resulting culture
                    for decision-making is free from disciplinary special interest but fully alert
                    to the wide-ranging impact which research and education must make in modern
                    life. </p>
                <p>Throughout its history, the Trust has combined the direct initiatives of the
                    Trustees made in the light of specialist peer review advice together with a
                    portfolio of awards made by a Research Awards Advisory Committee, itself
                    comprising eminent research colleagues drawn predominantly from the academic
                    world. The tradition continues to the present day. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Today</head>
                <p>The Trust, established at the wish of William Hesketh Lever, the first Viscount
                    Leverhulme, makes awards for the support of research and education. The Trust
                    emphasises individuals and encompasses all subject areas. </p>
                <p>The Trustees place special weight on: <list>
                        <item>the originality of the projects put to them; </item>
                        <item>the significance of the proposed work; </item>
                        <item>the ability to judge and take appropriate risk in the project; </item>
                        <item>the removal of barriers between traditional disciplines. </item>
                    </list></p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
