<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Project Participation</title>
                <principal>Mark Philp</principal>
                <funder>Leverhulme Foundation and the John Fell OUP Research Fund</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Published by the Godwin Diary Project, University of Oxford</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born Digital</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2010-09-09">
                <persName>Dr James Cummings</persName> created this file.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
        <body>

            <p>Editing the diary to appropriate scholarly standards so as to realize its unique
                potential as a research resource for all those working on the literature, history,
                and politics of the period is a considerable labour. The diary contains thousands of
                names, some of which are immediately recognizable, some of which are much more
                difficult to identify. For example, by the end of the 1790s Godwin was seeing
                something in the order of 140 different people a month (about half of whom were new
                or relatively new contacts). This figure probably does represent a peak, and there
                are certainly troughs when Godwin was working intensively on major projects, but
                throughout his long life, his remarkable sociability ensured he remained connected
                to an astonishingly wide range of people from London’s literary, artistic,
                scientific, political and cultural circles. </p>
            <p>Godwin’s participation in a wide range of different social and cultural networks
                suggests that editing his diary is a task that is particularly suited to
                collaborative consultation. We hope that by inviting scholars from across the
                disciplinary spectrum we will be able to identify the more obscure entries and that
                the unique perspective into Georgian London over a period of nearly fifty years the
                diary affords will be as penetrating as possible. The creation of such a scholarly
                network is essential to the project’s success. </p>
            <p>Our intention is to have an occasional newsletter from January 2008 in which we will
                report on progress and raise problems as we encounter them. Contributors will be
                asked to respond to those queries which pertain to their particular area of
                expertise. We anticipate that the queries will largely be concerned with individuals
                whose identity is uncertain and we will provide information that we hope will help
                an expert provide a more certain identification. Such information might include: the
                number of times this person appears in the diary; the dates of those appearances;
                how the name is denoted (sometimes Godwin varies the way he records individuals due
                to developing degrees of intimacy); the location of the meetings between Godwin and
                the individual (private residence, theatre); and the other people present at the
                meeting. From this fragmentary information, it is hoped that experts in other fields
                of interest and periods might be able to suggest possible identifications. See <ref
                    target="/example.html">this
                example diary entry</ref>. </p>
            <p>The Diary project is working closely with a separately funded project, the OUP
                edition of Godwin's letters, edited by Pamela Clemit (Durham University). This is a
                long-term project which will be published in six volumes. For the duration of the
                Diary project we will be asking people for help in identifying names and other
                elements in the Diary. Similar problems will arise with the Letters and in many
                cases these will overlap with problems for the Diary. We are hoping that those who
                wish to subscribe to the Diary network will also be willing to be consulted on
                aspects of the Letters and we would roll queries relating to the Letters into the
                newsletter. </p>
            <p>In all cases, those providing information will be thanked formally in the
                introduction to the website and/or the relevant volume of the edition, as
                appropriate. They will also be invited to attend a launch conference for the Diary
                in Oxford in 2010-11. It is hoped that the availability of both the Diary and the
                Letters will stimulate further research into Godwin and his circle by other
                scholars. </p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
