<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial team and acknowledgements</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published by the William Godwin's Diary project, University of Oxford</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>William Godwin's Diary</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div rend="indented">
                <p>The digitizing and editorial work on the project was funded by a Leverhulme Trust Major
                    Research Grant (2007-2010), with additional funding from the John Fell Fund at the
                    University of Oxford and from Pepperdine University, California. The British Academy
                    generously funded an international conference in Oxford on the project in July 2010. The
                    project team are grateful to the Bodleian Library for supporting the scanning of the
                    images.</p>
                <p>The project has been directed by David O’Shaughnessy and Mark Philp in the Department of
                    Politics and International Relations at the University of Oxford, and by Victoria Myers
                    in Pepperdine University, California. The website was designed and implemented by the 
                    project’s technical support officer, James Cummings at the 
		    Oxford University Computing Services at the University of Oxford. </p>
                <p>The project’s two research students were Kathryn Barush (Wadham College, Oxford) and
                    James Grande (Linacre College, Oxford). </p>
                <p>In addition, supplementary research work has been undertaken in Oxford by David Fallon
                    (St Anne’s College, Oxford), Hannah Simpson (St Hilda’s College, Oxford), Hannah Philp
                    (Cheney School, Oxford), Ruth Turvey (University College London), and in California by
                    Laura Kalinkewicz, Brent Russo and Vinnie Oliveri (Pepperdine University). The project 
                    is also deeply grateful to Edward Pope for his extensive contributions to the website 
                    drawing on his work on the Abinger Collection, the National Archive, and a wide range of 
                    archival and genealogical resources.  </p>
                <p>Richard Ovenden, Bruce Barker-Benfield, and Wilma Minty of the Bodleian Library, and Pat
                    Boreham, Genevieve Garrido, Kate Candy and Esther Byrom at the Department of Politics,
                    Jim Richardson at the Manor Road Building, have worked closely with the team throughout
                    the course of the project. Alfred Andrew Fote also provided technical support in
                    California. Pamela Clemit, who has been working in parallel on an edition of Godwin’s
                    letters to be published by Oxford University Press, generously shared her time and
                    expertise. Beth Lau played a critical role in initiating and directing the transcription
                    of the diary before this project began. The staff at UCLA’s Special Collections Library,
                    Law Library, and the Young Research Library, and those at the Henry E. Huntington
                    Library in California, provided invaluable support.</p>
                <p>Members of the project’s Advisory Board and participants at its <ref target="http://godwindiary.politics.ox.ac.uk/conference/">conference</ref> (Oxford, July
                    2010) have also contributed widely to the editorial work of the project. We would
                    especially like to thank: </p>
                <p>Robert Anderson, Judith Barbour, John Barrell, Gail Bederman, Stephen Burley, Lionel
                    Burman, Julie A. Carlson, Linda Clark, Nora Crook, Catherine Delafield, Martin
                    Fitzpatrick, Amy Garnai, Kevin Gilmartin, Katherine Gleadle, Robert Godwin, Christopher
                    Goulding, Isobel Grundy, John Halstead, Gary Handwerk, Maurice Hindle, Neil Hitchen, Joanna Innes, John
                    Issitt, Elizabeth Kraft, Robert Maniquis, Jon Mee, Tilottama Rajan, Glynis Ridley,
                    Sharon Ruston, Michael Scrivener, Tom Snjiders, William St Clair, and Tim Whelan. </p>
                
            </div>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
